<recipe class1="beverages"><p>In the first place, then, the French coffee is <ingredient>coffee,</ingredient> and not chickory, or rye, or beans, or peas. In the second place, it is freshly roasted, whenever made--roasted with great care and evenness in a little revolving cylinder which makes part of the furniture of every kitchen, and which keeps in the aroma of the berry. It is never overdone, so as to destroy the coffee-flavor, which is in nine cases out of ten the fault of the <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> we meet with. Then it is ground, and placed in a <implement>coffee-pot</implement> with a filter through which, when it has yielded up its life to the <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> poured upon it, the delicious extract percolates in clear drops, the <implement>coffee-pot</implement> standing on a heated stove to maintain the temperature. The nose of the <implement>coffee-pot</implement> is stopped up to prevent the escape <pb n="188" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=amwh&#38;PageNum=200"/> of the aroma during this process. The extract thus obtained is a perfectly clear, dark fluid, known as 



<purpose rend="italic">caf&#233; noir, or black coffee.</purpose>



It is black only because of its strength, being in fact almost the very essential oil of coffee. <variation>A table-spoonful of this in <ingredient>boiled milk</ingredient> would make what is ordinarily called a strong cup of <ingredient>coffee.</ingredient> The <ingredient>boiled milk</ingredient> is prepared with no less care. It must be fresh and new, not merely warmed or even brought to the boiling-point, but slowly simmered till it attains a thick, creamy richness. The <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> mixed with this, and sweetened with that sparkling <ingredient>beet-root sugar</ingredient> which ornaments a French table, is the celebrated 



<purpose rend="italic">caf&#233;-au-lait,</purpose>



the name of which has gone round the world.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages"><p>"Take particular care of the 



<purpose><alt synonym1="baby formula"><emph rend="italic">food</emph> of an infant.</alt></purpose>



If it is nourished by the mother, her own diet should be simple, nourishing, and temperate. If the child be brought up 'by hand,' the <ingredient>milk of a new-milch cow,</ingredient> mixed with one third <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and sweetened a little with <ingredient><emph rend="italic">white</emph> sugar,</ingredient> should be the only food given, until the teeth come. This is more suitable than any preparations of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> or <ingredient>arrowroot,</ingredient> the nourishment of which is too highly concentrated. Never give a child <emph rend="italic">bread, cake,</emph> or <emph rend="italic">meat,</emph> before the teeth appear. If the food appear to distress the child after eating, first ascertain if the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> be really from a new-milch cow, as it may otherwise be too old. Learn, also, whether the cow lives on proper food. Cows that are fed on <emph rend="italic">still-slops,</emph> as is often the case in cities, furnish <ingredient>milk</ingredient> which is very unhealthful."</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p>



<purpose><alt synonym1="to preserve apples, to preserve grapes, to preserve fruit">Apples, grapes, and such like fruit can be preserved in their natural state</alt></purpose>



by packing them when dry and solid in <ingredient>dry sand</ingredient> or <ingredient>saw-dust,</ingredient> putting alternate layers of <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> and <ingredient>cotton,</ingredient> saw-dust or sand. Some saw-dust gives a bad flavor to the <ingredient>fruit.</ingredient></p></recipe>



