<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">PLAIN CHOCOLATE</purpose>



For six people, use one quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> one tablespoonful of <ingredient>cornstarch,</ingredient> three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>hot water.</ingredient></p>



<p>Mix the <ingredient>cornstarch</ingredient> with one gill of the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Put the remainder of the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> on to heat in the 



<implement>double-boiler.</implement> When the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> comes to the boiling point, stir in the <ingredient>cornstarch</ingredient> and cook for ten minutes. Have the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> cut in fine bits, and put it in a <implement>small iron</implement> or <implement>granite-ware pan;</implement> add the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and place the pan over a hot fire. Stir constantly until the mixture is smooth and glossy. Add this to the hot <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and beat the mixture with a <implement>whisk</implement> until it is frothy. Or, the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> may be poured back and forth from the <implement>boiler</implement> to a pitcher, holding high the vessel from which you pour. This will give a thick froth. Serve at once.</p>



<p><variation>If you prefer not to have the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> thick, omit the cornstarch.</variation> <variation>If <ingredient>condensed milk</ingredient> is used, substitute <ingredient>water</ingredient> for the milk named above and add three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>condensed milk</ingredient> when the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> is added.</variation></p>



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">BREAKFAST COCOA</purpose>



<ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co,'s Breakfast Cocoa</ingredient> is powdered so fine that it can be dissolved by pouring <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> on it. For this reason it is often prepared at the table. A small teaspoonful of the powder is put in the cup with a teaspoonful of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> on this is poured two-thirds of a cup of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is added to suit the individual taste. This is very convenient; but cocoa is not nearly so good when prepared in this manner as when it is boiled.</p>



<p>For six cupfuls of <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> use two tablespoonfuls of the powder, two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and a pint and a half of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Put the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> on the stove in the <implement>double-boiler.</implement> Put the <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in a saucepan, and gradually pour the <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> upon them, stirring all the time. Place the saucepan on the fire and stir until the contents boil. Let this mixture boil for five minutes; then add the boiling <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and serve.</p>



<p>A gill of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is a great addition to this <ingredient>cocoa.</ingredient></p>



<p><variation><ingredient>Scalded milk</ingredient> may be used in place of boiled milk, if preferred.</variation> For flavoring, a few grains of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and a half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract</ingredient> may be added.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE CAKE</purpose>



For two sheets of cake, use three ounces of  <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1Chocolate,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one cupful and three-fourths of sifted <ingredient>pastry flour,</ingredient> one cupful and three-fourths of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a cupful of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> half a cupful of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient> one teaspoonful and a half of <ingredient>baking powder.</ingredient></p>



<p>Grate the <ingredient>chocolate.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and gradually beat in the <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Beat in the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> then the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> (already well beaten), next the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> and finally the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> in which the <ingredient>baking powder</ingredient> should be mixed. Pour into two well buttered shallow cake pans. Bake for twenty-five minutes in a moderate oven. Frost or not, as you like.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE ICING</purpose>



Make a <ingredient>vanilla icing</ingredient>, and add one tablespoonful of <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> to it. Scrape fine one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> and put it in a <implement>small iron</implement> or <implement>granite-ware saucepan,</implement> with two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>confectioner's sugar</ingredient> and one tablespoonful of <ingredient>hot water.</ingredient> Stir over a hot fire until smooth and glossy, then add another tablespoonful of <ingredient>hot water.</ingredient> Stir the dissolved <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> into the <ingredient>vanilla icing</ingredient>.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE SOUFFL&#201;</purpose>



Half a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Chocolate,</ingredient> three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one rounding tablespoonful of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></p>



<p>Put the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> in the <implement>double-boiler,</implement> and place on the fire. Beat the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to a <ingredient>soft cream,</ingredient> and beat the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into it. Gradually pour the <ingredient>hot milk</ingredient> on this, stirring all the time. Return to the fire and cook for six minutes. Put the <ingredient>shaved chocolate,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>water</ingredient> in a small pan over a hot fire, and stir until smooth and glossy. Stir this into the mixture in the <implement>double-boiler.</implement> Take from the fire and add the <ingredient>yolks of the eggs,</ingredient> well beaten; then set away to cool. When cool add the <ingredient>whites of the eggs,</ingredient> beaten to a stiff froth. Pour the batter into a well-buttered earthen dish that will hold about a quart, and cook in a moderate oven for twenty-two minutes. Serve immediately with <ingredient>vanilla cream sauce.</ingredient></p>



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">FORMULA FOR MAKING THREE GALLONS OF BREAKFAST COCOA</purpose>



<list><item>1/2 a pound of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Cocoa.</ingredient></item>



<item>1 1/2 gallons of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> hot,</item>



<item>1 1/2 gallons of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> hot.</item>



</list>



</p>



<p>This should not be allowed to boil. Either make it in a large <implement>double-boiler,</implement> or a large saucepan or kettle over water. Mix the <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> with enough <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> to make a paste, and be sure it is free from lumps. Heat together the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and pour in the <ingredient>cocoa;</ingredient> then cook at least an hour, stirring occasionally.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE FILLING</purpose>



<list><item>1 cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>



<item>Pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>



<item>1 1/2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>



<item>2 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient></item>



<item>2 <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> (<ingredient>yolks</ingredient>),</item>



<item>5 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> (level),</item>



<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>



</list>



</p>



<p>Put <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> in upper part of the <implement>double-boiler,</implement> and when hot and smooth, stir in the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> which has been mixed with enough <ingredient>cold milk</ingredient> to be thin enough to pour into the <ingredient>hot milk.</ingredient> Cook, stirring constantly, until it thickens; then let it cook eight or ten minutes. Mix the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> together and pour the hot mixture over them, stirring well; put back in <implement>double-boiler</implement> and cook, stirring constantly one minute. Remove, and when cool add one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA MARBLE CAKE</purpose>



<list><item>6 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>



<item>1 cup of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>



<item>3 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient></item>



<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>



<item>3/4 a cup of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item>



</list>



</p>



<p>Three level teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>baking powder,</ingredient> about one and three-quarter cups of <ingredient>sifted flour,</ingredient> or <ingredient>flour</ingredient> enough to make mixture stiff enough to drop from the spoon. Mix in the order given. Reserve one-third of this mixture and add to it four level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>Baker's Cocoa</ingredient> and to the other one cup of <ingredient>shredded cocoanut.</ingredient> Bake thirty-five or forty minutes according to size and shape of pan.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">PLAIN CHOCOLATE</purpose>



<list><item>1 ounce or square of <ingredient>Baker's Premium Chocolate,</ingredient></item>



<item>3 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>



<item>1/8 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>



<item>1 pint of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient></item>



<item>1 pint of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item>



</list>



</p>



<p>Place the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> in the <implement>agate chocolate-pot</implement> or saucepan, add the <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> and boil three minutes, stirring once or twice, as the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> is not grated. Add the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and allow it time to heat, being careful not to boil the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and keep it closely covered, as this prevents the scum from forming. When ready to serve turn in <implement>chocolate-pitcher</implement> and beat with <implement>Dover egg-beater</implement> until light and foamy.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA BUNS</purpose>



<list><item>2 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>



<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>



<item>1 <ingredient>egg,</ingredient></item>



<item>1/4 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>



<item>1 cup of scalded <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>



<item>2 compressed <ingredient>yeast cakes</ingredient> softened in</item>



<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient></item>



<item>1/4 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>extract cinnamon,</ingredient></item>



<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>Baker's Breakfast Cocoa,</ingredient></item>



<item>3 1/2 to 4 cups of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></item>



</list>



</p>



<p>Mix in order given, having dough as soft as can be handled, turn onto <implement>moulding board,</implement> roll into a square about an inch in thickness, sprinkle on one-half cup of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> fold the sides to meet the centre, then each end to centre, and fold again. Place in a bowl which is set in pan of warm water, let raise forty minutes. Shape, place in pan, let raise until doubled in size. Bake fifteen to twenty minutes. As you take from oven , brush the top with <ingredient>white of one egg</ingredient> beaten with one-half cup <ingredient>confectioners' sugar.</ingredient> Let stand five minutes. Then they are ready to serve.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MRS. BEDFORD'S CHOCOLATE CRULLERS</purpose>



Cream two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and one-half of a cupful of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> gradually add the beaten <ingredient>yolks of three eggs</ingredient> and one and one-half cupfuls more of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one cupful of <ingredient>sour milk,</ingredient> one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> grated and melted over <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> one-third of a teaspoonful of <ingredient>soda</ingredient> dissolved in one-half of a teaspoonful of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> the <ingredient>whites of the eggs</ingredient> whipped to a stiff froth, and sufficient <ingredient>sifted flour</ingredient> to make a soft dough. Roll out, cut into oblongs; divide each into three strips, leaving the dough united at one end. Braid loosely, pinch the ends together and cook until golden-brown in <ingredient>smoking-hot fat.</ingredient>--<attribution rend="italic">Mrs. Cornelia C. Bedford.</attribution></p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MRS. EWING'S CREAMY CHOCOLATE</purpose>



Mix together half a cup of <ingredient>sifted flour,</ingredient> half a cup of <ingredient>granulated sugar</ingredient> and half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Put into a saucepan half a cup of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 chocolate,</ingredient> finely shaved. Add one quart of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> stir until dissolved, add the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and boil gently, stirring constantly, five minutes. Then stir in a quart of <ingredient>boiling milk,</ingredient> and serve with or without <ingredient>whipped cream</ingredient>--<attribution rend="italic">By Mrs. Emma P. Ewing, author of "The Art of Cookery."</attribution></p>



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">PETITS FOUR</purpose>



Bake a simple, <ingredient>light sponge cake</ingredient> in a shallow biscuit tin or <implement>dripping pan,</implement> and when cold turn out on the <implement>moulding board</implement> and cut into small dominoes or diamonds. They should be about an inch in depth. Split each one and spread <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> or <ingredient>frosting</ingredient> between the layers, then ice tops and sides with different <ingredient>tinted icings,</ingredient> pale green flavored with <ingredient>pistachio,</ingredient> pale pink with <ingredient>rose,</ingredient> yellow with <ingredient>orange,</ingredient> white with <ingredient>almond.</ingredient> Little domino cakes are also pretty. Ice the cakes on top and sides with <ingredient>white icing</ingredient>, then when hard put on a second layer of <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> using <emph rend="italic">Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Unsweetened <ingredient>Chocolate</ingredient></emph> and made as for layer cake, dipping the brush in the <ingredient>melted chocolate</ingredient> to make the spots.</p>



<p>Candied violets, bits of <ingredient>citron</ingredient> cut in fancy shapes, <ingredient>candied cherries</ingredient> and <ingredient>angelica</ingredient> may all be utilized in making pretty designs in decoration.--<attribution rend="italic">American Housekeeper</attribution>.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">PEPPERMINTS, CHOCOLATE MINTS, Etc.<lb/>(Uncooked Fondant)</purpose>



<list><item><ingredient>White of 1 egg,</ingredient></item>



<item>2 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient></item>



<item><ingredient>Sifted confectioner's sugar,</ingredient></item>



<item>1/2 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>essence of peppermint</ingredient> or a few drops of <ingredient>oil of peppermint,</ingredient></item>



<item>1 or 2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>



<item><ingredient>Green color paste,</ingredient></item>



<item><ingredient>Pink color paste.</ingredient></item>



</list>



</p>



<p>Beat the <ingredient>egg</ingredient> on a plate, add the <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and gradually work in <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> enough to make a firm <ingredient>paste.</ingredient> Divide the <ingredient>sugar paste</ingredient> into three parts. To one part add the <ingredient>peppermint</ingredient> and a very little of the <ingredient>green color paste.</ingredient> Take the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> from the jar with a wooden tooth pick, add but a little. Work and knead the mixture until the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> is evenly distributed throughout. Roll the candy into a sheet one-fourth an inch thick, then cut out into small rounds or other shape with any utensil that is convenient. Color the second part a very delicate pink, flavor with <ingredient>rose extract</ingredient> and cut out in the same manner as the first. To the last part add one or two squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient> melted over <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and flavor with <ingredient>peppermint.</ingredient> Add also a little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> as the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> will make the mixture thick and crumbly. Begin by adding a tablespoonful of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> then add more if necessary, knead and cut these as the others.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">HOW TO COAT CANDIES, &#38; C.,<lb/>WITH BAKER'S "DOT" CHOCOLATE</purpose>



Half a pound of <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate</ingredient> will coat quite a number of candy or other "centers," but as depth of chocolate and an even temperature during the whole time one is at work are essential, it is well, when convenient, to melt a larger quantity of <ingredient>chocolate.</ingredient> When cold, the <ingredient>unused chocolate</ingredient> may be cut from the dish and set aside for use at a future time. If the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> be at the proper temperature when the centers are dipped in it, it will give a rich, glossy coating free from spots, and the candies will not have a spreading base. After a few centers have been dipped set them in a cool place to harden. The necessary utensils are a <implement>wire fork</implement> and a very small <implement>double boiler.</implement> The inner dish of the <implement>boiler</implement> should be of such size that the <ingredient>melted chocolate</ingredient> will come nearly to the top of it. Break the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> in small pieces and surround with <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> stir occasionally while melting. When the <ingredient>melted chocolate</ingredient> has cooled to about 80&#176; F. it is ready to use. Drop whatever is to be coated into the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> with the fork push it below the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> lift out, draw across the edge of the dish and drop onto a piece of table <implement>oil cloth</implement> or onto waxed paper. Do not let a drop of water get into the chocolate.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE PEANUT CLUSTERS</purpose>



Shell a quart of <ingredient>freshly-roasted peanuts</ingredient> and remove the skins. Drop the <ingredient>peanuts,</ingredient> one by one, into the center of a dish of <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate</ingredient> made ready for use; lift out onto <implement>oil cloth</implement> with a dipping fork (a <implement>wire fork</implement> comes for the purpose, but a <implement>silver oyster fork</implement> answers nicely) to make groups of three <ingredient>nuts,</ingredient>--two below, side by side, and one above and between the others.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE OYSERETTES,<lb/>PLAIN AND WITH CHOPPED FIGS</purpose>



<list><item><ingredient>Oyster crackers,</ingredient> salted preferred, fine-chopped, <ingredient>roasted peanuts</ingredient> or <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> or 3 or 4 basket <ingredient>figs</ingredient> or a little <ingredient>French fruit</ingredient> cut in very small bits.</item>



<item>1/2 a pound or more of <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>



</list>



</p>



<p>Select <ingredient>fresh-baked crackers</ingredient> free from crumbs. Dip in <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate,</ingredient> made ready as in previous recipes, and dispose on <implement>oil cloth</implement> or waxed paper. For a change add <ingredient>figs</ingredient> or other <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> cut very fine, or chopped <ingredient>nuts</ingredient> to the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> ready for dipping.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">PLAIN CHOCOLATE CARAMELS</purpose>



<list><item>2 1/2 cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>



<item>3/4 a cup of <ingredient>glucose,</ingredient> (<ingredient>pure corn syrup</ingredient>),</item>



<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>



<item>1/8 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient></item>



<item>2 1/2 cups of <ingredient>whole milk,</ingredient> (not skimmed),</item>



<item>2 1/2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>



<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract.</ingredient></item>



</list>



</p>



<p>Put the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>glucose,</ingredient> <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>cream of tartar</ingredient> and one cup of the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> over the fire, stir constantly, and when the mass has boiled a few moments, gradually stir in the rest of the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Do not let the mixture stop boiling while the milk is being added. Stir every few moments and cook to 248&#176; F., or, until when tested in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> a hard ball may be formed; add the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and beat them thoroughly through the candy, then turn it into two bread pans. When nearly cold cut into squares.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE BUTTER CREAMS</purpose>



<list><item>2 1/2 cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>



<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> </item>



<item>1/4 a cup of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient>,</item>



<item>1/4 a cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>



<item>2 1/2ozs. of <ingredient>Baker's Premium Chocolate,</ingredient></item>



<item>2 teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>



<item>1/2 a pound of <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>



</list>



</p>



<p>Put the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>water,</ingredient> <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> over the fire; stir until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is melted, then cook to the soft ball degree, or 236&#176; F.; pour on a damp marble and leave until cold; then pour on the <ingredient>Premium Chocolate,</ingredient> melted over <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and with a <implement>spatula</implement> turn to a <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> This process is longer than with the ordinary fondant. Cover the <ingredient>chocolate fondant</ingredient> with a bowl and let stand for thirty minutes; knead well and set over the fire in a <implement>double boiler;</implement> add the <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and stir until melted. The mixture is now ready to be dropped into small impressions in <ingredient>starch;</ingredient> when cold and brushed free of <ingredient>starch</ingredient> dip in <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient> When dropping the chocolate mixture into the <ingredient>starch</ingredient> it should be just soft enough to run level on the top. If too soft it will not hold its shape in coating.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE POP CORN BALLS</purpose>



<list><item>1 1/2 cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>



<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient>,</item>



<item>2/3 a cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>



<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient></item>



<item>3 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>



<item>3 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Premium Chocolate,</ingredient></item>



<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient></item>



<item>About 4 quarts of <ingredient>popped corn,</ingredient> well salted.</item>



</list>



</p>



<p>Set the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> over the fire, stir until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is melted, then wash down the sides of the saucepan, cover and let boil three or four minutes, then remove the cover and let cook without stirring to the hard ball degree; add the <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and stir constantly until brittle in <ingredient>cold water;</ingredient> remove from the fire and, as soon as the bubbling ceases, add the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> melted over <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>vanilla;</ingredient> stir, to mix the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> evenly through the candy, then pour onto the <ingredient>popped corn,</ingredient> mixing the two together meanwhile. With buttered hands lightly roll the mixture into small balls. Press the mixture together only just enough to hold it in shape. Discard all the hard kernels in the <ingredient>corn.</ingredient> Have the <ingredient>corn</ingredient> warm and in a warm bowl.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



