<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>An easy test <purpose>to distinguish between fresh butter and "process butter," and also oleomargarine,</purpose> is to boil a small amount, stirring thoroughly two or three times. <ingredient>Process butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>oleomargarine</ingredient> will boil noisily, sputtering more or less--like a mixture of grease and water--but will produce little or no foam. Genuine <ingredient>butter</ingredient> on the other hand boils with less noise and produces an abundance of foam.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose>To distinguish between process butter and oleomargarine,</purpose> melt a sample and note the odor--in <ingredient>process butter</ingredient> (and fresh butter) the "butyric acid" smell will be very noticeable, but it is absent from <ingredient>oleomargarine,</ingredient> a "meaty" odor taking its place.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose>When butter becomes rancid,</purpose> it is due to the formation of Butyric acid. A fair measure of freshness can be obtained by thoroughly washing it with <ingredient>fresh milk,</ingredient> which readily absorbs Butyric acid, and then with <ingredient>fresh water</ingredient> to remove the milk, so that it will not sour in the <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>The <purpose>perfumed butter</purpose> used in Paris is made by taking pats of <ingredient>"fresh" or unsalted butter</ingredient> and placing them on a layer of some variety of <ingredient>flowers,</ingredient> according to the perfume desired, a piece of muslin being laid between the butter and blossoms. Another layer of flowers is placed above the butter and then <ingredient>ice</ingredient> is added.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p>In places where cold storage is not available and circumstances warrant the trouble, <purpose><alt synonym1="to keep cabbage fresh" synonym2="to keep vegetables fresh, to keep celery fresh">cabbage of any kind, and several other vegetables, as celery, can be kept fresh for a considerable length of time</alt></purpose> by cutting so as to leave about two inches of stem below the leaves, scooping out the stem for from an inch to two inches, splitting the core of the <ingredient>vegetable</ingredient> to prevent sprouting, then suspending by a cord attached to the stem and each day filling the hollow part of the stem with fresh <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose>To keep cake fresh,</purpose> put an open vessel of <ingredient>water</ingredient> in the show-case. <variation><purpose><alt synonym1="to keep flies away from cake">To keep flies away,</alt></purpose> sprinkle <ingredient>cloves</ingredient> in it.</variation> Tin is the best receptacle.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>The <ingredient>shells of Edam or Pineapple cheese</ingredient> are useful <purpose>for serving macaroni.</purpose> Heat the shell in a moderate oven and pour in the (cooked) macaroni. If the <ingredient>macaroni</ingredient> is to be browned, set the filled shell in the oven again--this will, however, destroy the shell after three or four times.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages"><p><purpose>To keep new cider from fermentation,</purpose> <ingredient>powdered wood charcoal</ingredient> in the ratio of a pint to a barrel is recommended. Place in a cotton bag and suspend in the barrel.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages"><p>For the "old-fashioned" boiling method, the <ingredient>white of an egg</ingredient> is first stirred into the <ingredient>ground coffee.</ingredient> The latter is then placed in the pot and the proper amount of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> is poured over it--the water, taken fresh, having previously been allowed to boil hard for ten minutes. The <purpose>coffee</purpose> is permitted to come to a good boil, is stirred thoroughly once and then placed on the back of the stove for ten minutes. If any grounds appear on top, they are stirred a little and allowed to settle. This process gives excellent results but it requires a good deal of care.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><emph rend="italic">Preparation for the Table.</emph> In <purpose>preparing dried or evaporated fruits such as apples and peaches for the table,</purpose> the best results are attained by cooking slowly for several hours at a temperature just below the boiling point, enough <ingredient>water</ingredient> being added at first to cover the fruit. Every package of <ingredient>dried fruit</ingredient> should bear printed directions for making pies and for other forms of cooking, as very few housewives know how to use it to the best advantage.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose rend="bold">Boiling Eggs.</purpose> There are other ways of boiling <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> than by their immersion for a certain number of minutes in boiling water. A more pleasing result can be obtained,



<pb n="225" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=ency&#38;PageNum=233"/>



<illustration><caption>EGG PLANT</caption><description>A color illustration of a single whole eggplant and several horizontal slices of eggplant. An inlaid cut shows three rows of cultivated eggplants that have not yet been harvested.</description></illustration>



<pb n="226" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=ency&#38;PageNum=234"/>



<pb n="227" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=ency&#38;PageNum=235"/>



(1) by placing them in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and gradually bringing it to a boil, removing them when the boiling point has been reached, or <variation>(2) by placing them in <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> and then turning the gas flame out, or setting the pot well back on the range, removing the eggs in from seven to ten minutes.</variation> By either procedure, the white will be tender and jelly-like instead of the somewhat tough and leathery consistence of the ordinary boiled egg.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose rend="bold">FRENCH DRESSING:</purpose> a term applied to several receipts for simple salad dressings. The correct formula consists of four parts of <ingredient>olive oil</ingredient> to one part of good <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> with a small quantity of <ingredient>fine table salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>ground pepper</ingredient>--two saltspoonfuls of salt



<pb n="255" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=ency&#38;PageNum=263"/>



and one-half saltspoonful of pepper being in correct proportion when four tablespoonfuls of olive oil are used.</p>



<p>A little <ingredient>onion juice</ingredient> or chopped <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> <ingredient>tarragon,</ingredient> <ingredient>chives</ingredient> or <ingredient>chervil</ingredient> may be added if desired.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose>To properly boil ham,</purpose> first brush it off thoroughly to remove every particle of mold, soak for an hour in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and then wash thoroughly. Next, with a very sharp knife, shave off the hardened surface from both the face and butt. Place over the fire in cold water, let it come to a moderate boil and keep it steadily at that point, allowing it to cook twenty minutes for each pound of <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> replenishing the supply of water as fast as it boils away. When cooked, remove the skin--it will easily peel off if it has been properly boiled--and dish with the fat side up. The service is improved by dredging <ingredient>black pepper</ingredient> in spots on the upside, sticking in a few <ingredient>whole cloves</ingredient> and garnishing with <ingredient>parsley.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p>A little practice is needed to acquire <purpose>the art of eating a mango gracefully, yet without losing any of the aroma which distinguishes it.</purpose></p>



<p>The fine fibreless varieties are the most easily eaten. Such <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> is best prepared by cutting through the skin and turning it back in a broad band, as shown in the accompanying illustration, or by making an X cut on each side, peeling the corners back as far as possible, and temporarily laying the skin in place again to prevent the aroma from escaping. The pulp can then in either case be eaten with a spoon, like a cantaloupe, turning the skin back as necessary.</p>



<p><variation>A third method sometimes employed, but requiring considerable deftness and only appropriate for immediate service and consumption, is to halve the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> lengthwise with a sharp knife, remove the stone and serve the two halves as one would cantaloupe.</variation></p>



<p><variation>With a less delicate <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> a better way is to cut the skin in a circle around each end and make seven or eight lengthwise incisions from circle to circle. The skin can then be easily lifted in strips and the flesh cut off in sections, lengthwise, as, or just before, eating.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>The housewife who in warm weather finds that her <purpose>meat has become tainted, can restore its freshness</purpose> by cutting off and throwing the fat away and washing the lean in a solution of <ingredient>borax</ingredient> or <ingredient>bicarbonate of soda</ingredient> and <ingredient>cold water</ingredient>--a teaspoonful to a quart--and then sponging off with fresh water.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>A summer household <purpose><alt synonym1="to prevent taint in meat">preventive of taint</alt></purpose> is to wash all <ingredient>meat</ingredient> as received in <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> or to rub it over with <ingredient>salad oil.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>In <purpose>moistening or "mixing" dry mustard, or mustard flour,</purpose> two main objects must be kept in view--first, to obtain the desired consistence; second, to make it perfectly smooth. To produce these effects, add the liquid in small quantities and rub and pound the <ingredient>mustard</ingredient> well with a spoon. The simplest form of preparation consists of <ingredient>mustard flour,</ingredient> moistened with sufficient <ingredient>water</ingredient> to produce the consistence of thick batter, with half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> added for each two ounces of mustard flour. Some people like fine <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> included in the same proportion as salt. <ingredient>Vinegar</ingredient> and <ingredient>olive oil</ingredient> can be used according to taste, but some cold water is necessary for the first mixing in order to develop the pungency. If for immediate use, <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or milk and <ingredient>cream</ingredient> may be employed in place of either vinegar or oil.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p>In <purpose><alt synonym1="to serve pineapple">preparing a fresh pine for the table,</alt></purpose> peel off the outer skin, take out the eyes with a <implement>patent remover,</implement> cut in slices and core with a <implement>patent corer.</implement></p>



<p>A still better method, which does not, however, give the even round slices of the preceding directions, is first to remove the outer covering and eyes as above, then stand the <ingredient>pine</ingredient> up on the table, insert a fork in the blossom and, with another <emph rend="italic">silver</emph> fork, pick away the fruit-flesh from the core in small or large chunks as desired.</p>



<p>In either case, the result will be infinitely superior if the slices or pieces are packed in a glass <implement>fruit-jar,</implement> covered with <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and set in the <implement>ice box</implement> for at least twenty-four hours before serving.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose>To keep potatoes in good condition,</purpose> it is essential that they should be stored in a <emph rend="italic">dark, cool, well-ventilated</emph> place. Excessive dampness should be avoided, but extreme dryness is almost equally bad, as it has a tendency to shrivel them. When the latter result is noticed, they may be packed and covered with <ingredient>sand,</ingredient> the latter being dampened occasionally. A sprinkle of <ingredient>lime</ingredient> over any that are disposed to rot, will act as a deterrent.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes"><p><purpose><alt synonym1="pousse caf&#233;">A popular formula</alt></purpose> consists of a little <ingredient>raspberry syrup (<emph rend="italic">red</emph>),</ingredient> in the bottom of the glass; then <ingredient>anisette (<emph rend="italic">white</emph>),</ingredient> <ingredient><emph rend="italic">orange</emph> cura&#231;oa,</ingredient> <ingredient>maraschino (<emph rend="italic">white</emph>),</ingredient> <ingredient><emph rend="italic">green</emph> chartreuse</ingredient> and <ingredient>brandy (<emph rend="italic">golden</emph>)</ingredient> in the order named--the brandy on top.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p>Instead of ruining the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> by soaking it, rinse it in <ingredient>scalding water</ingredient> and wash thoroughly in <ingredient>cold water;</ingredient> then strain through a <implement>colander</implement> and place it in a cooking vessel (porcelain preferred), add as much <ingredient>water</ingredient> as fruit and set on the back of the stove or range to simmer until tender. <emph rend="italic">Do not boil.</emph> You will thus obtain <purpose>stewed prunes</purpose> that are tender but firm in flesh, palatable and in every way delicious.</p>



<p>No <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is needed for good <ingredient>California prunes,</ingredient> but <ingredient>Oregon prunes</ingredient> are more tart and are generally improved by about a tablespoonful for each pound of fruit.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>In <purpose>boiling rice,</purpose> see that the <ingredient>water</ingredient> is boiling hard before the <ingredient>rice</ingredient> is added; then, as the addition of the rice will stop the boiling, stir until the boiling point is again reached. After that, do not stir at all but see that the fire keeps the water boiling and add <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> if too much evaporates. The action of the boiling water will prevent the rice from burning, but it will not break the grains as stirring does. The result of the observance of these simple directions will be rice that is thoroughly cooked yet which has every grain clean and separate.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose>A simple and inexpensive method of keeping "naked" smoked meats in hot weather,</purpose> is to put them into paper flour sacks, tying the tops with strong twine and then hanging them from the ceiling, where the air can pass between them.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages"><p>To make good <purpose rend="italic">Iced Tea</purpose> use from one-quarter to one-third more of the leaf than for <ingredient>tea</ingredient> to be served hot. Prepare the beverage just as carefully, and do not allow it to stand on the <ingredient>leaves</ingredient> for longer than five to seven minutes. Pour the liquid off into another vessel and <emph rend="italic">allow it to cool gradually.</emph> It should always be made two or three hours before serving, to give it time to cool gradually. To chill hot tea by setting in the refrigerator or putting ice in it, is to spoil its flavor. When ready to serve, add <ingredient>ice,</ingredient> <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> etc., according to taste.</p></recipe>



