<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BROWN OR DYSPEPSIA BREAD.</purpose>







This bread is now best known as "Graham bread"--not that Doctor Graham invented or discovered the manner of its preparation, but that he has been unwearied and successful in recommending it to the public. It is an excellent article of diet for the dyspeptic and the costive; and for most persons of sedentary habits, would be beneficial. It agrees well with children; and, in short, I think it should be used in every family, though not to the exclusion of fine bread. The most difficult point in manufacturing this bread, is to obtain good pure meal. It is said that much of the bread commonly sold as <emph rend="italic">dyspepsia,</emph> is made of the <emph rend="italic">bran</emph> or <emph rend="italic">middlings,</emph> from which the fine flour has been separated; and that <emph rend="italic">saw-dust</emph> is sometimes mixed with the meal. To be certain that it is good, send good, clean wheat to the <implement>mill,</implement> have it ground rather coarsely, and keep the meal in a dry, cool place. Before using it, sift it through a common <implement>hair sieve;</implement> this will separate the very coarse and harsh particles.</p>



<p>Take six quarts of this <ingredient>wheat meal,</ingredient> one <implement>tea-cup</implement> of good <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> and half a <implement>tea-cup</implement> of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> mix these with a pint of <ingredient>milk-warm water</ingredient> and a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> or <ingredient>sal&#230;ratus.</ingredient> Make a hole in the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and stir this mixture in the middle of the meal till it is like batter. Then proceed as with fine flour bread. Make the dough when sufficiently light into four loaves, which will weigh two pounds per loaf when baked. It requires a hotter oven than fine flour bread and must bake about an hour and a half.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">RYE AND INDIAN BREAD.</purpose>







This is a sweet and nourishing diet, and generally acceptable to children.</p>



<p>It is economical, and when wheat is scarce, is a pretty good substitute for dyspepsia bread.</p>



<p>There are many different proportions of mixing it--some put one third <ingredient>indian meal</ingredient> with two of <ingredient>rye;</ingredient> others like one third <ingredient>rye</ingredient> and two of <ingredient>indian;</ingredient> others prefer it half and half.</p>



<p>If you use the largest proportion of <ingredient>rye meal,</ingredient> make your dough stiff, so that it will mould into loaves;--when it is two thirds <ingredient>indian,</ingredient> it should be softer and baked in deep earthen or tin pans after the following rules.</p>



<p>Take <emph rend="italic">four quarts</emph> of sifted <ingredient>indian meal;</ingredient> put it into a glazed earthen pan, sprinkle over it a table-spoonful of <ingredient>fine salt;</ingredient> pour over it about two quarts of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> stir and work it till every part of the meal is thoroughly wet; <ingredient>indian</ingredient> absorbs a greater quantity of <ingredient>water.</ingredient> When it is about milk warm, work in <emph rend="italic">two quarts of <ingredient>rye meal,</ingredient> half a pint</emph> of <ingredient>lively yeast,</ingredient> mixed with a pint of <ingredient>warm water;</ingredient> add more <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> if needed. Work the mixture well with your hands; it should be stiff, but not firm as <ingredient>flour</ingredient> dough. Have ready a large, deep, well buttered pan; put in the dough, and smooth the top by putting your hand in <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> and then patting down the loaf. Set this to rise in a warm place in the winter; in the summer it should not be put by the fire. When it begins to crack on the top, which will usually be in about an hour or an hour and a half, put it into a well-heated oven, and bake it three or four hours. It is better to let it stand in the oven all night, unless the weather is warm. <ingredient>Indian meal</ingredient> requires to be well cooked. The loaf will weigh between seven and eight pounds. Pan bread keeps best in large loaves.</p>



<p>Many use <ingredient>milk</ingredient> in mixing bread;--in the country where <ingredient>milk</ingredient> is plentiful, it is a good practice, as bread is certainly richer wet with <ingredient>sweet milk</ingredient> than with <ingredient>water;</ingredient> but it will not keep so long in warm weather.</p>



<p>Baking can very well be done in a stove; during the winter this is an economical way of cooking--but the stove 



 



<pb n="19" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=39"/>







must be carefully watched or there is danger of scorching the bread.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">RICE BREAD.</purpose>







Boil a <emph rend="italic">pint</emph> of <emph rend="italic"><ingredient>rice</ingredient></emph> very soft; when it is nearly cool add a pint of leaven, and work in three quarts of <ingredient>rice flour.</ingredient> Let it rise, till it is light--one hour, in warm weather is sufficient--Divide the dough into three parts, bake it in tin pans, well buttered; and you will have three large loaves of bread. It soongrows dry.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">YEAST.</purpose>







It is impossible to have good light bread, unless you have lively sweet <emph rend="italic">yeast.</emph> When common family <ingredient>beer</ingredient> is well brewed and kept in a clean <implement>cask,</implement> the settlings are the best of yeast. If you do not keep beer, then make common yeast by the following method.</p>



<p>Take two quarts of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> one handful of <ingredient>hops,</ingredient> two of <ingredient>wheat bran;</ingredient> boil these together twenty minutes; strain off the water, and while it is boiling hot stir in either <ingredient>wheat</ingredient> or <ingredient>rye flour,</ingredient> till it becomes a thick batter; let it stand till it is about blood warm; then add a half pint of good <ingredient>smart yeast</ingredient> and a large spoonful of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> if you have it, and stir the whole well. Set it in a cool place in summer and a warm one in winter. When it becomes perfectly light, it is fit for use. If not needed immediately, it should, when it becomes cold, be put in a clean jug or bottle; do not fill the vessel and the cork must be left loose till the next morning, when the yeast will have done working. Then cork it tightly, and set in a cool place in the cellar. It will keep ten or twelve days.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">MILK YEAST.</purpose>







One pint of <ingredient>new milk;</ingredient> one tea-spoonful of <ingredient>fine salt,</ingredient> and a large spoon of <ingredient>flour</ingredient>--stir these well together; set the mixture by the fire, and keep it just lukewarm; it will be fit for use in an hour. Twice the quantity of common <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> is necessary; it will not keep long. Bread made of this yeast dries very soon; but in the summer it is sometimes convenient to make this kind when yeast is needed suddenly.</p>



 



<pb n="20" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=40"/>







<p>Never keep yeast in a tin vessel.--If you find the old yeast <emph rend="italic">sour,</emph> and have not time to prepare new, put in <ingredient>sal&#230;ratus,</ingredient> a tea-spoonful to a pint of yeast, when ready to use it. If it foams up lively, it will raise the bread, if it does not, never use it.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">HARD YEAST.</purpose>







Boil three ounces of <ingredient>hops</ingredient> in six quarts of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> till only two quarts remain. Strain it, and stir in while it is boiling hot, <ingredient>wheat</ingredient> or <ingredient>rye meal</ingredient> till it is thick as batter. When it is about milk warm add half a pint of <ingredient>good yeast,</ingredient> and let it stand till it is very light, which will probably be about three hours. Then work in sifted <ingredient>indian meal</ingredient> till it is stiff dough. Roll out on a board; cut it in oblong cakes about three inches by two. They should be about half an inch thick. Lay these cakes on a smooth board, over which a little <ingredient>flour</ingredient> has been dusted; prick them with a fork, and set the board in a dry clean chamber or store-room, where the sun and air may be freely admitted. Turn them every day. They will dry in a fortnight unless the weather is damp. When the cakes are fully dry, put them into a coarse cotton bag; hang it up in a cool dry place. If rightly prepared these cakes will keep a year, and save the trouble of making new yeast every week.</p>



<p>Two cakes will make yeast sufficient for a peck of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Break them into a pint of <ingredient>lukewarm water</ingredient> and stir in a large spoonful of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> the evening before you bake. Set the mixture where it can be kept moderately warm. In the morning it will be fit for use.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO ROAST BEEF.</purpose>







The <ingredient>sirloin</ingredient> is too large for a private family; one weighing fifteen pounds is the best size for roasting; but this may be divided if a small one is required. It should be washed in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> then dried with a clean cloth and rubbed over with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>fat</ingredient> covered with a piece of white paper tied on with thread. The spit should be clean as sand and water can make it. Be sure and wipe it dry immediately after it is drawn from the <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> and scour and wash it always before using.</p>



<p>The fire must be bright and clear, but not scorching when the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> is put down. Place it about ten inches from the fire at first and gradually move it nearer. It should be basted with a little clean dripping or <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> put into the <implement>roaster</implement> or <implement>tin-kitchen,</implement> as soon as it is down. Be sure this <implement>roaster</implement> is perfectly clean. Continue to baste the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> at intervals, and turn the spit frequently, and when the roast is nearly done--or about half an hour before you take it up--remove the paper from the fat, sprinkle on a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and baste it well--then pour off the top of the dripping, which is nearly all liquid fat, and would prove unhealthy if used in the gravy; then take a <implement>tea-cup</implement> of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> into which put a salt-spoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and drop this by degrees, on the brown parts of the joints (the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> will soon brown again.)--Stir the fire and make it clear; sprinkle a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> over the roast, baste it with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and dredge it with <ingredient>flour</ingredient>--very soon the froth will rise; then it must be taken up directly and dished.--Pour the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> from the <implement>roaster,</implement> skim it, and give it a boil, then send it to table in a boat. 



 



<pb n="28" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=48"/>







Scraped <ingredient>horse-radish</ingredient> is used to garnish it, or may be sent up in a plate with <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient></p>



<p>The inside of the <ingredient>sirloin</ingredient> is excellent for hash.</p>



<p>Twenty minutes of time to each pound of <ingredient>meat</ingredient> is the rule for roasting. In cold weather, and when the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> is very fat it will require a little more time--in warm weather, and with <ingredient>lean beef</ingredient> fifteen minutes to a pound will be sufficient. Experience and judgment must regulate these things.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BEEF ALAMODE.</purpose>







Take a thick piece of <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> bone it, beat it well and <ingredient>lard</ingredient> it with <ingredient>fat bacon,</ingredient> then put it into a <implement>stew-pan</implement> with some <ingredient>rind of bacon,</ingredient> an <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> <ingredient>carrot,</ingredient> a bunch of <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> a <ingredient>clove of garlic,</ingredient> some <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> pour over the whole a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> let it stew over a slow fire for six hours at least. A clean cloth should be placed over the <implement>stew-pan</implement> before the lid is put on, which must be carefully closed. When it is done, strain the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> through a sieve, clear off the fat, and serve.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BEEF BAKED.</purpose>







Let a buttock of <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> weighing ten pounds, which has been in <ingredient>salt</ingredient> about a week, be well washed and put into an earthen pan, with a pint of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> cover the pan tight with two or three sheets of <emph rend="italic"><implement>foolscap</implement></emph> paper--let it bake four or five hours in a moderately heated oven.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BEEF BAKED WITH POTATOES.</purpose>







Boil some <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> peel, and pound them in a <implement>mortar</implement> with one or two small <ingredient>onions;</ingredient> moisten them with <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and an <ingredient>egg</ingredient> beaten up; add a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper.</ingredient> Season slices of <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> or <ingredient>mutton</ingredient> chops, with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> rub the bottom of a <implement>pudding dish</implement> with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and put a layer of the <ingredient>mashed potatoes,</ingredient> which should be as thick as a batter, and then a layer of <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> and so on alternately till the dish is filled, ending with <ingredient>potatoes.</ingredient> Bake it in an oven for one hour.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">BEEF STEWED.</purpose>







Take ten pounds of a <ingredient>brisket of beef,</ingredient> cut the short ribs, and put it into a well-buttered saucepan, with two large <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> stuck with three or four <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> two or three <ingredient>carrots</ingredient> cut into quarters, a bunch of <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> a small <ingredient>lemon sliced,</ingredient> and five quarts of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> let it stew seven hours. Strain and clarify the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient>--thicken it with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Chop the <ingredient>carrots</ingredient> with some <ingredient>capers,</ingredient> <ingredient>mushroom catchup,</ingredient> and <ingredient>Cayenne.</ingredient> Any other <ingredient>pickle</ingredient> that is liked may be added.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BEEF BALLS.</purpose>







Mince very finely a piece of <ingredient>tender beef,</ingredient> <ingredient>fat</ingredient> and <ingredient>lean;</ingredient> mince an <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> with some <ingredient>parsley;</ingredient> add <ingredient>grated bread crumbs,</ingredient> and season with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>grated nutmeg,</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon-peel;</ingredient> mix all together, and moisten it with an <ingredient>egg</ingredient> beaten; roll it into balls; <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and fry them in boiling fresh dripping. Serve them with <ingredient>fried bread crumbs,</ingredient> or with a thickened <ingredient>brown gravy.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BEEF, SHORT OR SPICED.</purpose>







(To be eaten cold.) Hang up ten or twelve pounds of the middle part of a <ingredient>brisket of beef</ingredient> for three or four days, then rub well into it three ounces of <ingredient>finely powdered saltpetre,</ingredient> and, if spice is approved of, one ounce of <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> and half an ounce of <ingredient>black pepper;</ingredient> let it stand all night, then <ingredient>salt</ingredient> it with three pounds of <ingredient>well-pounded bay salt,</ingredient> and half a pound of <ingredient>treacle,</ingredient> in which let it remain ten days, rubbing it daily. When it is to be boiled, sew it closely in a cloth, let the <ingredient>water</ingredient> only simmer, upon no account allowing it to boil, for nine hours over a slow fire, or upon a stove. When taken out of the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> place two sticks across the pot, and let the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> stand over the steam for half an hour, turning it, from side to side, then press it with a heavy weight. It must not be taken out of the cloth till perfectly cold.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BEEF BOILED.</purpose>







The perfection of boiling is that it be done slowly and the pot well skimmed. If the scum be permitted to boil<pb n="30" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=50"/>







down it sticks to the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> and gives it a dirty appearance. A quart of <ingredient>water</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>meat</ingredient> is an old rule; but, there must always be <ingredient>water</ingredient> sufficient to cover it well, so that the scum may be taken off easily.</p>



<p>When <ingredient>beef</ingredient> is very <ingredient>salt</ingredient> (which it rarely will be if rightly cured) it must be soaked for half an hour or more in <ingredient>lukewarm water,</ingredient> before it is put on to boil, when the <ingredient>water</ingredient> must be changed.</p>



<p>The ROUND is the best piece to boil--then the <ingredient>H-BONE.</ingredient></p>



<p>Take part of a <ingredient>ROUND of beef</ingredient>--put into your <implement>boiler</implement> with plenty of <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> to cover it; set the pot on one side of the fire to boil gently, if it boil <emph rend="italic">quick</emph> at first, no art can make the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> tender. <emph rend="italic">The slower it boils the tenderer it will be.</emph></p>



<p>(How much good fuel is wasted, to say nothing of the hard labor cooks impose on themselves and the injury to their health by heating over a great blaze, through this carelessness in making fires. In the country, especially, and often during summer, a fire is prepared nearly hot enough for Nebuchadnezzar's furnace, merely to boil the pot! Instead of hanging the <implement>boiler</implement> low, it seems the ambition of the housewife to elevate it as near the stars as possible. Three small sticks of wood or two with chips, will boil a large dinner, and if the pot is hung very low, but little inconvenience will be felt from the fire. This, in hot weather, for those who are obliged to be in the kitchen, is a great comfort. But the pot is boiling all this time. So to our receipt.)</p>



<p>Be sure to take off all the scum as it rises. When you take the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> up, if any stray scum sticks to it, wash it off with a <implement>paste brush.</implement> Garnish the dishes with <ingredient>carrots</ingredient> and <ingredient>turnips.</ingredient> <ingredient>Boiled potatoes,</ingredient> <ingredient>carrots,</ingredient> <ingredient>turnips</ingredient> and <ingredient>greens,</ingredient> on separate plates, are good accompaniments.</p>



<p>If the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> weigh ten pounds it requires to boil, or rather simmer about three hours. In cold weather all meats need to be cooked a longer time than in warm weather. Always cook them till tender.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">BEEF STEAKS BROILED.</purpose>







The inside of the sirloin is the best <ingredient>steak</ingredient>--but all are cooked in the same manner. Cut them about half an inch 



 



<pb n="31" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=51"/>







thick--do not beat them; it breaks the cells in which the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> of the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> is contained and renders it drier and more tasteless.</p>



<p>Have the <implement>gridiron</implement> hot and the bars rubbed with <ingredient>suet</ingredient>--the fire clear and brisk; sprinkle a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> over the fire, lay on the <ingredient>steaks,</ingredient> and turn them often. Keep a dish close to the fire, into which you must drain the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> from the top of the <ingredient>steak</ingredient> as you lift it to turn. The <implement>gridiron</implement> should be set in a slanting direction on the coals, to prevent the fat from dropping into the fire and making a smoke. But should a smoke occur, take off the <implement>gridiron</implement> a moment, till it is over. With a good fire of coals, <ingredient>steaks</ingredient> will be thoroughly done in fifteen minutes. These are much healthier for delicate stomachs than <emph rend="italic">rare done <ingredient>steaks.</ingredient></emph></p>



<p>When done lay them in a hot plate, put a small <implement>slice</implement> of good <ingredient>butter</ingredient> on each piece--sprinkle a <emph rend="italic">little</emph> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> pour the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> from the dish by the fire, and serve them hot as possible. <ingredient>Pickles</ingredient> and <ingredient>finely scraped horse-radish</ingredient> are served with them.</p>



<p>I have now given the most important receipts for cooking beef.--The re-cooking requires skill and judgement which experience only can give. When well done it makes excellent dishes, and is economical in housekeeping. The following are good receipts.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BEEF, COLD TENDERLOIN.</purpose>







Cut off entire the inside of a large <ingredient>sirloin of beef,</ingredient> brown it all over in a <implement>stew-pan,</implement> and then add a quart of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> some <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and a large <ingredient>onion</ingredient> finely minced; cover the pan closely, and let it stew till the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> be very tender. Garnish with <ingredient>pickles.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BEEF, COLD STEAKS TO WARM.</purpose>







Lay them in a <implement>stew-pan,</implement> with one large <ingredient>onion</ingredient> cut in quarters, six berries of <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> the same of <ingredient>black pepper,</ingredient> cover the <ingredient>steaks</ingredient> with <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> let them stew gently one hour, thicken the liquor with <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rubbed together on a plate; if a pint of <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> about one ounce of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and the like weight of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> will do; put it into the <implement>stew-pan,</implement> shake it well over the fire for five minutes, and it is ready; 



 



<pb n="32" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=52"/>







lay the <ingredient>steaks</ingredient> and <ingredient>onions</ingredient> on a dish and pour the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> through a sieve over them.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BEEF MINCED.</purpose>







Mince you <ingredient>beef</ingredient> very small; put it into a saucepan with a little <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> and a little of the <ingredient>fat of fowl</ingredient> or any other <ingredient>fat,</ingredient> season according to your taste, then let it simmer over a gentle fire till it is sufficiently done.</p>



<p>Boiled beef, when thoroughly done is excellent to eat cold, as a relish at breakfast. The slices should be cut even and very thin.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PORK TO ROAST.</purpose>







Take a <ingredient>leg of pork,</ingredient> one weighing eight pounds will require full three and a half hours to roast it. Wash it clean, and dry it with a cloth; with a sharp knife score the skin in diamonds about an inch square.</p>



<p>Make a stuffing with <ingredient>grated bread,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>sage,</ingredient> and two small <ingredient>onions</ingredient> chopped fine, seasoned with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and moistened with the <ingredient>yolk of an egg.</ingredient> Put this in under the skin of the knuckle, and in deep incisions made in the thick part of the <ingredient>leg;</ingredient> rub a little <ingredient>fine powdered sage</ingredient> into the skin where it is scored; and then, with a <implement>paste brush</implement> or goose feather, rub the whole surface of the skin with <ingredient>sweet oil</ingredient> or <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> this makes the crackling crisper and browner than basting it with dripping, it will be perfect in color, and the skin will not blister.</p>



<p>Do not put it too near the fire; and it must be moistened at intervals with <ingredient>sweet oil</ingredient> or <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> tied up in a rag. When it is done, skim the fat from the <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> which may be thickened with a little <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></p>



<p><ingredient>Apple-sauce</ingredient> is always proper to accompany roasted pork--this, with <ingredient>potatoes, mashed or plain,</ingredient> <ingredient>mashed turnips,</ingredient> and <ingredient>pickles</ingredient> are good.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">SPARE-RIB</purpose>







Should be rubbed with <ingredient>powdered sage</ingredient> mixed with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> before it is roasted. It will require, if large and thick, two or three hours to roast it--a very thin one may roast in an hour. Lay the thick end to the fire. When you put it down, dust on some <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and baste with a little <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p>



<p>The <ingredient>shoulder,</ingredient> <ingredient>loin,</ingredient> or <ingredient>chine</ingredient> are roasted in the 



 



<pb n="34" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=54"/>







same manner. A shoulder is the most economical part to buy, and is excellent boiled. Pork is always salted before it is boiled.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">PICKLED PORK</purpose>







Takes more time than any other meat. If you buy your pork ready salted, ask how many days it has been in salt; if many, it will require to be soaked in <ingredient>water</ingredient> for six hours before you dress it. When you cook it, wash and scrape it as clean as possible; when delicately dressed, it is a favorite dish with almost everybody. Take care it does not boil fast; if it does, the knuckle will break to pieces, before the thick part of the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> is warm through; a <ingredient>leg</ingredient> of seven pounds takes three hours and a half very slow simmering. Skim your pot very carefully, and when you take the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> out of the <implement>boiler,</implement> scrape it clean.</p>



<p>The proper vegetables are <ingredient>parsnips,</ingredient> <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> <ingredient>turnips,</ingredient> or <ingredient>carrots.</ingredient> Some like <ingredient>cabbage,</ingredient> but it is a strong, rank vegetable, and does not agree with a delicate stomach. It should not be given to children.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">PORK STEAKS.</purpose>







Cut them off a <ingredient>neck</ingredient> or <ingredient>loin;</ingredient> trim them neatly, and <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> them; broil them over a clear fire, turning them frequently; they will take twenty minutes. Sprinkle with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> when put in the plate, and add a small piece of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BROILED HAM.</purpose>







Cut <ingredient>ham</ingredient> into very thin slices and broil on a <implement>gridiron.</implement> If the <ingredient>ham</ingredient> is too salt, soak the slices before broiling in <ingredient>hot water;</ingredient> if you are obliged to do this, dry them well with a cloth before broiling.</p>



<p>Fry what <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> you want in <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and when dished lay an <ingredient>egg</ingredient> on each <implement>slice</implement> of <ingredient>ham,</ingredient> and serve.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">HAM BOILED.</purpose>







A <ingredient>ham</ingredient> if dry, requires to be soaked from twelve to twentyfour hours in <ingredient>warm water.</ingredient> Then put it on in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and let it simmer, not boil, four or five hours. It is 



 



<pb n="35" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=55"/>







better and goes farther not to be cut till it is quite cold. Boiled ham is delicate to broil.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">SAUSAGES FRIED.</purpose>







<ingredient>Sausages</ingredient> are best when quite fresh. Put a little dripping or bit of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the frying pan; as soon as it is melted, put in the <ingredient>sausages</ingredient> and shake them and turn often. Fry them over a very slow fire and be sure not to break or prick them. Fry them till they are a nice brown--then drain them from the fat and serve.</p>



<p>They are easily digested and a very nutritious food--proper for the elderly whose teeth are not good.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">TO MAKE SAUSAGE MEAT.</purpose>







Chop two pounds of <ingredient>lean</ingredient> with one of <ingredient>fat pork</ingredient> very fine--mix with this <ingredient>meat</ingredient> five teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> seven of <ingredient>powdered sage,</ingredient> two of <ingredient>black pepper</ingredient> and one of <ingredient>cloves.</ingredient>--You can add a little <ingredient>rosemary,</ingredient> if you like it.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO ROAST A PIG.</purpose>







A <ingredient>pig</ingredient> about three weeks old is the best. It should be killed the morning if it is to be eaten for dinner.</p>



<p>Make the <ingredient>stuffing</ingredient> with about six ounces of <ingredient>grated bread,</ingredient> a handful of <ingredient>sage</ingredient> minced fine, (or two ounces) and a large <ingredient>onion.</ingredient> Mix these together with an <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> some <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and a bit of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> as large as an egg.</p>



<p>Wash the <ingredient>pig</ingredient> in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> cut off the petti-toes, leaving the skin long to wrap around the ends of the legs.--Then fill the belly with the <ingredient>stuffing</ingredient> and sew it up. The <ingredient>liver</ingredient> and <ingredient>heart</ingredient> may be kept with the <ingredient>feet</ingredient> for <ingredient>gravy.</ingredient></p>



<p>The fire must be clear and hotter at the ends than in the middle. You can place a <implement>flat iron</implement> before the middle of the fire.</p>



<p>Before the <ingredient>pig</ingredient> is put down rub it over with <ingredient>sallad oil</ingredient> or fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and baste with these till it is done. It requires constant care. A small one will be done enough in an hour and a half.</p>



<p>Before you take it from the fire, cut off the <ingredient>head</ingredient> and part it down the middle, take out the <ingredient>brains,</ingredient> chop them fine with some <ingredient>boiled sage leaves</ingredient> and mix these with <ingredient>veal</ingredient> or 



 



<pb n="36" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=56"/>







<ingredient>beef gravy</ingredient> or that which runs from the <ingredient>pig</ingredient> when you cut it down the middle, which must be done before you lay it in the dish.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">MUTTON LEG TO BOIL.</purpose>







Cut off the shank bone and trim the knuckle--if it weigh nine pounds it will require three hours to cook it.</p>



 



<pb n="37" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=57"/>







<p><ingredient>Parsley</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> or <ingredient>caper-sauce</ingredient> should be served with it--<ingredient>onion sauce,</ingredient> <ingredient>turnips,</ingredient> spinage and <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> are all used.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">TO STEW A SHOULDER OF MUTTON.</purpose>







Bone and flatten a <ingredient>shoulder of mutton,</ingredient> sprinkle over it <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> roll it up tightly, bind it with tape, and put it into a <implement>stew-pan</implement> that will just hold it, pour over it a well <ingredient>seasoned gravy</ingredient> made with the <ingredient>bones,</ingredient> cover the pan closely, and let it stew till tender; before serving, take off the tape, thicken the <ingredient>gravy.</ingredient> It will take about three hours to stew the shoulder.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">MUTTON CHOPS.</purpose>







Cut the chops off a <ingredient>loin</ingredient> or the best end of a <ingredient>neck of mutton;</ingredient> pare off the fat, dip them in a beaten <ingredient>egg</ingredient> and strew over them <ingredient>grated bread,</ingredient> seasoned with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>finely minced parsley</ingredient>--then fry them in a little <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and make a <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> or broil them over coals, and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> them in a hot dish. Garnish with <ingredient>fried parsley.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">LAMB.</purpose>







Lamb is a delicate and tender meat; but it requires to be kept a few days, when the weather will permit--and should be thoroughly cooked to be healthful. Never take lamb or veal from the spit till the gravy that drops is white.</p>



<p>The forequarter of lamb consists of the shoulder, neck and breast together; this is best roasted; it requires about two hours to cook it well. The leg may be boiled or roasted.</p>



<p><ingredient>Mint sauce</ingredient> (the leaves of <ingredient>mint</ingredient> chopped fine and mixed with <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient>--<ingredient>lettuce leaves</ingredient> prepared in the same way, if you have no mint, will do) is much esteemed with roast lamb.</p>



<p>Lamb is fine for cutlets, or with rice cooked as follows.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">LAMB DRESSED WITH RICE.</purpose>







Half roast a small fore quarter; cut it into <ingredient>steaks;</ingredient> season them with a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper;</ingredient> lay them into a dish, and pour in a little <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Boil a pound of <ingredient>rice</ingredient> with a blade or two of <ingredient>mace;</ingredient> strain it, and stir in a good piece of fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> add also the greater part of the <ingredient>yolk of four eggs</ingredient> beaten; cover the <ingredient>lamb</ingredient> with the <ingredient>rice,</ingredient> and with a feather 



 



<pb n="38" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=58"/>







put over it the remainder of the beaten <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient> Bake it in an oven till it has acquired a light brown color.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">VENISON STEAKS.</purpose>







May be broiled or fried in the same manner as mutton chops or veal cutlets. Mutton is the best substitute for the real venison; dressed by the following receipt, it is much relished.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">VENISON MOCK.</purpose>







Hang up, for several days, a large <ingredient>fat loin of mutton;</ingredient> then bone it, and take off all the kidneyfat, and the skin from the upper fat; mix together one ounce of <ingredient>ground allspice,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>brown sugar</ingredient> and one ounce of <ingredient>ground black pepper.</ingredient> Rub it well into the <ingredient>mutton;</ingredient> keep it covered with the <ingredient>skin;</ingredient> rub and turn it daily for five days. When to be roasted, cover it with the <ingredient>skin,</ingredient> and paper it the same way as venison is done. Serve it with made <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> and <ingredient>current jelly.</ingredient> It must be well washed from the spices before it is roasted.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO ROAST A TURKEY.</purpose>







Make a <ingredient>stuffing</ingredient> like that for <ingredient>veal;</ingredient> or take a <implement>tea-cup</implement> of <ingredient>sausage meat</ingredient> and add a like quantity of <ingredient>bread crumbs,</ingredient> with the beaten <ingredient>yolks of two eggs</ingredient>--then fill the crop; dredge the <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> over with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> lay it before the fire, taking care this is most on the stuffed part, as that requires the greatest heat. A strip of paper may be put on the breast bone to prevent its scorching. Baste with a little <ingredient>butter</ingredient> or <ingredient>salt and water</ingredient> at first, then with its own dripping. A little before it is taken up, dredge it again with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> baste with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and froth it up. A large <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> requires full three hours roasting--a smaller in proportion.</p>



<p><ingredient>Ham</ingredient> or <ingredient>tongue</ingredient> is usually eaten with turkey; <ingredient>stewed cranberries</ingredient> also.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO BOIL A TURKEY.</purpose>







Clean it as to roast, make a <ingredient>stuffing of bread,</ingredient> <ingredient>green parsley,</ingredient> one <ingredient>lemon peel,</ingredient> a few <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> or an <ingredient>onion</ingredient>--season with, <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and mix one <ingredient>egg</ingredient> and a small bit of <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> put this into the crop, fasten up the skin, put the <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> on in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> enough to cover it, let it boil slowly, and take off all the scum; when this is done, it should only simmer closely covered till it is done. It will take about two hours for a small <ingredient>turkey,</ingredient> longer if large. A little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> three teaspoonfuls, may be put in the <ingredient>water</ingredient> and the <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> dredged with <ingredient>flour</ingredient> before it is boiled. The <ingredient>neck,</ingredient> and <ingredient>liver</ingredient> are chopped and put in the <ingredient>gravy.</ingredient></p>



<p><ingredient>Fowls</ingredient> and <ingredient>chickens</ingredient> may be boiled in the same way, with a like <ingredient>stuffing,</ingredient> only allowing less time. A <ingredient>chicken</ingredient> will take about 35 minutes. A <ingredient>fowl</ingredient> <emph rend="italic">nearly an hour.</emph> Let them boil till tender--serve with <ingredient>parsely-sauce</ingredient> or <ingredient>egg-sauce.</ingredient></p>



<p><ingredient>Fowls</ingredient> and <ingredient>chickens</ingredient> are cooked in a great variety of ways. <ingredient>Fowls</ingredient> are good stuffed and roasted, the same as <ingredient>turkeys,</ingredient> only allowing less time at the fire;--an hour and 



 



<pb n="41" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=61"/>







a half for a large <ingredient>fowl</ingredient>--not quite an hour for a <ingredient>chicken;</ingredient> this last need not be stuffed.</p>



<p>It is needless to repeat over again the ingredients for <ingredient>stuffing,</ingredient> way of making <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> &amp;c. A female who has sense enough to cook a dinner will manage these things to her own liking and means. It is not necessary to good cooking, that every one should season alike.</p>



<p>Young <ingredient>chickens</ingredient> are best broiled or fricaseed.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO BROIL A CHICKEN.</purpose>







Pick and singe them nicely, wash them clean, and dry them in a cloth; cut them down the back, truss the <ingredient>legs</ingredient> and <ingredient>wings,</ingredient> as for boiling; flatten them, and put them upon a cold <implement>gridiron;</implement> when they become a little dry, put them upon a plate, turn them with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and strew a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> over the inside, which part is laid first upon the <implement>gridiron</implement>: turn them frequently, and let them broil slowly for about half an hour. Serve them hot, with melted <ingredient>butter</ingredient> poured over them, or plenty of <ingredient>stewed mushrooms.</ingredient> The <ingredient>livers</ingredient> and <ingredient>gizzards</ingredient> may be broiled with them, fastened into the <ingredient>wings,</ingredient> well seasoned, and served with the <ingredient>chickens.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO FRICASEE A CHICKEN.</purpose>







Wash and cut the <ingredient>chicken</ingredient> into joints; scald and take off the skin, put the pieces in a <implement>stew-pan,</implement> with an <ingredient>onion</ingredient> cut small, a bunch of <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>thyme</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon-peel,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper</ingredient>--add a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> a bit of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> as large as an egg. Stew it an hour; a little before serving, add the <ingredient>yolks of two eggs</ingredient> beaten up, with a <implement>tea-cup</implement> of <ingredient>sweet cream,</ingredient> stirring it in gradually; take care that this <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> does not boil.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CHICKEN BAKED IN RICE.</purpose>







Cut a <ingredient>chicken</ingredient> into joints as for a fricasee, season it well with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> lay it into a <implement>pudding-dish</implement> lined with slices of <ingredient>ham</ingredient> or <ingredient>bacon,</ingredient> add a pint of <ingredient>veal gravy,</ingredient> and an <ingredient>onion</ingredient> finely minced; fill up the dish with <ingredient>boiled rice</ingredient> well pressed and piled as high as the dish will hold, cover it with a <ingredient>paste of flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and bake one hour in a 



 



<pb n="42" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=62"/>







slow oven. If you have no veal gravy use <ingredient>water</ingredient> instead, adding a little more <ingredient>ham</ingredient> and <ingredient>seasoning.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO ROAST A GOOSE.</purpose>







Geese seem to bear the same relation to poultry that pork does to the flesh of other domestic quadrupeds; that is, the flesh of goose is not suitable for, or agreeable to, the very delicate in constitution. One reason doubtless is, that it is the fashion to bring it to table very rare done; a detestable mode!</p>



<p>Take a young <ingredient>goose,</ingredient> pick, singe, and clean well. Make the <ingredient>stuffing</ingredient> with two ounces of <ingredient>onions</ingredient> (about four common sized), and one ounce of <ingredient>green sage</ingredient> chopped very fine; then add a large coffee cup of <ingredient>stale bread crumbs,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a bit of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> as big as a walnut, the <ingredient>yolk of an egg</ingredient> or two; mix these well together and stuff the <ingredient>goose;</ingredient> do not fill it entirely; the <ingredient>stuffing</ingredient> requires room to swell. Spit it; tie the spit at both ends to prevent its swinging round, and to keep the <ingredient>stuffing</ingredient> from coming out. The fire must be brisk. Baste it with <ingredient>salt and water</ingredient> at first--then with its own dripping. It will take two hours or more to roast it thoroughly.</p>



<p>A green <ingredient>goose,</ingredient> that is one under four months old, is seasoned with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> instead of sage and onions. It will roast in an hour.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">DUCK, TO ROAST,</purpose>







May be stuffed the same as a goose. It will roast in an hour, or less if it be young.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">DUCK, TO STEW.</purpose>







Cut one or two <ingredient>ducks</ingredient> into quarters; fry them a light brown in <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> put them into a saucepan, with a pint of <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> four <ingredient>onions</ingredient> whole, <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and some <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a bunch of <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> two <ingredient>sage leaves,</ingredient> a sprig of <ingredient>winter savory,</ingredient> and <ingredient>sweet marjoram.</ingredient> Cover the pan closely, and stew them till tender; take out the herbs and pepper; skim it; if the <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> be not sufficiently thick, mix with two table-spoonfuls of it a little <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and stir it into the saucepan; boil it up, and garnish the dish with the four <ingredient>onions.</ingredient></p>



 



<pb n="43" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=63"/>







<p>Both <ingredient>geese</ingredient> and <ingredient>ducks,</ingredient> if old, are better to be parboiled before they are roasted. Put them on in just sufficient <ingredient>water</ingredient> to boil them; keep the vessel close covered; let a tough <ingredient>goose</ingredient> simmer two hours, then dry and wipe it clean; stuff and roast, basting it at first with a little <ingredient>bacon fat</ingredient> or <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PIGEONS.</purpose>







About the only birds in New England worth cooking, are the pigeon and partridge. A few quails and woodcocks are occasionally found; the robin is sometimes killed; but it is a sin against feeling to destroy a singing bird--one, too, so innocent and gentle. Any one who kills a robin to eat, ought to have it hung round his neck as the albatross was around the "Ancient Mariner."</p>



<p>Pigeons are dry and easily digested food, but not quite so delicate as partridges. For the sick, the latter are very appropriate, and may be eaten, if good, (they are sometimes almost poisonous, in the early spring, supposed to be caused by feeding on a certain berry,) when other meats would be injurious.</p>



<p><ingredient>Pigeons</ingredient> may be broiled like chickens, or roasted, only tying over the breast thin slices of <ingredient>fat bacon.</ingredient> When the bird is nearly done, then remove the bacon; dredge with <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> baste with a little <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>froth.</ingredient> They will roast in about half an hour. They may be stuffed or not, as you like. Make a <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> with the <ingredient>giblets,</ingredient> mixed with <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> seasoned with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and thickened with a little <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO STEW PIGEONS.</purpose>







Wash and clean six <ingredient>pigeons,</ingredient> cut them into quarters, and put all their <ingredient>giblets</ingredient> with them into a <implement>stew-pan,</implement> a piece of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> a bit of <ingredient>lemon peel,</ingredient> two blades of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> some chopped <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper;</ingredient> cover the pan closely, and stew them till they are tender; thicken the <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> with the <ingredient>yolk of an egg</ingredient> beaten up with three table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> and a bit of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> dusted with <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> let them stew ten minutes longer before serving. This is an excellent and economical way of cooking them.</p>



<p>Partridges may be roasted like pigeons; but they are better stewed, because such dry meat.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO STEW PARTRIDGES.</purpose>







Truss the <ingredient>partridges</ingredient> as fowls are done for boiling; pound the <ingredient>livers</ingredient> with double the quantity of <ingredient>fat bacon</ingredient> and <ingredient>bread crumbs</ingredient> boiled in <ingredient>milk;</ingredient> and some <ingredient>chopped parsley,</ingredient> and <ingredient>mushrooms;</ingredient> season with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> grated <ingredient>lemon-peel,</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace.</ingredient> Stuff the inside of the birds, tie them at both ends, and put them into a <implement>stew-pan</implement> lined with slices of <ingredient>bacon;</ingredient> add a quart of good <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> if you have it, otherwise <ingredient>water,</ingredient> two <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> a bunch of <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> and a few blades of <ingredient>mace;</ingredient> let them stew gently till tender; take them out, strain and thicken the <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> with <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> make it hot, and pour it over the <ingredient>partridges.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PICKLE FOR BEEF.</purpose>







Allow to four gallons of <ingredient>water</ingredient> two pounds of <ingredient>brown sugar</ingredient> and six pounds of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> boil it about twenty minutes, 



 



<pb n="45" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=65"/>







taking off the skum as it rises; the following day pour it over the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> which has been packed into the pickling-tub. Boil it every two months, adding three ounces of <ingredient>brown sugar</ingredient> and half a pound of <ingredient>common salt.</ingredient> By this means it will keep good a year. The <ingredient>meat</ingredient> must be sprinkled with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and the next day wiped dry, before pouring the <ingredient>pickle</ingredient> over it, with which it should always be completely covered. You must add four ounces of <ingredient>saltpetre.</ingredient> The same <ingredient>pickle</ingredient> will do for <ingredient>tongues</ingredient> and <ingredient>hams.</ingredient></p>



<p>Canvas lids should be placed over salting tubs, to admit air and exclude flies, which are more destructive to salting meat than to fresh.</p>



<p>Care must be taken to secure bacon and hams from the fly. The best method is, to put them in coarse calico or canvas bags; paper is apt to break in damp weather. Always keep smoked meat in a dark place.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO SALT FAT PORK.</purpose>







Pack it down tightly in the barrel, each layer of <ingredient>pork</ingredient> covered with clean <ingredient>coarse salt;</ingredient> then make a strong <ingredient>brine</ingredient> with two gallons of <ingredient>water</ingredient> and as much <ingredient>coarse salt</ingredient> as will dissolve in it; boil and skim; let it stand till it is perfectly cold, and then pour it to the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> till that is covered. <ingredient>Pork</ingredient> is best without sugar or saltpetre, provided it be always kept covered with this strong <ingredient>brine.</ingredient></p>



<p>An excellent way to keep fresh meat during the winter, is practised by the farmers in the country, which they term "salting in snow." Take a large clean tub, cover the bottom three or four inches thick with clean snow; then lay in pieces of fresh meat, spare-ribs, fowls, or whatever you wish to keep, and cover each layer with two or three inches of snow, taking particular care to fill snow into every cranny and crevice between the pieces, and around the edges of the tub. Fowls must also be filled inside with the snow. When the tub is filled the last layer must be snow, pressed down tight; then cover the tub, which must be in a cold place, the colder the better. The <ingredient>meat</ingredient> will not freeze, and unless there happen to be a long <emph rend="italic">spell</emph> of warm weather, the snow will not thaw; but the meat remain as fresh and juicy when it is taken out to be cooked, as when it was first killed.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="soups">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">MOCK TURTLE SOUP.</purpose>







<ref target="n005">*</ref> Scald and clean thoroughly a calve's <ingredient>head</ingredient> with the skin on; boil it gently one hour in four quarts of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> skimming it well. Take out the head, and when almost cold, cut the meat off and divide it into bits about an inch square.</p>



<p>Slice and fry of a light brown in <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> two pounds of the <ingredient>leg of beef,</ingredient> and two of <ingredient>veal</ingredient> with five <ingredient>onions</ingredient> cut small and two ounces of <ingredient>green sage.</ingredient>--Add these to the liquor in which the <ingredient>head</ingredient> was boiled, also the <ingredient>bones</ingredient> of the <ingredient>head</ingredient> and trimmings, two whole <ingredient>onions;</ingredient> a handful of <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> one teaspoonful of <ingredient>ground allspice</ingredient> and two of <ingredient>black pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to your taste, and the <ingredient>rind</ingredient> of one <ingredient>lemon;</ingredient> let it simmer and stew gently for three hours--then strain it and when cold take off the fat. Put the liquor into a clean <implement>stew-pan,</implement> add the meat cut from the <ingredient>head,</ingredient> and for a gallon of soup add half a pint of <ingredient>madeira wine,</ingredient> or <ingredient>claret,</ingredient> and some mix a spoonful of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> with a little of the <ingredient>broth</ingredient> and stir it in. Let it stew very gently till the meat is tender, which will be about an hour.</p>



<p>About twenty minutes before it is to be served, add a small tea-spoonful of <ingredient>cayenne,</ingredient> the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> of eight or ten <ingredient>hard boiled eggs</ingredient> and a dozen <ingredient>force-meat balls;</ingredient> some add the <ingredient>juice of a lemon.</ingredient> When the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> is tender, the soup is done.</p>



<p>To make the meat balls, boil the <ingredient>brains</ingredient> for ten minutes, then put them in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> when cool chop and mix them with five spoonfuls of <ingredient>grated bread,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>grated nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>thyme</ingredient> and two <ingredient>eggs;</ingredient> roll the balls as 



 



<pb n="49" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=69"/>







large as the yolk of an egg and fry them of a light brown in <ingredient>butter</ingredient> or good dripping.</p>



<p id="n005" size="smaller">{footnote}*There is no use in a receipt for making the <emph rend="italic">real turtle</emph>--that is so seldom done in a family.</p>



<ednote>The Following Footnote Appears at the End of Page 48 in the Original Text.</ednote>



<p>Very good soup in imitation of turtle is also made from <ingredient>calves' feet.</ingredient> Four of these boiled in two quarts of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> till very tender--the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> taken from the <ingredient>bones,</ingredient> the liquor strained--a pint of good <ingredient>beef gravy</ingredient> and two glasses of <ingredient>wine</ingredient> added, seasoned as the <ingredient>calves' head</ingredient> soup--with <ingredient>hard eggs, balls,</ingredient> &amp;c.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="soups">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CURRIE SOUP.</purpose>







Make about two quarts of strong <ingredient>veal broth,</ingredient> seasoned with two <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> a bunch of <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper;</ingredient> strain it, and have ready a <ingredient>chicken,</ingredient> cut in joints and skinned; put it into the <ingredient>broth,</ingredient> with a table-spoonful of currie-powder; boil the <ingredient>chicken</ingredient> till quite tender, a little before serving, add the <ingredient>juice of a lemon,</ingredient> and stir in a teacupful of <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Serve<ingredient> boiled rice</ingredient> to eat with this broth.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="soups">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">VEAL SOUP.</purpose>







Skin four pounds of a <ingredient>knuckle of veal,</ingredient> break, and cut it small, put it into a <implement>stew-pan</implement> with two gallons of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> when it boils skim it, and let it simmer till reduced to two quarts; strain, and season it with <ingredient>white pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> a dessert-spoonful of <ingredient>lemon juice,</ingredient> and thicken it with a large table-spoonful of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> kneaded with an ounce of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="soups">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BEEF OR MUTTON SOUP.</purpose>







Boil very gently in a closely covered saucepan, four quarts of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and two table-spoonfuls of sifted <ingredient>bread crumbs,</ingredient> with three pounds of <ingredient>beef</ingredient> cut in small pieces, or the same quantity of <ingredient>mutton</ingredient> chops taken from the middle of the <ingredient>neck;</ingredient> season with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> add two <ingredient>turnips,</ingredient> two <ingredient>carrots,</ingredient> two <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> and one head of <ingredient>celery,</ingredient> all cut small; let it stew with these ingredients four hours, when it will be ready to serve.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="soups">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">WHITE SOUP.</purpose>







Take a good <ingredient>knuckle of veal,</ingredient> or two or three short shanks, boil it about four hours, with some whole <ingredient>white pepper,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> two <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> and a small bit of 



 



<pb n="50" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=70"/>







<ingredient>lean ham;</ingredient> strain it, and when cold take off all the fat and sediment; beat up six <ingredient>yolks of eggs</ingredient> and mix them with a pint of good <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> then pour the boiling soup upon it by degrees, stiring it well, and if it is liked, add the best part of the gristles.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="soups">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PIGEON SOUP.</purpose>







Take eight <ingredient>pigeons,</ingredient> cut down two of the oldest, and put them with the <ingredient>necks,</ingredient> <ingredient>pinions,</ingredient> <ingredient>livers,</ingredient> and <ingredient>gizzards</ingredient> of the others, into four quarts of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> let it boil till the substance is extracted, and strain it; season the <ingredient>pigeons</ingredient> with <ingredient>mixed spices</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and truss them as for stewing; pick and wash clean a handful of <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> <ingredient>chives</ingredient> or young <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> and a good deal of <ingredient>spinach,</ingredient> chop them; put in a frying-pan a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and when it boils, mix in a handful of <ingredient>bread crumbs,</ingredient> keep stirring them with a knife till of a fine brown; boil the whole <ingredient>pigeons</ingredient> till they become tender in the soup with the <ingredient>herbs,</ingredient> and <ingredient>fried bread.</ingredient> If the soup be not sufficiently high seasoned, add more <ingredient>mixed spices</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="soups">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">VEGETABLE SOUP.</purpose>







Pare and cut small one dozen of common-sized <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> five large yellow <ingredient>turnips,</ingredient> two heads of <ingredient>celery,</ingredient> and the red part of three large <ingredient>carrots;</ingredient> wash and put them in a <implement>stew-pan</implement> with two ounces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> cover it closely; and when the vegetables are a little soft, add to them four quarts of well seasoned <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> soup made of <ingredient>roast beef bones,</ingredient> and let it stew four or five hours; rub it through a sieve, put it on the fire, boil and skim it before serving.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="soups">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">RICE SOUP.</purpose>







Boil in four quarts of <ingredient>water</ingredient> the scrag end of a <ingredient>neck of veal</ingredient> and one pound of <ingredient>lean ham,</ingredient> till it is reduced nearly half; carefully skimming it, season with <ingredient>white pepper,</ingredient> and two blades of <ingredient>mace.</ingredient> Wash very clean three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>rice,</ingredient> strain the soup, and boil the <ingredient>rice</ingredient> in it till it is tender.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="soups">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">OLD PEAS SOUP.</purpose>







Put a pound and a half of <ingredient>split peas</ingredient> on in four quarts of 



 



<pb n="51" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=71"/>







<ingredient>water,</ingredient> with <ingredient>roast beef</ingredient> or <ingredient>mutton bones,</ingredient> and a <ingredient>ham bone,</ingredient> two heads of <ingredient>celery,</ingredient> and four <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> let them boil till the <ingredient>peas</ingredient> are sufficiently soft to pulp through a sieve, strain it, put it into the pot with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and boil it nearly one hour. Two or three handsful of <ingredient>spinach,</ingredient> well washed and cut a little, added when the soup is strained, is a great improvement; and in the summer young <ingredient>green peas</ingredient> in place of the spinach. A tea-spoonful of <ingredient>celery seed,</ingredient> or <ingredient>essence of celery,</ingredient> if celery is not to be had.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="medhealth" class2="soups">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">SOUP FOR AN INVALID.</purpose>







Cut in small pieces one pound of <ingredient>beef</ingredient> or <ingredient>mutton,</ingredient> or part of both; boil it gently in two quarts of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> take off the scum, and when reduced to a pint, strain it. Season with a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and take a teacupful at a time.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="inline">MELTED BUTTER.</purpose>







Always use <ingredient>sweet butter;</ingredient> if in the least injured, it spoils the gravy. To make it of the best quality,--cut two ounces of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into little bits, put these in a clean <implement>stew-pan,</implement> with a large teaspoonful of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and a table-spoonful of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></p>



<p>When thoroughly melted and mixed, add six table-spoonfuls 



 



<pb n="52" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=72"/>







of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> hold it over the fire, and shake it round every minute (all the time one way) till it just begins to simmer, then let it stand quietly and boil up. It should be of the thickness of good <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">EGG SAUCE</purpose>







is made by putting two or three <ingredient>hard boiled eggs,</ingredient> minced fine, into <ingredient>melted butter</ingredient>--The <ingredient>butter</ingredient> need not be as thick when <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> are to be added.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">PARSLEY AND BUTTER</purpose>







is made by adding <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> that has been boiled a few minutes and chopped fine, to the <ingredient>melted butter.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">WHITE SAUCE FOR BOILED FOWLS.</purpose>







Melt in a teacupful of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> a large table-spoonful of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> kneaded in a little <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> beat up the <ingredient>yolk of an egg</ingredient> with a teaspoonful of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> stir into the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and put it over the fire, stirring it constantly; <ingredient>chopped parsley</ingredient> may be added.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">CAPER SAUCE </purpose>







is made by adding one or two spoonfuls of <ingredient>capers</ingredient> to <ingredient>melted butter.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">OYSTER SAUCE.</purpose>







Beard and scald the <ingredient>oysters,</ingredient> strain the liquor, and thicken it with a little <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> squeeze in a little <ingredient>lemon juice,</ingredient> and add three table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Heat it well, but do not let it boil.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">BREAD SAUCE. </purpose>







Boil a half pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and put into it a teacupful of <ingredient>bread crumbs</ingredient> a little powdered, a small chopped <ingredient>onion</ingredient> which has been boiled in three waters, and let it simmer twenty minutes; then add a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> as large as a walnut, boil up and serve.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TOMATO SAUCE.</purpose>







Peel and <implement>slice</implement> twelve <ingredient>tomatoes,</ingredient> picking out the <ingredient>seeds;</ingredient> add three pounded <ingredient>crackers,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to your taste, stew twenty minutes.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TOMATO CATSUP.</purpose>







Take two quarts skinned <ingredient>tomatoes</ingredient>--two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>salt</ingredient>--same of <ingredient>black pepper,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>allspice;</ingredient> four pods of <ingredient>red pepper,</ingredient> two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>ground mustard;</ingredient> mix and rub these thoroughly together; and stew them slowly, in a pint of <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> for three hours--then strain the liquor through a sieve, and simmer it down to one quart of catshup. Put this in bottles and cork it tight.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">COD'S HEAD AND SHOULDERS, TO BOIL.</purpose>







Wash it clean; tie it up, and dry it with a cloth. Allow in the proportion of every five measures of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> when it boils take off the scum; put in the <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> and keep it boiling very fast for twentyfive or thirty minutes. 



 



<pb n="54" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=74"/>







Serve with the <ingredient>roe</ingredient> and milt parboiled, cut into slices and fried, and garnish with curled <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> and <ingredient>horse-radish.</ingredient> Sauces;--<ingredient>oyster,</ingredient> <ingredient>melted butter,</ingredient> or <ingredient>egg.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO CRIMP COD.</purpose>







Cut a fresh <ingredient>cod</ingredient> into slices or steaks; lay them for three hours in <ingredient>salt and water,</ingredient> and a glass of <ingredient>vinegar;</ingredient> when they may be boiled, fried, or broiled, as you please.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">COD SOUNDS.</purpose>







This is reckoned a great delicacy: and may be either boiled, baked, roasted or broiled. Previous to cooking in any way they must be well soaked, the black skin all picked off and washed clean; then parboiled. If broiled, dust with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> season with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Put a table spoonful of <ingredient>catsup</ingredient> into a little <ingredient>melted butter</ingredient> for the <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> or stew with <ingredient>bread crumbs</ingredient> and fry them.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO BOIL FRESH SALMON.</purpose>







<ingredient>Salmon</ingredient> requires more boiling and in a larger quantity of <ingredient>water</ingredient> than any other kind of fish. It must be thoroughly done, or it is very unhealthy.</p>



<p>Make the <ingredient>water</ingredient> strong with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> let it boil, skim and put in the <ingredient>salmon;</ingredient> continue to skim off all the scum that rises. A piece weighing half a pound requires fifteen minutes. Sauces--<ingredient>lobster,</ingredient> <ingredient>egg</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO PICKLE SALMON.</purpose>







To a quart of liquor the <ingredient>fish</ingredient> has been boiled in, put rather more than half a pint of <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> and half an ounce of whole <ingredient>black pepper;</ingredient> boil it, and when it is cold pour it over the <ingredient>fish</ingredient> previously laid in a deep dish.</p>



<p>This is a good way to dress the <ingredient>salmon</ingredient> left after a dinner. If you boil it purposely to pickle, do not remove the scales, it keeps better.</p>



<p>Pour a little <ingredient>sweet oil</ingredient> over the top of the <ingredient>pickle,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>fish</ingredient> will keep good for months.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO BROIL SALMON.</purpose>







Cut it in slices about an inch and a half thick, dry it in a<pb n="55" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=75"/>







clean cloth, sprinkle over a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient>--put your <implement>gridiron</implement> over a clear but not very hot fire, when the bars are warm rub them with <ingredient>sweet oil</ingredient> or <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> lay the <ingredient>salmon</ingredient> on, and when done on one side, turn it gently and broil the other.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO BOIL MACKEREL.</purpose>







The excellence of <ingredient>mackerel</ingredient> is to have it fresh as possible--it must be cleaned nicely--put it into sufficient <ingredient>water</ingredient> to cover it--(a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> should be sprinkled in the <ingredient>water</ingredient>) and let it rather simmer than boil. A small <ingredient>mackerel</ingredient> will be done in fifteen minutes.--Do not allow them to stand in the <ingredient>water</ingredient> a moment after they are done.</p>



<p><ingredient>Trout,</ingredient> <ingredient>perch</ingredient> and <ingredient>bass</ingredient> are boiled in the same manner.</p>



<p><ingredient>Melted butter</ingredient> is used for boiled fish.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO BROIL MACKEREL.</purpose>







Clean and split them open; wipe dry; lay them on a clean <implement>gridiron,</implement> rubbed with <ingredient>suet</ingredient> over a very clear slow fire--turn, season with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>butter</ingredient>--fine minced <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> is also used.</p>



<p><ingredient>Trout</ingredient> and <ingredient>perch</ingredient> are broiled in the same way.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO BROIL A SHAD.</purpose>







This is a delicate and delicious <ingredient>fish</ingredient>--Clean, wash, and split the <ingredient>shad,</ingredient> and wipe it dry; sprinkle it with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and broil it like mackerel.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO FRY COD OR OTHER FISH.</purpose>







It is much more difficult to fry fish than meat.</p>



<p><ingredient>Lard</ingredient> or <ingredient>dripping</ingredient> is better than butter, because the last burns so easily. The <ingredient>fat</ingredient> fried from <ingredient>salt pork</ingredient> is best of all.</p>



<p>The fire must be clear and hot but not furious; the <ingredient>fat</ingredient> hot when the <ingredient>fish</ingredient> is put in, and there should be sufficient to cover the <ingredient>fish.</ingredient> Skim the <ingredient>fat</ingredient> before laying in the <ingredient>fish.</ingredient></p>



<p>Cut the <ingredient>cod</ingredient> in slices half or three quarters of an inch thick; rub them with <ingredient>indian meal</ingredient> to prevent breaking, fry it thoroughly.</p>



<p><ingredient>Trout</ingredient> and <ingredient>perch</ingredient> are fried in the same manner; only do not rub indian meal on them--dip in <ingredient>white of an egg</ingredient> and <ingredient>bread crumbs</ingredient> or dust with <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO MAKE CHOWDER.</purpose>







Lay some slices cut from the fat part of <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> in a deep <implement>stew-pan,</implement> mix sliced <ingredient>onions</ingredient> with a variety of <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> and lay them on the <ingredient>pork.</ingredient> Bone and cut a fresh <ingredient>cod</ingredient> into thin slices, and place them on the <ingredient>pork;</ingredient> then put a layer of <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> on that a layer of <ingredient>biscuit,</ingredient> then alternately the other materials until the pan is nearly full, season with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> put in about a pint and a half of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> cover the <implement>stew-pan</implement> very close, and let it stand, with fire above as well as below, for four hours; then skim it well, and it is done.</p>



<p>This is an excellent dish and healthy, if not eaten <emph rend="italic">too hot.</emph></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">SHELL FISH.</purpose>







Oysters and clams generally agree well with those who like them; but lobster must be eaten cautiously. It is very apt to disagree with delicate stomachs.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO FRY OYSTERS.</purpose>







Make a batter as for pancakes, seasoned with <ingredient>grated nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>white pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and add some <ingredient>finely grated bread crumbs;</ingredient> dip in the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> and fry them of a light brown. Or, dip them into the <ingredient>white of an egg</ingredient> beat up, then roll them in <ingredient>bread crumbs,</ingredient> seasoned with a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO STEW OYSTERS.</purpose>







Open and take the liquor from them, cleanse them from grit, strain the liquor and add the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon peel,</ingredient> a bit of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and a few <ingredient>white peppers.</ingredient> Simmer them very gently for eight or ten minutes. Toast thin slices of <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> lay these at the bottom of a dish and pour the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> over.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO SCALLOP OYSTERS.</purpose>







Take off the beards; stew them in their liquor strained with a little <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> fry some <ingredient>grated bread crumbs</ingredient> in a little <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> till of a nice brown; put the crumbs alternately with the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> into a dish and serve.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO STEW LOBSTERS.</purpose>







A middling sized <ingredient>lobster</ingredient> is best--pick all the meat from the shells and mince it fine; season with a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>grated nutmeg,</ingredient> add three or four spoons of rich <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> and a small bit of <ingredient>butter</ingredient>--if you have no <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> use more <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and two spoonfuls of <ingredient>vinegar;</ingredient> stew about twenty minutes.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">LOBSTER COLD.</purpose>







It is frequently eaten in this way, with a dressing of <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> <ingredient>mustard,</ingredient> <ingredient>sweet oil,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>cayenne.</ingredient></p>



<p>The meat of the <ingredient>lobster</ingredient> must be minced very fine--and care must be taken to <emph rend="italic">eat but little</emph> of the dish.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose rend="italic" align="center" placement="inline">To boil Potatoes in the best manner,</purpose>







is a very great perfection in cookery. The following way is a good one. Take <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> as nearly equal in size as possible, wash, but do not pare or cut them; put them into a pot, the largest <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> at the bottom, cover them with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and about one inch over. Too much <ingredient>water</ingredient> injures them very much.</p>



<p>Throw in a spoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and let them boil about five minutes, then take off the pot and set it where it will simmer slowly for thirty minutes--then try the <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> with a fork; if it passes easily through they are done; if not, let them simmer till they are; then pour off the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> place the pot where the <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> will keep hot, but not burn, 



 



<pb n="61" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=81"/>







and let them stand, <emph rend="italic">uncovered,</emph> till the moisture has evaporated. Then they are mealy and in perfection.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose rend="italic" align="center" placement="inline">To roast Potatoes.</purpose>







--Choose all of a size, wash clean and rinse; put them on a tin and bake them in a stove, or <implement>Dutch oven.</implement> It takes nearly two hours. Send them to the table with the <ingredient>skins</ingredient> on. They are excellent with <ingredient>cold meat,</ingredient> and healthy food for children, mashed with a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">ANOTHER WAY TO BOIL POTATOES.</purpose>







Pare, wash and throw them into a pan of <ingredient>cold water;</ingredient> then put them on to boil in a clean pot with <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> sufficient to cover them, and sprinkle over a little <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> let them boil slowly <emph rend="italic">uncovered</emph> till you can pass a fork through them; pour off the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and set them where they will keep hot till wanted.--When done in this way they are very mealy and dry.</p>



<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Potatoes</ingredient></emph> either boiled or roasted, should <emph rend="italic">never be covered</emph> to keep them hot.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">MASHED POTATOES.</purpose>







When old, <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> are best <emph rend="italic">boiled and mashed,</emph> with a little <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> or <ingredient>milk.</ingredient>--They may be also sliced and fried raw, in hot <ingredient>salt-pork fat</ingredient>--or after they are boiled--Both these dishes are relished. But a plain, boiled, or roasted <ingredient>potato,</ingredient> when well cooked, is the best and most healthy; and though not a substitute for bread, it is one of the most useful vegetable productions.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">TURNIPS </purpose>







should be pared; put into <ingredient>water</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> boiled till tender; then squeeze them thoroughly from the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> mash them smooth, add a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">CABBAGE </purpose>







requires to be well washed before it is cooked; boil it in a large quantity of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> till it is soft and tender; skim the <ingredient>water</ingredient> carefully when it first boils. If the head is large, cut it--but a small head is the best.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">ONIONS</purpose>







are best boiled in <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>water.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">BEETS </purpose>







should be washed clean but never cut--put in <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and cooked till very tender.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">CARROTS</purpose>







may be cut if too large; put in <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">PARSNIPS </purpose>







must be washed and scraped very clean, boiled like carrots.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">GREEN PEAS </purpose>







should be young and fresh-shelled, wash them clean, put them on in plenty of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and a teaspoonful of <ingredient>pounded loaf sugar.</ingredient> Boil till tender.</p>



<p><ingredient>Green peas</ingredient> are a most delicious vegetable when cooked enough, but half-done, hard things, are very unhealthy. It takes from half an hour to an hour to boil them. Never let them stand in the <ingredient>water</ingredient> after they are done. Season with a little <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO STEW YOUNG PEAS AND LETTUCE.</purpose>







Wash and make perfectly clean one or two heads of <ingredient>cabbage lettuce,</ingredient> pick off the outside leaves, and lay them for two hours in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> in it; then <implement>slice</implement> them, and put them into a saucepan, with a quart or three pints of <ingredient>peas,</ingredient> three table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> a bit of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> dredged with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> some <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and a teaspoonful of <ingredient>pounded loaf sugar.</ingredient> Let them stew, closely covered, till the <ingredient>peas</ingredient> are soft.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">GREEN BEANS OR STRING BEANS</purpose>







, as they are usually called, must be done till very tender--it takes nearly an hour and a half. Put them on in <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> after they have been prepared and well washed.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">GREENS</purpose>







of all kinds, <ingredient>spinach,</ingredient> <ingredient>beet-tops,</ingredient> &amp;c. must be put in when the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">SQUASH </purpose>







is a rich vegetable, particularly the yellow winter <ingredient>squash.</ingredient>--This requires more boiling than the summer kind. Pare it, cut in pieces, take out the <ingredient>seeds</ingredient> and boil it in a very little <ingredient>water</ingredient> till it is quite soft. Then <implement>press</implement> out all the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> mash it and add a little <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">TO STEW CUCUMBERS.</purpose>







Pare eight or ten large <ingredient>cucumbers,</ingredient> and cut them into thick slices, <ingredient>flour</ingredient> them well, and fry them in <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> then put them into a saucepan with a teacupful of <ingredient>gravy;</ingredient> season it with <ingredient>cayenne,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>catsup.</ingredient> Let them stew for an hour and serve them hot.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">ARROW-ROOT PUDDING.</purpose>







From a quart of <ingredient>new milk</ingredient> take a small teacupful, and mix it with two large spoonfuls of <ingredient>arrow-root.</ingredient> Boil the remainder of the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and stir it amongst the <ingredient>arrow-root;</ingredient> add, when nearly cold, four well beaten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> with two ounces of <ingredient>pounded loaf sugar,</ingredient> and the same of fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> broken into small bits; season with <ingredient>grated nutmeg.</ingredient> Mix it well together, and bake it in a buttered dish fifteen or twenty minutes.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading">SAGO PUDDING.</purpose>







Boil five table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>sago,</ingredient> well picked and washed, in a quart of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> till quite soft, with a stick of <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient> Then stir in one teacup of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and two of <ingredient>powdered loaf sugar.</ingredient>--When it is cold add six <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beaten, and a little <ingredient>grated nutmeg.</ingredient> Mix all well together, and bake it in a buttered dish about three quarters of an hour. <ingredient>Brown sugar,</ingredient> if dried will answer very well to sweeten it.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading">TAPIOCA PUDDING.</purpose>







Wash four large table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>tapioca,</ingredient> and soak it for an hour in a little <ingredient>warm water;</ingredient> strain it through a sieve, and mix it with the well beaten <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> of four, and the <ingredient>whites of two eggs,</ingredient> a quart of good <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>grated nutmeg,</ingredient> and sweeten it with <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Bake it in a dish, with or without <ingredient>puff paste</ingredient> round the edges, one hour.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading">RICE PUDDING BAKED OR BOILED.</purpose>







Wash in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and pick very clean six ounces of <ingredient>rice;</ingredient> boil it in one quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> with a bit of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> very gently, till it is quite tender; it will take about an hour; be careful to stir it often. Take it from the fire, pick out the <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> and stir in a teacupful of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a cup of 



 



<pb n="65" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=85"/>







<ingredient>butter,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beaten, a little <ingredient>powdered nutmeg</ingredient>--stir it till it is quite smooth. You can line a <implement>pie-dish</implement> with <ingredient>puff paste,</ingredient> or bake it in a buttered dish which is better,--about three quarters of an hour will bake it.</p>



<p>If you wish it more like custard, add one more <ingredient>egg</ingredient> and half a pint of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></p>



<p>If you boil it you can add whatever <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> you like,--three ounces of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> or <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> or <ingredient>apples</ingredient> minced fine; it will take an hour to boil it.</p>



<p>Serve with <ingredient>wine sauce</ingredient> or <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading">RICE BLANCMANGE.</purpose>







Simmer a teacupful of <ingredient>whole rice</ingredient> into the least <ingredient>water</ingredient> possible, till it almost bursts, then add half a pint of good <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or thin <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and boil it till it is quite a mash, stirring it the whole time it is on the fire, that it may not burn. Dip a mould in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and pour the hot <ingredient>rice</ingredient> in and let it stand till cold, when it will come easily out.</p>



<p>This dish may be eaten with <ingredient>cream</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> or <ingredient>custard</ingredient> and <ingredient>preserved fruits;</ingredient> <ingredient>raspberries</ingredient> are best. It should be made the day before it is wanted.</p>



<p>It can be flavored with <ingredient>spices,</ingredient> <ingredient>lemon-peel,</ingredient> &amp;c; and sweetened with a little <ingredient>loaf sugar;</ingredient> it is then very excellent.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading">ARROW-ROOT BLANCMANGE.</purpose>







Dissolve a teacupful of <ingredient>arrow-root</ingredient> in a little <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> take one pint of <ingredient>new milk,</ingredient> and one pint <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> boil it for a few minutes with six blades of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> pounded--then add a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and boil all together for ten minutes. Strain it over the <ingredient>arrow-root,</ingredient> and stir it till it is cool--then wet the mould and pour it in; it will be congealed when it is cold.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading">RICE SNOW BALLS.</purpose>







Boil some <ingredient>rice</ingredient> in <ingredient>milk</ingredient> till it is swelled and soft; pare and carefully scoop out the core of five or six good-sized <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> put into each a little <ingredient>grated lemon-peel</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon;</ingredient> place as much of the <ingredient>rice</ingredient> upon a bit of linen as will entirely cover an <ingredient>apple,</ingredient> and tie each closely. Boil them 



 



<pb n="66" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=86"/>







two hours, and serve them with <ingredient>melted butter,</ingredient> sweetened with <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">BATTER PUDDING.</purpose>







Take six ounces of <ingredient>fine flour,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and three <ingredient>eggs;</ingredient> beat up well with a little <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> added by degrees till the batter is quite smooth; make it the thickness of <ingredient>cream;</ingredient> put into a buttered <implement>pie-dish,</implement> and bake three quarters of an hour; or in a buttered and floured basin, tied over tight with a cloth: boil one hour and a half, or two hours.</p>



<p>Any kind of <ingredient>ripe fruit</ingredient> that you like may be added to the batter,--only you must make the batter a little stiffer. <ingredient>Blueberries</ingredient> or finely chopped <ingredient>apple</ingredient> are most usually liked.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">POTATO PUDDING.</purpose>







Boil three large mealy <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> mash them very smoothly, with one ounce of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and two or three table-spoonfuls of thick <ingredient>cream;</ingredient> add three well beaten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> grated <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and a table-spoonful of <ingredient>brown sugar.</ingredient> Beat all well together, and bake it in a buttered dish, for half or three quarters of an hour in a <implement>Dutch oven.</implement> A few <ingredient>currants</ingredient> may be added to the pudding.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">SWEET POTATO PUDDING.</purpose>







Boil the <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> and mash them very smooth. To two cups full of <ingredient>potato</ingredient> add one cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one glass of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> five <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and the <ingredient>grated rind of lemon.</ingredient> Bake with an under crust.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PLAIN BREAD PUDDING.</purpose>







Pour a pint of boiling <ingredient>milk</ingredient> over four ounces of <ingredient>bread crumbs,</ingredient> cover it till cold, and mix with it three well beaten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a table-spoonful of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and half the peel of a <ingredient>grated lemon,</ingredient> or a little <ingredient>pounded cinnamon;</ingredient> bake it in a buttered dish, and serve with <ingredient>sweet sauce.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="eggscheesedairy">



<p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">CUSTARD PUDDING.</purpose>







Mix with one table-spoonful of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> or <ingredient>new milk,</ingredient> a spoonful of <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> one ounce of fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> broken in small bits; sweeten with <ingredient>pounded loaf sugar,</ingredient> 



 



<pb n="67" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=87"/>







and add a little <ingredient>grated nutmeg.</ingredient> Bake it in a buttered dish for half an hour. Before serving, you can strew over it <ingredient>pounded loaf sugar,</ingredient> and stick over it thin cut bits of <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> if you wish it to look very rich.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">RICH APPLE PUDDING.</purpose>







Peel and core six very large <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> stew them in six table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with the <ingredient>rind of a lemon;</ingredient> when soft, beat them to a pulp, add six ounces of good <ingredient>brown sugar,</ingredient> six well beaten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>rich cream,</ingredient> and a teaspoonful of <ingredient>lemon juice;</ingredient> line a dish with a <ingredient>puff paste,</ingredient> and when baked, stick all over the top thin chips of <ingredient>candied citron</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon-peel.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">DAMSON PUDDING.</purpose>







Make a batter with three well beaten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>brown sugar</ingredient> four table-spoonfuls each; stone a pint of <ingredient>damsons,</ingredient> and mix them with the batter; boil it in a buttered basin for an hour and a half.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">LEMON PUDDING.</purpose>







Boil in <ingredient>water,</ingredient> in a closely covered saucepan, two large <ingredient>lemons</ingredient> till quite tender; take out the seeds, and pound the <ingredient>lemons</ingredient> to a paste; add a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>pounded loaf sugar,</ingredient> the same of fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> beaten to a <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and three well beaten <ingredient>eggs;</ingredient> mix all together, and bake it in a tin lined with <ingredient>puff paste;</ingredient> take it out, strew over the top <ingredient>grated loaf sugar.</ingredient></p>



<p>As Christmas comes but once a year, a rich plum pudding may be permitted for the feast, though it is not healthy food; and children should be helped very sparingly. The following is a good receipt.</p>



<p>Chop half a pound of <ingredient>suet</ingredient> very fine; stone half a pound of <ingredient>raisins;</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>currants</ingredient> nicely washed and picked; four ounces of <ingredient>bread crumbs;</ingredient> four ounces of <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beaten; a little <ingredient>grated nutmeg</ingredient>--<ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> pounded very fine; half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> four ounces of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> one ounce <ingredient>candied lemon;</ingredient> same of <ingredient>citron.</ingredient></p>



<p>Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and <ingredient>spices</ingredient> well together; mix the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> with them by degrees, then the rest of the ingredients; dip a fine, close linen cloth into <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and place it 



 



<pb n="68" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=88"/>







in a <implement>hair sieve;</implement> <ingredient>flour</ingredient> it a little, then pour in the batter and tie it up close; put it into a pot containing six quarts of <ingredient>boiling water;</ingredient> keep a tea-kettle of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> and fill up your pot as it wastes; be sure to keep it boiling, at least six hours--seven would not injure it.</p>



<p>This pudding should be mixed an hour or too before it is put on to boil; it makes it taste richer.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PUFF PASTE.</purpose>







Weigh an equal quantity of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> rub rather more than the half of the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> then add as much <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> as will make it into a stiff <ingredient>paste;</ingredient> work it until the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> be completely mixed with the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> make it round, beat it with the rolling-pin, dust it, as also the rolling-pin, with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and roll it out towards the opposite side of the slab, or <implement>paste-board,</implement> making it of an equal thickness; then with the point of a knife put little bits of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> all over it, dust <ingredient>flour</ingredient> over and under it, fold in the sides and roll it up, dust it again with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> beat it a little, and roll it out, always rubbing the rolling--pin with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and throwing some underneath the <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> to prevent its sticking to the board. If the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is not all easily put in at the second time of rolling out the <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> the remainder may be put in at the third; it should be touched as little as possible with the hands.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TART PASTE.</purpose>







Rub into half a pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> six ounces of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and a table spoonful of <ingredient>powdered loaf sugar;</ingredient> make it into a stiff <ingredient>paste</ingredient> with <ingredient>hot water.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">SHORT PASTE FOR FRUIT PIES.</purpose>







Rub into three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>lard</ingredient> and a spoonful of <ingredient>grated sugar.</ingredient> Make it into a <ingredient>paste</ingredient> with <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> roll it out, and add a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> For a <ingredient>fruit tart</ingredient> it must be rolled out half an inch thick.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">RAISED CRUST.</purpose>







Melt in one pint of <ingredient>water</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>lard;</ingredient> put four pounds of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> in a pan and sprinkle over a large spoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and when the <ingredient>water</ingredient> and <ingredient>lard</ingredient> is hot, stir it with a spoon among the <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> When well mixed work it with the hands till it is a stiff <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> when it is fit for use.</p>



<p><ingredient>Beef drippings</ingredient> may be used to shorten pie-crust, but it must be well clarified. Allow half a pound of <ingredient>drippings</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">APPLE PIE.</purpose>







<ingredient>Apples</ingredient> of a pleasant sour and fully ripe make the best pies--pare, core and <implement>slice</implement> them, line a deep buttered dish with <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> lay in the <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> strewing in moist <ingredient>brown sugar</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>pounded lemon-peel</ingredient> or <ingredient>cinnamon;</ingredient> cover and bake about forty minutes. The oven must not be very hot.</p>



<p>When <ingredient>apples</ingredient> are green, stew them with a very little <ingredient>water</ingredient> before making your pie. <ingredient>Green fruit</ingredient> requires a double quantity of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p>



<p><ingredient>Gooseberries</ingredient> and <ingredient>green currants</ingredient> are made in the same manner.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">RHUBARB PIES.</purpose>







In England they call this "Spring fruit," which is a much more <emph rend="italic">relishing name than rhubarb.</emph></p>



<p>Peel off the skin from the young green stalks, and cut these into small pieces--put them in the pie with plenty of <ingredient>brown sugar,</ingredient> you can hardly put in too much. Cover the pie and bake like apple.</p>



<p>You may stew the "Spring fruit" very soft and make tarts.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">FRUIT PIES.</purpose>







When making pies from ripe summer fruits, such as <ingredient>raspberries,</ingredient> <ingredient>blueberries,</ingredient> <ingredient>cherries,</ingredient> <ingredient>damsons,</ingredient> &amp;c. always take a deep plate, line it with <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> place a teacup, inverted in the middle and fill the pie with <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> a good quantity of <ingredient>brown sugar,</ingredient> with very little <ingredient>spice</ingredient> or <ingredient>seasoning.</ingredient> The cup is placed to receive the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> which will flow from the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> as they bake, and which would otherwise ooze out at 



 



<pb n="71" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=91"/>







the edges. It will all settle under the cup; which must be removed when the pie is cut open.</p>



<p>It is a pity to make these ripe fruits into pies; they would be so much healthier eaten with bread than pie-crust; still they are harmless compared with <emph rend="italic">meat pies, which should never be made.</emph></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">SQUASH PIE.</purpose>







Pare, take out the seeds and stew the <ingredient>squash</ingredient> till very soft and dry. Strain or rub it through a sieve or <implement>colander.</implement> Mix this with good <ingredient>milk</ingredient> till it is thick as batter; sweeten it with <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Allow five <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> to a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well, add them to the <ingredient>squash</ingredient> and season with <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> or whatever <ingredient>spices</ingredient> you like. Line a <implement>pie-plate</implement> with crust, fill and bake about an hour.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PUMPKIN PIE.</purpose>







Stew the <ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient> dry, and make it like squash pie, only season rather higher. In the country, where this <emph rend="italic">real yankee pie</emph> is prepared in perfection, <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> is almost always used with other <ingredient>spices.</ingredient> There too, part <ingredient>cream</ingredient> instead of milk, is mixed with the <ingredient>pumpkin,</ingredient> which gives it a richer flavor.</p>



<p>Roll the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> rather thicker than for fruit pies, as there is only one crust. If the pie is large and deep it will require to bake an hour in a brisk oven.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="eggscheesedairy">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CUSTARD PIE.</purpose>







Beat seven <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> sweeten a quart of <ingredient>rich milk,</ingredient> that has been boiled and cooled--a stick of <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> or a bit of <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> should be boiled in it--sprinkle in a saltspoon of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> add the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and a <ingredient>grated nutmeg,</ingredient> stirring the whole well together.</p>



<p>Line two deep plates with good <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> set them in the oven three minutes to harden the crust; then pour in the custard and bake twenty minutes.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CUSTARD TART.</purpose>







Line a deep plate with <ingredient>puff paste;</ingredient> have ready six or eight middling sized <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> pared and the cores taken out. 



 



<pb n="72" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=92"/>







They should be mellow and pleasant. Put into each <ingredient>apple</ingredient> any kind of <ingredient>preserve</ingredient> you have, or a bit of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> flavored. Now fill the dish with rich custard and bake it about half an hour.</p>



<p>Make it in the same manner without crust--it is then called "Custard Pudding."</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TARTS OF PRESERVED FRUITS.</purpose>







Cover <implement>patty-pans,</implement> or shallow tins or dishes, with light <ingredient>puff paste,</ingredient> and lay the <ingredient>preserve</ingredient> in them, cover with light cross bars of <ingredient>puff paste,</ingredient> or with <ingredient>paste stars, leaves, or flowers.</ingredient> For the most delicate <ingredient>preserves,</ingredient> the best way is to bake the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> first, then put in the <ingredient>preserves,</ingredient> and ornament with leaves, baked for the purpose, on tins.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PUFFS</purpose>







. Roll out <ingredient>puff paste</ingredient> nearly a quarter of an inch thick, and, with a small saucer, or <implement>tin cutter</implement> of that size, cut it into round pieces; place upon one side <ingredient>raspberry</ingredient> or <ingredient>strawberry jam,</ingredient> or any sort of <ingredient>preserved fruit,</ingredient> or <ingredient>stewed apples;</ingredient> wet the edges, fold over the other side, and press it round with the finger and thumb. Or cut the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> into the form of a diamond, lay on the <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> and fold over the <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> so to give it a triangular shape.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">MINCE PIES.</purpose>







The custom of eating mince pies at Christmas, like that of plum puddings, was too firmly rooted for the "Pilgrim fathers" to abolish; so it would be vain for me to attempt it. At Thanksgiving too, they are considered indispensable; but I may be allowed to hope that during the remainder of the year, this rich, expensive, and exceedingly unhealthy diet will be used very sparingly by all who wish to enjoy sound sleep or pleasant dreams.</p>



<p>The dyspeptic should always avoid them as he would his bane, and for children they should be forbidden food; so tempting is the taste, that the only security consists in not tasting. So the "good housekeeper" will be careful not to place the temptation too often before her family.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy" class2="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">RICH MINCE MEAT.</purpose>







Cut the root off a <ingredient>neat's tongue,</ingredient> rub the <ingredient>tongue</ingredient> well with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> let it lie four days, wash it perfectly clean, and boil it till it becomes tender; skin, and when cold, chop it very finely. Mince as small as possible two pounds of fresh <ingredient>beef suet</ingredient> from the sirloin, stone and cut small two pounds of <ingredient>bloom raisins,</ingredient> clean nicely two pounds of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> pound and sift half an ounce of <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and a quarter of an ounce of <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> grate a large <ingredient>nutmeg;</ingredient> mix all these ingredients thoroughly, together with one pound and a half of good <ingredient>brown sugar.</ingredient> Pack it in jars.</p>



<p>When it is to be used, allow, for the quantity sufficient to make twelve small mince pies, five finely-minced <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> the <ingredient>grated rind</ingredient> and <ingredient>juice</ingredient> of a large <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> and a wine glass and a half of <ingredient>wine;</ingredient> put into each a few bits of <ingredient>citron</ingredient> and <ingredient>preserved orange peel.</ingredient></p>



<p>Three or four <ingredient>whole green lemons,</ingredient> preserved in good <ingredient>brown sugar,</ingredient> and cut into thin slices may be added to the <ingredient>mince meat.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">FAMILY MINCE PIES.</purpose>







Boil three pounds of <ingredient>lean beef</ingredient> till tender and when cold chop it fine. Chop three pounds of clear <ingredient>beef suet</ingredient> and mix the <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> sprinkling in a table-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></p>



<p>Pare, core and chop fine six pounds of good <ingredient>apples;</ingredient> stone four pounds of <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> and chop them; wash and dry two pounds of <ingredient>currants;</ingredient> and mix them all well with the <ingredient>meat.</ingredient> Season with <ingredient>powdered cinnamon</ingredient> one spoonful, a <ingredient>powdered nutmeg,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and a few <ingredient>cloves</ingredient> pounded and one pound of <ingredient>brown sugar</ingredient>--add a quart of <ingredient>Madeira wine</ingredient> and half a pound of <ingredient>citron</ingredient> cut into small bits. This mixture, put down in a stone jar and closely covered will keep several weeks. It makes a rich pie for Thanksgiving and Christmas.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PLAIN MINCE PIES.</purpose>







Take two pounds of <ingredient>lean beef</ingredient> boiled and one pound of <ingredient>suet,</ingredient> chop fine--three pounds of <ingredient>apples</ingredient>--two pounds of <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> or <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> 



 



<pb n="74" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=94"/>







<ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> and one <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient>--moisten with new <ingredient>cider</ingredient> or <ingredient>sweet cream.</ingredient> Make a good <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> and bake about an hour.</p>



<p>The <ingredient>currants</ingredient> must be washed and dried at the fire; <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> stoned and chopped.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CHICKEN PIE.</purpose>







Pick, clean, and singe the <ingredient>chickens;</ingredient> if they are very young, keep them whole, if large, cut them in joints, and take off the skin, wash them well, parboil in a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> season them with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>white pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>grated nutmeg</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace</ingredient> mixed, and if whole, put into them a bit of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and a little of the <ingredient>mixed spices;</ingredient> lay them into a dish with the <ingredient>livers,</ingredient> <ingredient>gizzards,</ingredient> and <ingredient>hearts</ingredient> well seasoned, add the <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> of five <ingredient>hard boiled eggs;</ingredient> cover with a <ingredient>puff paste,</ingredient> and bake it for an hour.</p>



<p>Slices of <ingredient>cold ham</ingredient> and <ingredient>forcemeat balls</ingredient> may be added to this pie. Or wash in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> two or three ounces of <ingredient>macaroni,</ingredient> break it into small bits, simmer it for nearly half an hour in <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> drain, and put it with the <ingredient>chickens</ingredient> into the dish, and also an ounce of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO BOIL SUGAR.</purpose>







To every pound of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> allow one gill of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> stir it over the fire till the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is entirely dissolved; when it 



 



<pb n="77" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=97"/>







first boils up, pour in a very little <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and when it boils the second time, take it off the fire; let it settle ten minutes, carefully skim it, and boil it for half an hour, or till it will candy, and then put in the <ingredient>fruit.</ingredient></p>



<p>Very good <ingredient>preserves</ingredient> for family use are made with <ingredient>brown sugar.</ingredient></p>



<p>If you wish to clarify the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> add the <ingredient>white of one egg,</ingredient> well beaten to every three pounds of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p>



<p>The <implement>preserving pans</implement> must be very clean.</p>



<p>The rule is to allow a pound of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>fruit;</ingredient> if to be kept for several months, this proportion is necessary; to use in the family three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> is sufficient.</p>



<p><ingredient>Cherries</ingredient> should be stoned, and <ingredient>berries</ingredient> picked over very carefully.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">RASPBERRY JAM.</purpose>







Weigh equal proportions of pounded loaf (or lump) <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>raspberries;</ingredient> put the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> in a <implement>preserving pan,</implement> and with a silver spoon or flat wooden stick, bruise and mash it well; let it boil up, then add the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> stirring it well with the <ingredient>fruit;</ingredient> when it boils skim it, and then boil fifteen or twenty minutes.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PEACH JAM.</purpose>







Gather the <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> when quite ripe, peel and stone them, put them into a <implement>preserving pan,</implement> and mash them over the fire till hot; rub them through a sieve, and add to a pound of <ingredient>pulp</ingredient> the same weight of <ingredient>pounded loaf sugar,</ingredient> and half an ounce of <ingredient>bitter almonds,</ingredient> blanched and pounded; let it boil ten or twelve minutes, stir and skim it well.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO PRESERVE DAMSONS.</purpose>







To every pound of <ingredient>damsons</ingredient> allow three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>powdered sugar;</ingredient> put into jars or well glazed earthen pots, alternately a layer of <ingredient>damsons,</ingredient> and one of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> tie strong paper or cloth over the pots and set them in the oven after the <ingredient>bread</ingredient> is drawn; and let them stand till the oven is cold. The next day, strain off the syrup and boil it till thick; when it is cold, put the <ingredient>damsons</ingredient> into small 



 



<pb n="78" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=98"/>







jars or glasses, pour over the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> which should cover them, and tie a wet bladder or strong cloth over them.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments" class2="eggscheesedairy">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BLACK BUTTER.</purpose>







This is a very nice preserve to spread on bread for children and much healthier in the winter than salt butter. Take any kind of <ingredient>berries,</ingredient> <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> or <ingredient>cherries</ingredient> (the latter must be stoned)--to every pound of <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> allow half a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and boil till it is reduced one fourth.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose>TO PRESERVE QUINCES.</purpose>







Pare the <ingredient>quinces</ingredient> very thin, cut them in quarters, and to every five pounds of <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> put three pounds of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and half a pint of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> cover them to keep in the steam and let them simmer gently for three hours. Or they may be preserved whole.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading">BAKED PEARS.</purpose>







Take a pound of fine <ingredient>pears;</ingredient> peel, cut them in halves, and take out the cores; put them into a pan with a few <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and some <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Set them in a moderate oven till tender, then put them on a slow fire to stew gently; add <ingredient>grated lemon peel.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">STEWED PEARS.</purpose>







Slice and stew a small <ingredient>beet root</ingredient> in a pint of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> take out the <ingredient>beet;</ingredient> pare, core and quarter your <ingredient>pears,</ingredient> and stew in the same <ingredient>water,</ingredient> sweeten to your taste, and add a little <ingredient>lemon peel.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PRESERVED APPLES.</purpose>







Weigh equal quantities of good <ingredient>brown sugar</ingredient> and of <ingredient>apples;</ingredient> peel, core and mince them small. Boil the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> allowing to every three pounds a pint of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> skim it well, and boil it pretty thick; then add the <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> the grated peel of one or two <ingredient>lemons,</ingredient> and two or three pieces of <ingredient>white ginger;</ingredient> boil till the <ingredient>apples</ingredient> look clear and yellow. This preserve will keep for years.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CLEAR APPLES.</purpose>







Boil half a pound of <ingredient>loaf sugar</ingredient> in a pint of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> take off the scum, and put in some large <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> pared, cored and cut into quarters, with the <ingredient>peel and juice of a lemon;</ingredient> let them boil till clear, without a cover upon the saucepan.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO STEW FRUIT.</purpose>







The best way to stew any kind of <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> is to put the quantity you wish to cook into a wide mouthed jar, with enough <ingredient>brown sugar</ingredient> to sweeten it; then cover the jar close, set it in a kettle of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and boil it till the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> is tender. This preserves the flavor of the <ingredient>fruit.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose>APPLE SAUCE.</purpose>







In the country it is thought almost as indispensable to provide the stock of apple sauce for winter use, as the pork; and there is no doubt of the healthiness as well as pleasantness of fruit taken in this way as food. To eat with meat it is best made of <ingredient>sour apples,</ingredient> not too mellow, but pleasant flavored. Boil down new <ingredient>sweet cider</ingredient> till it is nearly as thick, when cold, as <ingredient>molasses;</ingredient> strain it through a sieve; wash the kettle (it must be brass) put in the <ingredient>syrup,</ingredient> and as soon as it boils put in the <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> which must have been previously pared, quartered and cored. Stew over a slow fire of coals till very tender.</p>



<p>A barrel of cider will make half a barrel of very strong apple sauce, which will keep through the winter.</p>



<p>If you like it sweet to eat with tea, use <ingredient>sweet apples,</ingredient> and skim out the whole quarters, when soft;--then boil the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> and pour over them.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CURRANT JELLY.</purpose>







Strain the <ingredient>juice of currants,</ingredient> add a pound and a quarter of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to every pint of <ingredient>juice.</ingredient> Boil it gently till it is clear, skimming it all the time. <ingredient>Raspberry,</ingredient> <ingredient>strawberry,</ingredient> &amp;c. are made in the same manner.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO PRESERVE PUMPKINS.</purpose>







Choose a thick <ingredient>yellow pumpkin</ingredient> which is sweet; pare, take 



 



<pb n="80" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=100"/>







out the seeds and cut the thick part into any form you choose, round, square, egg shaped, stars, wheels, &amp;c. weigh it, put it into a stone jar or deep dish and place in a pot of <ingredient>water</ingredient> to boil till the <ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient> is so soft that you can pass a fork through it. The pot may be kept uncovered, and be sure that no water boils into the jar.</p>



<p>Take the weight of the <ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient> in good <ingredient>loaf sugar,</ingredient> clarify it and boil to <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> with the <ingredient>juice of one lemon</ingredient> to every pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and the peel cut in little squares. When the <ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient> is soft, put it into the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> and simmer gently about an hour or till the liquor is thick and rich, then let it cool and put it in glass jars well secured from air. It is a very rich sweetmeat.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">FRESH CALVES FEET JELLY.</purpose>







Scald, take off the hair, and wash very clean four <ingredient>feet;</ingredient> put them into a saucepan with two quarts of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and when it comes to a boil let them simmer for six or seven hours; take out the <ingredient>feet,</ingredient> and strain the liquor into a deep dish. The following day remove the fat carefully from the top, and give it another boil, which will reduce it to one quart of stiff stock or jelly.--This may be flavored as you like; it must be dissolved and boiled again when seasoned. It is very delicate and nourishing for an invalid.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CRANBERRY AND RICE JELLY.</purpose>







Boil and press the <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> strain the <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> and, by degrees, mix into as much <ingredient>ground rice</ingredient> as will, when boiled, thicken to a jelly; boil it gently, stirring it, and sweeten to you taste. Put it in a basin or form, and serve to eat with <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">ARROW-ROOT JELLY.</purpose>







Steep for some hours, in two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> the <ingredient>peel of a lemon,</ingredient> and three or four <ingredient>bitter almonds</ingredient> pounded; strain, and mix it with three table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>arrow-root,</ingredient> the same quantity of <ingredient>lemon-juice,</ingredient> and one of <ingredient>wine;</ingredient> sweeten, and stir it over the fire till quite thick, and when quite cold, put it into <implement>jelly glasses.</implement></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">WHOLE RICE IN A SHAPE.</purpose>







Wash a large teacupful of <ingredient>rice</ingredient> in several waters, put it into a saucepan with <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> to cover it, and when it boils, add two cupfuls of <ingredient>rich milk,</ingredient> and boil it till it becomes dry; put it into a shape, and press it in well. When cold, turn it out, and serve with <ingredient>preserved currants,</ingredient> <ingredient>raspberries,</ingredient> or any sort of <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> round it.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">ARROW-ROOT CREAM.</purpose>







Mix a table-spoonful of <ingredient>arrow-root</ingredient> with a teacupful of <ingredient>cold water;</ingredient> let it settle, and pour the water off. Sweeten and boil a quart of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> with the <ingredient>peel of a lemon</ingredient> and some <ingredient>cinnamon;</ingredient> pick them out, and pour it boiling upon the <ingredient>arrow-root,</ingredient> stirring it well and frequently till it is cold. Serve in a glass or china dish, with or without grated nutmeg on the top. It may be eaten with any <ingredient>preserved fruit,</ingredient> or <ingredient>fruit tarts.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CREAM FOR FRUIT TART.</purpose>







Boil a stick of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> two or three <ingredient>peach leaves,</ingredient> or a few <ingredient>bruised bitter almonds,</ingredient> in a quart of <ingredient>milk;</ingredient> strain. sweeten, and mix it, when cool, with three or four well-beaten <ingredient>eggs;</ingredient> stir it constantly over the fire till it thickens, It may be eaten with <ingredient>stewed apples,</ingredient> <ingredient>prunes,</ingredient> <ingredient>damsons,</ingredient> or any other <ingredient>fruit.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">RED CURRANT OR PINK CREAM.</purpose>







Squeeze three quarters of a pint of <ingredient>juice from red currants</ingredient> when full ripe, add to it rather more than a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>pounded loaf sugar,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>juice of one lemon;</ingredient> stir it into a pint and a half of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and <implement>whisk</implement> it till quite thick. Serve it in a glass dish, or in <implement>jelly glasses.</implement> It may be made with <ingredient>currant jelly,</ingredient> which mix with the <ingredient>lemon juice</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p>



<p><ingredient>Raspberry</ingredient> and <ingredient>strawberry cream</ingredient> may be made in the same way.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">APPLE CREAM.</purpose>







Peel and core five large <ingredient>apples;</ingredient> boil them in a little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> till soft enough to <implement>press</implement> through a sieve; sweeten, and 



 



<pb n="82" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=102"/>







beat with them the whisked <ingredient>whites of five eggs.</ingredient> Serve it with <ingredient>cream</ingredient> poured round it.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">WHITE LEMON CREAM.</purpose>







Boil the thin <ingredient>peel of two lemons</ingredient> in a pint of <ingredient>cream;</ingredient> strain and thicken it with the well beaten <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> of three and <ingredient>whites of four eggs;</ingredient> sweeten with <ingredient>pounded loaf sugar;</ingredient> stir till nearly cold, and put it into glasses.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CUSTARD.</purpose>







Sweeten a quart of <ingredient>thin cream</ingredient> or good <ingredient>milk</ingredient> with <ingredient>pounded sugar;</ingredient> boil it with a bit of <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and half the <ingredient>peel of a lemon;</ingredient> strain it and when a little cooled, mix it gradually with the well beaten <ingredient>yolks of ten eggs;</ingredient> stir it over a slow fire till it is pretty thick; pour it into a basin and add a table-spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water;</ingredient> keep stirring it every now and then; put it into glasses, cups or a dish. It may be made the day before it is wanted.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">LEMON CUSTARD.</purpose>







Put the <ingredient>juice of four lemons</ingredient> with three ounces of <ingredient>pounded loaf sugar</ingredient> into a deep dish. Boil the grated <ingredient>peel of one lemon</ingredient> and two ounces of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in a quart of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and pour it over the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>juice.</ingredient> Stir it well. It will keep several days.</p>



<p><ingredient>ORANGE</ingredient> CUSTARD may be made in the same manner.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BAKED CUSTARD.</purpose>







Boil a pint of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> with <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> or <ingredient>peach leaves;</ingredient> when cold add three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> well beaten, a little <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg;</ingredient> sweeten to your taste, and bake in china cups.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">RICE CUSTARD.</purpose>







Mix a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> one ounce of sifted <ingredient>ground rice,</ingredient> five or six <ingredient>bitter almonds,</ingredient> blanched and pounded with two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>rose-water;</ingredient> sweeten with <ingredient>loaf sugar,</ingredient> and stir it all together till it nearly boils; add the well beaten <ingredient>yolks of three eggs;</ingredient> stir, and let it simmer 



 



<pb n="83" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=103"/>







for about a minute; pour it into a dish, or serve it in cups, with sifted <ingredient>loaf sugar</ingredient> over the top.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO ORNAMENT CUSTARDS OR CREAMS.</purpose>







Whisk for one hour the <ingredient>whites of two eggs</ingredient> together with two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>raspberry,</ingredient> or <ingredient>red currant syrup</ingredient> or <ingredient>jelly;</ingredient> lay it in any form upon a <ingredient>custard</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> piled up to imitate rock. It may be served in a dish with <ingredient>cream</ingredient> round it.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">SPONGE CAKE.</purpose>







Take one pound of finely pulverized <ingredient>loaf sugar,</ingredient> nine <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and twelve ounces of <ingredient>dried and sifted flour.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>eggs, yolks</ingredient> and <ingredient>whites</ingredient> separately, nearly half an hour; then beat the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> with the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> till the whole is of a foam, have the oven ready, and stir in the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> lightly, adding a <ingredient>grated nutmeg</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> or <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> then put the mixture in buttered tins filled only half full, and bake about half an hour; if in one large cake it will require one hour. The oven should be quick--that is, just heated, but not so hot as to scorch.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">LEMON SPONGE CAKE.</purpose>







Take one pound of <ingredient>dried flour,</ingredient> three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>finely-pounded loaf sugar,</ingredient> seven <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> and <ingredient>whites</ingredient> beaten separately, the <ingredient>grated peel and juice of a lemon,</ingredient> a table-spoonful of <ingredient>rose water;</ingredient> beat all for an hour with the hand; <ingredient>butter</ingredient> a tin, line it with a paper also buttered, put in the cake, and sift <ingredient>pounded sugar</ingredient> over the top. Bake it for an hour.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">SEED CAKES.</purpose>







One pound of <ingredient>flour</ingredient>--twelve ounces of <ingredient>lump sugar,</ingredient> pounded fine; seven <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beaten with the <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>caraway seeds</ingredient> dried and pounded, and two large tablespoonsful of <ingredient>sour cream</ingredient> with a teaspoonful of <ingredient>pearlash.</ingredient> Bake an hour, if in one cake--in small tins fifteen minutes.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">MACAROONS.</purpose>







Beat to a froth the <ingredient>whites of eight eggs,</ingredient> then add two pounds of finely pounded and <ingredient>sifted loaf sugar,</ingredient> one pound of blanched <ingredient>sweet almonds,</ingredient> which must be pounded to a paste with <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient> Beat all these together till they become a thick 



 



<pb n="86" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=106"/>







paste then drop it from a spoon upon a buttered tin. Place the drops a little apart, as they may spread. Bake them about ten minutes in a moderate oven.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">KISSES.</purpose>







Beat the <ingredient>whites of four eggs</ingredient> till they stand alone. Then beat in, gradually, a pound of <ingredient>finely powdered sugar,</ingredient> a teaspoonful at a time. Add eight drops of the <ingredient>essence of lemon,</ingredient> and beat the whole very <ingredient>hard.</ingredient></p>



<p>Lay a wet sheet of paper on the bottom of a square tin pan. Drop on it, at equal distance, small teaspoonfuls of stiff <ingredient>currant jelly.</ingredient> Put a little of the <ingredient>beaten egg</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> at first, under the <ingredient>currant jelly.</ingredient> With a large spoon, pile some of the beaten <ingredient>white of egg</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> on each lump of <ingredient>jelly,</ingredient> so as to cover it entirely. Drop on the mixture as evenly as possible, so as to make the kisses of a round smooth shape.</p>



<p>Set them in a cool oven, and as soon as they are coloured, they are done. Then take them out and place them two bottoms together. Lay them lightly on a sieve, and dry them in a cool oven, till the two bottoms stick fast together, so as to form one ball or oval.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">SUGAR DROPS.</purpose>







Beat the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> and <ingredient>yolks of four eggs</ingredient> separately to a light foam; dilute the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> with two teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>water</ingredient> and turn them with the <ingredient>whites,</ingredient> and beat them some time; then add by degrees a pound of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in fine powder, and then four ounces of <ingredient>superfine flour,</ingredient> beating the mixture constantly. Drop the mixture on white paper placed in a tin plate, in any shape you please, ice them over with <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in powder to prevent running, and bake about ten minutes in a moderate oven.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">RICE CAKES.</purpose>







Take eight <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> and four <ingredient>whites of eggs</ingredient> and beat to a foam, add six ounces of <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>peel of one lemon</ingredient> grated; then stir in half a pound of <ingredient>ground rice,</ingredient> and beat all together for half an hour. Put it into a buttered tin and bake twenty minutes. This cake is recommended as very easy of digestion. All the foregoing cakes are 



 



<pb n="87" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=107"/>







made without butter and therefore are not apt to prove injurious.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">RICE CAKES WITH BUTTER.</purpose>







Beat, till extremely light, the <ingredient>yolks of nine eggs;</ingredient> add half a pound of <ingredient>sifted loaf sugar,</ingredient> and the same quantity of <ingredient>sifted rice flour;</ingredient> melt half a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and mix it with the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> along with a few <ingredient>pounded bitter almonds;</ingredient> half fill small buttered tins and bake in a quick oven.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CURRANT CAKES.</purpose>







Take half a pound of cleaned and <ingredient>dried currants,</ingredient> the same quantity of dried and <ingredient>sifted flour,</ingredient> a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>pounded sugar,</ingredient> a quarter of a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> four <ingredient>yolks,</ingredient> and three <ingredient>whites of eggs,</ingredient> both well beaten, and a little <ingredient>grated nutmeg</ingredient> or <ingredient>pounded cinnamon;</ingredient> then beat the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream;</ingredient> add the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and then the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and the <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> beat these well for twenty minutes, mix in the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> and the <ingredient>grated nutmeg.</ingredient> Drop the cakes in a round form upon buttered paper or bake them in small tins in a quick oven.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CARAWAY CAKES.</purpose>







One pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> well rubbed into it, half a pound of <ingredient>sifted loaf sugar</ingredient> and half a teacup of <ingredient>caraway seeds;</ingredient> make them into a stiff paste with a little <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> roll it out two or three times, cut it into round cakes, prick them and bake them upon floured tins, in a slow oven. <ingredient>Currants</ingredient> may be used instead of caraway seeds, if preferred.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">SUGAR CAKES.</purpose>







Take half a pound of <ingredient>dried flour,</ingredient> a quarter of a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>sifted loaf sugar;</ingredient> then mix together the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and the <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> rub in the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and add the <ingredient>yolk of an egg</ingredient> beaten with a tablespoonful of <ingredient>cream;</ingredient> make it into a <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> roll, and cut it into small round cakes, which bake upon a floured tin.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TEA CAKES.</purpose>







With a pound of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> rub a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient>: 



 



<pb n="88" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=108"/>







add the beaten <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> of two, and the <ingredient>white of one egg,</ingredient> quarter of a pound of <ingredient>pounded loaf sugar,</ingredient> and a few <ingredient>caraway seeds;</ingredient> mix it to a <ingredient>paste</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>warm milk,</ingredient> cover it with a cloth, and let it stand before the fire for nearly an hour; roll out the <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> and cut it into round cakes with the top of a glass, and bake them upon floured tins.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">HARD GINGERBREAD.</purpose>







Rub half a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into a pound of <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> then rub in half a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> and a spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water;</ingredient> work it well; roll out and bake in flat pans in a moderate oven. It will take about half an hour to bake. This gingerbread will keep good some time.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">SUGAR GINGERBREAD.</purpose>







Take two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and one of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> five <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beaten, two ounces of <ingredient>powdered ginger</ingredient> and a teaspoonful of <ingredient>pearlash.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose>COMMON GINGERBREAD.</purpose>







Take a pound and a half of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and rub into it half a pound of <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> add half a pound of <ingredient>brown sugar</ingredient> and half a pint of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> a teaspoonful of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> and <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> to the taste. Make it into a stiff paste, and roll it out thin. Put it on buttered tins and bake in a moderate oven.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">SOFT GINGERBREAD.</purpose>







Six teacups of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> three cups of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> three cups of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> two of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one table-spoonful of <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> and the same of ginger. Bake in a quick oven about half an hour.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">A LIGHT CAKE TO BAKE IN CUPS.</purpose>







Take a pound and a half of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rubbed in two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one glass of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> eight <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beaten, and half a <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">COMPOSITION CAKE.</purpose>







Take one pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pound of 



 



<pb n="89" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=109"/>







<ingredient>butter,</ingredient> seven <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and <ingredient>spices</ingredient> to your taste. Beat all well together, and bake in a buttered tin, or in cups.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TUNBRIDGE CAKE.</purpose>







Rub six ounces of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into a quart of <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> then mix six ounces of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> into three well beaten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and make the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into paste, adding a little <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> and what <ingredient>spices</ingredient> you like. Roll the paste very thin and cut with the top of a glass, prick the cakes with a fork, and cover with <ingredient>caraways,</ingredient> or wash with the <ingredient>white of an egg</ingredient> and dust a little <ingredient>white sugar</ingredient> over. Bake on tins in a moderate oven.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">GERMAN PUFFS.</purpose>







Take a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>almonds;</ingredient> beat well in a <implement>mortar</implement> with a little <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> three spoonfuls and a half of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> sweeten to your taste; <ingredient>butter</ingredient> your cups and bake them half an hour; this quantity makes twelve puffs in middle-sized teacups.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="inline">COMMON PLUM CAKE.</purpose>







Mix five ounces of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> with three pounds of dry <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and five ounces fine <ingredient>powdered sugar;</ingredient> add six ounces of <ingredient>currants</ingredient> washed and dried and some <ingredient>pimento</ingredient> or <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace</ingredient> finely powdered. Put three table-spoonfuls of good <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> into a pint of <ingredient>new milk</ingredient> warmed and mix the dough; let it stand till it is light. Make it into twelve cakes, and bake on a floured tin half an hour. <ingredient>Raisins</ingredient> may be used instead of currants if more convenient; but <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> must be stoned and chopped.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">RICH PLUM OR WEDDING CAKE.</purpose>







Take two pounds and a half of <ingredient>dried and sifted flour,</ingredient> allow the same quantity of fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> washed with <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> two pounds of finely pounded <ingredient>loaf sugar,</ingredient> three pounds of cleaned and <ingredient>dried currants,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> stoned, one <ingredient>nutmeg grated,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>sweetmeats</ingredient> cut small, a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>blanched almonds</ingredient> pounded with a little <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> and twenty <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> and <ingredient>whites</ingredient> separately 



 



<pb n="90" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=110"/>







beaten. The <ingredient>butter</ingredient> must be beaten with the hand till it becomes like cream; then add the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and by degrees the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> after these the rest of the ingredients, mixing in at last the <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> with nearly a teacupful of rose, or <ingredient>orange-flower water.</ingredient> This mixture must be beaten together rather more than half an hour, then put into a cake-pan, which has previously been buttered and lined with buttered paper; fill it rather more than three quarters full. It should be baked in a moderate oven for three hours, and then cooled gradually, by at first letting it stand some time at the mouth of the oven.</p>



<p>If you fear the bottom of the cake may burn, put the pan on a plate with saw-dust between.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">POUND CAKE.</purpose>







Take one pound of <ingredient>dried and sifted flour,</ingredient> the same of <ingredient>loaf sugar,</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient>--the well beaten <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> of twelve, and the <ingredient>whites of six eggs.</ingredient> Then with the hand beat the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to a cream, add the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> by degrees, then the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and the <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> beat it all well together for an hour, mixing half a glass of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> or twelve drops of the <ingredient>essence of lemon,</ingredient> and a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> or a little <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> powdered. Bake it in a tin pan buttered or in small ones in a quick oven.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PLUM POUND CAKE.</purpose>







Take of <ingredient>dried and sifted flour,</ingredient> <ingredient>sifted loaf sugar,</ingredient> fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> cleaned and <ingredient>dried currants,</ingredient> one pound each, and twelve <ingredient>eggs;</ingredient> then whisk the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> and <ingredient>whites of the eggs</ingredient> separately, while another with the hand beats the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to a cream; and as the froth rises upon the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> add it to the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and continue so doing till it is all beaten in; mix the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> together, and add them by degrees; the last thing, mix in the <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> together with a glass of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> and a <ingredient>powdered nutmeg.</ingredient> It will require to be beaten during a whole hour. Bake it in a buttered tin.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">HEART CAKES.</purpose>







Beat one pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to cream, with some <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> dried, one pound of <ingredient>sifted sugar,</ingredient> twelve <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> beat all well together; add a few <ingredient>currants</ingredient> 



 



<pb n="91" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=111"/>







washed and dried; <ingredient>butter</ingredient> small pans of a size for the purpose, heart shaped, pour in the mixture; grate <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> over them; they are soon baked. They may be done in a <implement>Dutch oven.</implement></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">FROST OR ICEING FOR CAKES.</purpose>







Beat the <ingredient>whites of four eggs</ingredient> to a stiff foam, and add gradually three quarters of a pound of the best <ingredient>double refined loaf sugar,</ingredient> pounded and sifted; mix in the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> of half a <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> or a teaspoonful of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient> Beat the mixture till very light and white; place the cake before the fire, pour over the iceing and smooth over the top and sides with the back of a spoon.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">WARM CAKES FOR BREAKFAST AND TEA.</purpose>







If I thought there was any hope of the advice being followed, I would say do not eat warm cakes at all; cold or toasted bread is far better for the constitution. But as most people will have warm bread of some kind, a part of the time, at least, I consider it better to give directions for the sorts which seem likely to do the least injury; only adding here, that those persons will be <emph rend="italic">least</emph> likely to be injured who eat the smallest quantity of hot cakes in proportion to their cold bread, which our customs allow.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TEA CAKES.</purpose>







Rub into a pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> an ounce of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> a beaten <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> and half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt</ingredient>--wet it with <ingredient>warmed milk;</ingredient> make the paste rather stiff, and let it remain before the fire, where it will be kept warm for an hour or two; then roll it thin and cut it with the top of a <implement>tumbler;</implement> bake it quick.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BREAKFAST CAKE.</purpose>







Put into a quart of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> four ounces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and, if you use <ingredient>new milk,</ingredient> put in three large spoonfuls of <ingredient>yeast;</ingredient> make it into <ingredient>biscuits</ingredient> and prick them with a fork.</p>



<p>If you have <ingredient>sour milk,</ingredient> omit the yeast, and put a teaspoonful of <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> in the <ingredient>sour milk;</ingredient> pour it while effervescing into the <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> These biscuits are less likely to injure the health, than if raised with yeast.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BUCKWHEAT CAKES.</purpose>







Take one quart of <ingredient>buckwheat meal,</ingredient> a handful of <ingredient>indian meal,</ingredient> and a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> mix them with two large spoonfuls of <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> and sufficient <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> to make a thick batter. Put it in a warm place to rise, which will take three or four hours; or if you mix it at night, let it stand where it is rather cool.</p>



<p>When it is light, bake it on a griddle, or in a pan. The griddle must be well buttered, and the cakes are better to be small and thin.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">INDIAN SLAPJACKS.</purpose>







Mix one pint of <ingredient>sifted indian meal</ingredient> and four large spoonfuls of <ingredient>wheat flour</ingredient> into a quart of <ingredient>new milk,</ingredient> add four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> beaten, and a little <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Bake them on a griddle like buckwheat cakes; eat with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>molasses.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PLAIN INDIAN CAKES.</purpose>







Take a quart of <ingredient>sifted indian meal,</ingredient> sprinkle a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> over it, and mix it with scalding <ingredient>water,</ingredient> stirring it well; bake it on a board, before the fire, or on a tin in a stove.--It is healthy food for children eaten warm (not <emph rend="italic">hot)</emph> with <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> or <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></p>



<p>Indian cake made with <ingredient>buttermilk,</ingredient> or <ingredient>sour milk,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>cream</ingredient> or <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rubbed into the meal, and a teaspoonful of <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> in the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> is very light and nutritious.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BREAKFAST BATTER CAKES.</purpose>







One pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> as large as an egg, two spoonfuls of <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour</ingredient> enough to make a stiff batter, bake them in <implement>tin hoops</implement> or on a griddle, let them stand and rise all night, but not in a very warm place.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BATTER CAKES FOR TEA.</purpose>







Beat two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> put them in half a pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and a teacup of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> with half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> dissolved in it; sprinkle a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and grate half a <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> and <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> if you like. Stir in <ingredient>sifted flour</ingredient> till the batter is smooth and thick. Bake them on 



 



<pb n="93" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=113"/>







a griddle or in a pan. Butter the pan well, and drop the batter in small round cakes, and quite thin. They must be turned, nicely browned, but not made black; lay them on a plate, in a pile, with a little <ingredient>butter</ingredient> between each layer.</p>



<p>This batter will make good pancakes, fried in hot <ingredient>lard.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CREAM SHORT CAKES.</purpose>







In the country where cream is plenty this is a favorite cake at the tea table.--Put into a quart of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> a bit of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> as large as an <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> sprinkle over a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt</ingredient>--take half a pint of thick <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> a little sour, half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> dissolved in <ingredient>water,</ingredient> poured into the <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk</ingredient> added sufficient to wet the <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Some use all <ingredient>cream</ingredient> and that sweet. Then there needs no pearlash. It is expensive food.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">ROLLS.</purpose>







Rub into a pound of <ingredient>sifted flour</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> beat the <ingredient>whites of three eggs</ingredient> to a froth and add a table-spoonful of good <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and sufficient <ingredient>warm milk</ingredient> to make a stiff dough. Cover and put it where it will be kept warm, and it will rise in an hour. Then make it into rolls, or round cakes, put them on a floured tin, and bake in a quick oven or stove. They will be done in ten or fifteen minutes.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CHEAP BREAD.</purpose>







<ingredient>Indian meal</ingredient> is the cheapest, and a bushel furnishes more nutriment than the same quantity of wheat. It is also a generally healthy diet, and those who wish to practise close economy should use much of this meal in their families.</p>



<p>It makes excellent puddings, and warm cakes, which are much less apt to oppress the stomach than hot wheat bread or short cakes of any kind. And good, light, nourishing bread may be made by using five parts of <ingredient>indian</ingredient> and one of <ingredient>rye</ingredient> or <ingredient>wheat flour,</ingredient> (see receipts for "Rye and Indian Bread"); which is better than to cook it hot at every meal.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PLAIN BAKED INDIAN PUDDING.</purpose>







Scald a quart of <ingredient>skimmed milk,</ingredient> and stir in while it is hot, half a pint of <ingredient>sifted indian meal</ingredient> and a teacup of <ingredient>molasses;</ingredient> season with a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> or <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient> Let it cool, (it is better to stand an hour or two,) then pour it into an earthen pot or deep pan, that has been well buttered (<ingredient>clarified drippings</ingredient> will answer to rub the pan, but <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is best) and bake it three or four hours. Pour in half a teacup of <ingredient>cold milk,</ingredient> and stir the whole when you set it in the oven.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">INDIAN FRUIT PUDDING.</purpose>







Take a pint of <ingredient>hot milk</ingredient> and stir in <ingredient>sifted indian meal</ingredient> till the batter is stiff; add a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>molasses;</ingredient> then stir in a pint of whortleberries, or the same 



 



<pb n="95" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=115"/>







quantity of <ingredient>chopped sweet apple.</ingredient> Tie it in a cloth that has been wet and leave room for it to swell, or put it in a <implement>pudding pan,</implement> and tie a cloth over--boil it three hours. The <ingredient>water</ingredient> must boil when it is put in.</p>



<p>You can use <ingredient>cranberries,</ingredient> and eat it with <ingredient>sweet sauce.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PLAIN BAKED RICE PUDDING.</purpose>







A pint of <ingredient>rice,</ingredient> washed and boiled soft in a pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> with a <ingredient>salt</ingredient>-spoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient>--when cold add three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> two cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a small piece of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> or a <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient> Bake it an hour in a buttered dish.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PLAIN BOILED RICE.</purpose>







Wash in four or five waters a pint of good <ingredient>rice;</ingredient> tie it in a <implement>pudding cloth,</implement> allowing plenty of room to swell;--put it on in a pot of <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and let it boil slowly for two hours. It may be eaten with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> or <ingredient>molasses.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PLAIN APPLE PUDDING.</purpose>







Make a batter with two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and three or four spoonfuls of <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> pour it into a deep dish, and having pared six or eight small <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> place them whole in the batter and bake it in a stove or oven. It will be done in an hour.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">A CHEAP AND QUICK PUDDING.</purpose>







Beat up four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> add a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and stir in four large spoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to your taste. Beat it well, and pour it into buttered teacups, filling them rather more than half full. They will bake in a stove or <implement>dutch oven</implement> in fifteen minutes; and if you have company unexpectedly to dinner, and wish to add a little dish, this is a good and cheap one.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BREAD PUDDING.</purpose>







Pieces of <ingredient>dry bread,</ingredient> crust, &amp;c., if kept clean and used before they are sour, make good puddings; no prudent housekeeper will allow them to be wasted. Soak the crusts in <ingredient>milk</ingredient> till they are soft--then add <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>sweetening and spice</ingredient> to your taste. Bake or boil.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PEASE PUDDING.</purpose>







Take a pint of good <ingredient>split peas,</ingredient> and having washed, soak them well in <ingredient>warm water;</ingredient> then tie them in a cloth, put the pudding into a saucepan of <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and boil it until quite soft. When done, beat it up with a little <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> serve it with boiled <ingredient>pork</ingredient> or <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> or with a little <ingredient>cold meat</ingredient> it makes a good dinner for children in the winter season.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame" class2="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PORK AND BEANS</purpose>







Is an economical dish; but it does not agree with weak stomachs. Put a quart of <ingredient>beans</ingredient> into two quarts of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and hang them all night over the fire, to swell. In the morning pour off the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> rinse them well with two or three waters poured over them in a <implement>colander.</implement> Take a pound of <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> that is not very fat, score the rind, then again place the <ingredient>beans</ingredient> just covered with <ingredient>water</ingredient> in the kettle and keep them hot over the fire for an hour or two; then drain off the water, sprinkle a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and a spoon of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> over the <ingredient>beans;</ingredient> place them in a well glazed earthen pot, not very wide at the top, put the <ingredient>pork</ingredient> down in the <ingredient>beans,</ingredient> till the rind only appears; fill the pot with <ingredient>water</ingredient> till it just reaches the top of the <ingredient>beans,</ingredient> put it in a brisk oven and bake three or four hours.</p>



<p>Stewed <ingredient>beans and pork</ingredient> are prepared in the same way, only they are kept over the fire, and the <ingredient>pork</ingredient> in them three or four hours instead of being in the oven. The <ingredient>beans</ingredient> will not be white or pleasant to the taste unless they are well soaked and washed--nor are they healthy without this process.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BEEF STEAKS STEWED.</purpose>







This is a very good and economical way of cooking <ingredient>steaks</ingredient> that are not very tender. Put the <ingredient>steaks</ingredient> in a <implement>stew-pan</implement> with a little <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and fry them brown. Then add a little <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> or <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> some <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and a table-spoonful of <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> and let them stew gently till tender. Thicken the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> with a bit of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO STEW A ROUND OF BEEF.</purpose>







Tie up the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> with a strong tape and put it on to stew with as much <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> as will cover it--season with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>black pepper,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace</ingredient> or <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> and a gill of <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient> Let it stew gently skimming it well, seven or eight hours, till it is tender. Take out the <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> skim off the fat, strain the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> and thicken with a little <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> let it boil and pour it over the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> before serving.</p>



<p>This is a rich dish and economical, because stewing meat saves all the juices and essence.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BAKED MUTTON CHOPS.</purpose>







Cut a <ingredient>neck of mutton</ingredient> into neat chops, season them with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>butter</ingredient> a dish, lay in the chops and pour over them a batter made of a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> beaten up, four table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> An hour will bake them. This is a quick mode of dressing a dinner, if you are baking.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">LAMB FRY.</purpose>







Take the <ingredient>heart,</ingredient> <ingredient>liver</ingredient> and <ingredient>sweet bread of a lamb;</ingredient> cut it into slices and fry it in <ingredient>salt pork fat;</ingredient> or dip it in the beaten <ingredient>white of an egg</ingredient> and strew <ingredient>bread crumbs</ingredient> over it, before you fry it. Garnish with <ingredient>crisp parsley.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">VEAL LIVER.</purpose>







There is none of the solid meat of animals so cheap as the <ingredient>liver,</ingredient> and if well cooked it makes a good dish. Cut it in thin slices, rub them with <ingredient>flour</ingredient> or <ingredient>indian meal,</ingredient> and fry in <ingredient>salt pork fat</ingredient> till thoroughly done--or you may broil it like a <ingredient>steak.</ingredient> <ingredient>Beef liver</ingredient> is cooked in the same way.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame" class2="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">VEAL AND RICE.</purpose>







Take one pound of <ingredient>veal;</ingredient> wash the same quantity of <ingredient>rice,</ingredient> and stew them together in three quarts of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> seasoned with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Let it stew gently two hours, then add half a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and let it just come to a simmer. This with <ingredient>boiled potatoes</ingredient> will make a comfortable dinner for a large family.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame" class2="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">A VERY ECONOMICAL DINNER.</purpose>







One pound of <ingredient>sausages,</ingredient> cut in pieces, with four pounds of <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> and a few <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> if they are liked, with about a table-spoonful of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> mixed in a pint of <ingredient>water</ingredient> and added to the dish, will make a sufficient dinner for five or six persons. The <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> must be cut in slices and stewed with the <ingredient>sausages</ingredient> till tender.</p>



<p>Or you may use a pound and a half of <ingredient>meat</ingredient> (<ingredient>mutton</ingredient> is best) instead of the sausages. Season with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>sage</ingredient> or <ingredient>thyme.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">HASHES.</purpose>







All the pieces and bits of <ingredient>cold meat</ingredient> should be minced and warmed; if this is rightly done the dish is generally a favorite one.</p>



<p>It is best to chop the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> very fine, (gristles and gelatinous matter from the bones may be included) then make a <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> by putting a lump of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> (what you judge necessary) into a <implement>stew-pan;</implement> when it is hot add a little <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and stir it into the <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> then add a teacupful of the <ingredient>broth</ingredient> the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> was boiled in and a little <ingredient>catsup.</ingredient> Let this boil up, then put in the mince <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>chopped parsley,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Let it stand and simmer a few minutes covered, but do not let it boil--it hardens the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> to boil it.--Lay slices of <ingredient>toasted bread</ingredient> in the dish and pour the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> and <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> over.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="soups">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PEA SOUP WITHOUT MEAT.</purpose>







Take a quart of <ingredient>green pease,</ingredient> (keep out half a pint of the youngest; boil them separately, and put them in the soup when it is finished;) put them on in <ingredient>boiling water;</ingredient> boil them tender, and then pour off the water, and set it by to make the soup with; put the <ingredient>peas</ingredient> into a <implement>mortar,</implement> and pound them into a mash; then put them into two quarts of the <ingredient>water</ingredient> you boiled the <ingredient>peas</ingredient> in; stir all well together; let it boil up for about five minutes, and then rub it through a <implement>hair sieve.</implement> If the <ingredient>peas</ingredient> are good, it will be as thick and fine a vegetable soup as need be sent to table.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="soups">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">OX CHEEK SOUP.</purpose>







Separate the <ingredient>bones</ingredient> from the <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> and break the former, cut the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> into pieces the length of a finger and the breadth of two, put a quart of <ingredient>water</ingredient> to every pound of <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> set it on a gentle fire, and skim it well during the first boiling; after it has stewed gently two hours, add <ingredient>carrots,</ingredient> <ingredient>turnips,</ingredient> <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> <ingredient>celery,</ingredient> a head of <ingredient>cabbage,</ingredient> and a bunch of <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>vermicelli;</ingredient> let it stew two hours and a half longer, skim it, and take out the herbs and bones. <ingredient>Rice</ingredient> may be used instead of vermicelli, and <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> instead of cabbage. This is an economical dinner for a number of laboring men.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">FISH.</purpose>







The <ingredient>salted cod fish</ingredient> is cheap food, if <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> are used freely with it. Thick <ingredient>fish</ingredient> are more profitable than thin ones. To cook <ingredient>salt fish</ingredient> well requires considerable care. It should never <emph rend="italic">boil;</emph> put it on in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and let it soak over night. Then wash and scrape it very clean--put it into a kettle of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and let it stand near the fire where it can be hot, but not boil up, for two hours. It should be scalding hot the last half hour. Drain it and send it to table. <ingredient>Egg sauce</ingredient> or <ingredient>melted butter</ingredient> is eaten with it.</p>



<p>Should any <ingredient>fish</ingredient> remain after dinner, have it minced before it is put away, and the <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> mashed up with it. They can be done much better and easier when warm than if allowed to stand till morning. Then the <ingredient>fish</ingredient> may be rolled into balls, flattened and fried in <ingredient>hot butter</ingredient> or <ingredient>lard.</ingredient> Dip the balls into the beaten <ingredient>white of an egg,</ingredient> and they will not break. This is a fine dish for breakfast in the winter season.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CAKES, PIES, ETC.</purpose>







In making these kinds of food, people who live in the country must often use maple or <ingredient>brown sugar;</ingredient> in these cases, always dry it well for cake and pound it fine.</p>



<p><ingredient>Honey</ingredient> or <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> will answer for preserves of fruit, that are to be used in the family, but they will not keep long unless scalded often.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BLACKBERRY JAM.</purpose>







Gather the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> in dry weather; allow half a pound of <ingredient>coarse brown sugar,</ingredient> to every pound of <ingredient>fruit;</ingredient> boil the whole together gently for an hour, or till the <ingredient>blackberries</ingredient> are soft, stirring and mashing them well. Preserve it like any other jam, and it will be found very useful in families, particularly for children, regulating their bowels and enabling you to dispense with cathartics. It may be spread on bread or on puddings instead of butter; and even when the blackberries are bought it is cheaper than butter. In the country, every family should preserve, at least, a half peck of blackberries.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO MAKE COFFEE.</purpose>







Take <ingredient>fresh-roasted coffee,</ingredient> (a quarter of a pound for three persons is the rule, but <emph rend="italic">less</emph> will do;) allow two table-spoonfuls for each person, grind it just before making, put it in a basin and break into it an <ingredient>egg, yolk,</ingredient> <ingredient>white,</ingredient> shell and all. Mix it up with the spoon to the consistence of <implement>mortar,</implement> put in a warm not <emph rend="italic">boiling</emph> <ingredient>water</ingredient> in the <implement>coffee pot;</implement> let it boil up and <emph rend="italic">break</emph> three times; then stand a few minutes and it will be as clear as amber, and the <ingredient>egg</ingredient> will give it a rich taste.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">ANOTHER WAY TO MAKE COFFEE.</purpose>







Pour <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> into your <implement>coffee pot,</implement> and then stir in your <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> a spoonful at a time, allowing three to every pint of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> this makes <emph rend="italic">strong</emph> coffee. Stir it to prevent the mixture from boiling over, as the <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> swells, and to force it to combine with the <ingredient>water.</ingredient> This will be done after it has boiled gently a few minutes. Then let it stand and boil slowly for half an hour; remove it from the fire, and pour in a teacup of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and set it in the corner to settle.--As soon as it becomes clear, it is to be poured, gently, into a clean <implement>coffee-pot</implement> for the table.</p>



<p>Made in this manner it may be kept two or three days in summer, and a week in winter; you need only heat it over when wanted.</p>



<p>The grounds and sediment, may be boiled over and used once for coffee.</p>



 



<pb n="102" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=122"/>







<p><ingredient>Fish skin</ingredient> is often used to settle coffee, and will answer tolerably well, if rightly prepared. Pull off the <ingredient>skin</ingredient> from a <ingredient>salted cod,</ingredient> scrape, wash and dry it in the oven, after removing the bread--then divide it in pieces about an inch square, and put it in a paper bag for use. It will require one bit for every pint of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> put in when you make the coffee. Several substitutes for coffee are used by those who cannot afford the real berry. Rye, pease, &amp;c.--none of these are very healthy, and certainly are not good--The best substitute is <ingredient>toasted crust of bread,</ingredient> but it is cheaper to drink water, and if taken for a little time will be as palatable; or else use</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">COCOA SHELLS.</purpose>







These should be soaked over night, then boil them in the same <ingredient>water</ingredient> in the morning. They are considerably nutritious, and allowed to be healthy, and are cheap.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CHOCOLATE.</purpose>







To each square of <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> scraped off fine, and put in the pot, allow a pint, (less if you like it strong) of <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Stir it while boiling; and let it be uncovered. Let it boil about fifteen minutes, or half an hour, then pour in your <ingredient>cream</ingredient> or <ingredient>rich milk,</ingredient> and let it boil up.--<ingredient>Nutmeg</ingredient> grated over a cup of <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> improves the flavor.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TEA.</purpose>







Scald the teapot with <ingredient>boiling water;</ingredient> then put in the <ingredient>tea,</ingredient> allowing three teaspoonfuls to a pint of <ingredient>water</ingredient>--or for every two persons. Pour on the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> it must be boiling hot, and let the <ingredient>tea</ingredient> steep about ten minutes.</p>



<p><ingredient>Black tea</ingredient> is healthier than green. <ingredient>Hyson</ingredient> and Souchong mixed together, half and half, is a pleasanter beverage than either alone, and safer for those who drink <emph rend="italic">strong</emph> tea, than to trust themselves wholly with green.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">COMMON BEER.</purpose>







Two gallons of <ingredient>water</ingredient> to a large handful of <ingredient>hops</ingredient> is the rule. A little fresh gathered <ingredient>spruce,</ingredient> or <ingredient>sweet fern</ingredient> makes the <ingredient>beer</ingredient> more agreeable, and you may allow a quart of <ingredient>wheat bran</ingredient> to the mixture--then boil it two or three hours. 



 



<pb n="103" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=123"/>







Strain it through a sieve, and stir in, while the liquor is hot, a teacup of <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> to every gallon. Let it stand till lukewarm, pour it into a clean barrel and add good <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> a pint if the barrel is nearly full; shake it well together; it will be fit for use the next day.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">SPRUCE BEER.</purpose>







Allow an ounce of <ingredient>hops</ingredient> and a spoonful of <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> to a gallon of <ingredient>water.</ingredient> When well boiled, strain it, and put in a pint of <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> and half an ounce or less of the <ingredient>essence of spruce</ingredient>--when cool add a teacup of <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> and put into a clean tight <implement>cask</implement> and let it ferment for a day or two, then bottle it for use. You can boil the sprigs of <ingredient>spruce</ingredient> fir in room of the essence.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">GINGER BEER QUICKLY MADE.</purpose>







A gallon of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> is poured over three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>loaf sugar,</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>peel of one lemon;</ingredient> when milk-warm, the <ingredient>juice of the lemon</ingredient> and a spoonful of <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> are added. It should be made in the evening, and bottled next morning, in stone bottles, and the cork tied down with twine.</p>



<p>Good <ingredient>brown sugar</ingredient> will answer, and the lemon may be omitted, if <emph rend="italic">cheapness</emph> is required.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">LEMONADE.</purpose>







Three <ingredient>lemons</ingredient> to a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> makes strong lemonade; sweeten to your taste.</p>



<p>This is the best beverage for parties, cool, refreshing, pleasant and salubrious.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">ORANGEADE.</purpose>







Roll and press the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> from the <ingredient>oranges</ingredient> in the same way as from lemons. It requires less <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> than lemonade. The <ingredient>water</ingredient> must be pure and cold, and then there can be nothing more delicious than these two kinds of drink.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">CURRANT WINE.</purpose>







Gather the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> when dry, extract the <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> either by mashing and pressing the <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> or putting it in a jar, 



 



<pb n="104" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=124"/>







placed in <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient>--strain the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> and for every gallon allow one gallon of <ingredient>water</ingredient> and three pounds of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Dissolve the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in the <ingredient>water</ingredient> and take off the scum; let it cool, add it to the <ingredient>currant juice,</ingredient> and put the mixture in a keg--but do not close it tightly till it has ceased fermenting, which will not be under a week. In three or four weeks it may be bottled. The <ingredient>white of an egg</ingredient> beaten, mixed with a teaspoonful of <ingredient>cream of tartar</ingredient> and stirred into the liquid makes the wine look clear and bright.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">WATER.</purpose>







The foregoing receipts will teach the manner of preparing those drinks which are most agreeable to the palate, suitable for the purposes of hospitality, economy and that attention to the real welfare of a family which should never be neglected.</p>



<p>But after all, the best beverage for the healthy, who wish to continue well, is good pure cold WATER! The danger in recommending it as the common and constant drink of all persons, at all times and places, arises from the difficulty of finding it pure and good. There is no doubt that, besides the diseases known to be generated by drinking bad water, serious injury is frequently inflicted on the constitution from the long continued use of much that is called <emph rend="italic">good,</emph> that is, though known to be <emph rend="italic">hard</emph> and consequently impregnated with chemical solutions of lime, still it does not taste unpleasant, and is clear. But this <emph rend="italic">hard</emph> water always leaves a mineral matter on the skin, when we use it in washing, which renders the hands and face rough and liable to chap. Does not this water, if we drink it, likewise corrode and injure the fine membranes of the stomach? The Boston people who constantly use hard water for all purposes of cookery and drink, certainly have bad complexions, sallow, dry, and <emph rend="italic">hard</emph>-looking; and complaints of the stomach or dyspepsia are very common among them.</p>



<p>A Salem gentleman declared that when his daughters, who frequently visited at Boston, passed two or three weeks at a time there, he could see a very material change in their complexions. At Salem there is plenty of soft water, and the ladies of that ancient town are famed for their beauty, which is chiefly owing (its superiority I mean) to a 



 



<pb n="105" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=125"/>







peculiarly fair, delicate tincture of skin, contrasted with the half petrified of appearance of those who are obliged to drink <emph rend="italic">hard water</emph> always, and often to wash in it.</p>



<p>The best water to drink as well as wash with, when it can be obtained pure, or rendered so, is <emph rend="italic">rain-water.</emph> This may generally be effected with a little care and expense. A clean reservoir to collect the rain water is needed, and a portable <implement>filterer</implement>--that is all the expense; the care of filtering, every young lady who values her health or <emph rend="italic">complexion,</emph> always synonymous, will gladly undertake.</p>



<p>Filtering cools the water, and in the summer ice may be used.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">PICKLE FOR BUTTER.</purpose>







Allow half a pound of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> an ounce of <ingredient>saltpetre,</ingredient> and half a pound of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to three quarts of <ingredient>water.</ingredient>--Dissolve them together; scald and skim the <ingredient>pickle;</ingredient> let it be entirely cold and then pour it over the <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">TO MAKE GRUEL.</purpose>







Sift the <ingredient>Indian meal</ingredient> through a fine sieve--wet two spoonfuls of this meal with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and beat it till there are no lumps; then stir it into a pint of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and let it boil half an hour, stirring it all the time.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BEEF TEA.</purpose>







Cut half a pound of <ingredient>lean fresh beef</ingredient> into slices, lay it in a dish and pour over it a pint of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> cover the dish and let it stand half an hour by the fire, then just boil it up--pour it off clear and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> it a very little.</p>



<p><purpose placement="inline">VEAL TEA</purpose>







is made in the same way--and <purpose placement="inline">CHICKEN TEA</purpose>







also.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BARLEY WATER.</purpose>







Upon one ounce of <ingredient>pearl barley,</ingredient> after it has been well washed in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> pour half a pint of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and then boil it for a few minutes; the <ingredient>water</ingredient> must then be strained off and thrown away; afterwards a quart of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> must be poured over the <ingredient>barley;</ingredient> and which should then be boiled down to one pint and a quarter, and strained off. The barley water thus made is clear and mucilaginous; and when mixed with an equal quantity of good <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and a small portion of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> is an excellent substitute for the mother's milk, when infants are, unfortunately, to be brought up by hand. Without milk, it is one of the best beverages for all acute diseases, and may have <ingredient>lemon juice,</ingredient> <ingredient>raspberry vinegar,</ingredient> <ingredient>apple tea,</ingredient> <ingredient>infusion of tamarinds,</ingredient> or any other acidulous substance that is agreeable to the palate of the patient, mixed with it.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">ARROW-ROOT.</purpose>







Forms an excellent nutritive mucilage. Put two teaspoonfuls of the powder into a half pint basin; mix them smooth with a few teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and then let another person pour <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> over the mixture while you continue to stir it, until it forms a kind of starchy-looking substance.</p>



<p>Arrow-root thus prepared, may be used in the same manner as gruel. It is well adapted for the food of infants, because it is less liable to ferment than either gruel or barley water; and, for the same reason, it is the best fluid nourishment for those who are afflicted with diseases of indigestion. As it is very insipid, it requires either <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> or <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> or <ingredient>acids,</ingredient> to be mixed with it, whichever may suit the taste and the state of habit of the person for whom it is intended. It forms an excellent pudding, when prepared 



 



<pb n="130" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=150"/>







like rice, for children who are a little beyond the age of infancy.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="medhealth">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">DECOCTION OF ICELAND LIVERWORT.</purpose>







An ounce of liverwort must be carefully freed from the moss, fragments of stalks, and particles of dirt, with which it is frequently mixed, by rubbing it between the hands in cold water. Then steep it, for two hours, in such a quantity of <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> as will completely cover it; after which it must be bruised, pounded, or cut, and the steeping continued for three or four days longer in a fresh quantity of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> which when the steeping is finished, must be strained off by pressure. The liverwort is then to be put into a quart of fresh <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and kept boiling until the fluid be reduced two-thirds, or to a pint and a quarter. When strained and allowed to cool, it forms a thick mucilage, free from any bitter taste; and may be rendered very palatable by the addition of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon juice;</ingredient> or by <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> in those cases which permit the use of <ingredient>wine.</ingredient></p>



<p>This decoction of liverwort is an excellent demulcent nutriment, in consumption, dysentery and in convalesence from acute diseases, and particularly after the hooping cough, in which case the bitter need not be completely removed, as it tends to invigorate the digestive organs.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">WHITE WINE WHEY.</purpose>







To make this whey, put half a pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> diluted with a quarter of a pint of <ingredient>water</ingredient> into a sauce-pan, which must be placed on the fire uncovered. Watch the moment when the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> boils, which may be known by the frothing and rising up of the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> to the top of the pan; pour into it, at that instant, two glasses of <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> and a teaspoonful of <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> which should be previously mixed with with the <ingredient>wine.</ingredient> The curd will immediately form; and, after boiling the mixture for a few minutes, may be separated from the whey, either by letting it settle at the bottom, and then pouring off the whey clear from it, or by straining it through a fine sieve.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="medhealth">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">BALM, MINT, AND OTHER TEAS.</purpose>







These are simple infusions, the strength of which can only be regulated by the taste. They are made by putting<pb n="151" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=gohk&#38;PageNum=151"/>







either the fresh or the dried plants into <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> in a covered vessel, which should be placed near the fire for an hour. The young shoots both of <ingredient>balm</ingredient> and of <ingredient>mint</ingredient> are to be preferred, on account of their strong aromatic qualities. These infusions may be drunk freely in feverish and in various other complaints, in which diluents are recommended. Mint tea, made with the fresh leaves, is useful in allaying nausea and vomiting.</p>



</recipe>



