<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To Make Corn Bread.--</purpose>



Four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> to a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to six pounds of <ingredient>meal.</ingredient> Stir well until it is about the thickness of good molasses. A tea-cupful of <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> to six pounds of meal--to which add a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>sal&#230;ratus.</ingredient> Grease your pans well with <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Put it in a good hot oven; bake three quarters of an hour.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To Make Buckwheat Cakes.</purpose>



--Six pounds of <ingredient>meal;</ingredient> add to that a<pb n="105" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=111"/> pound of <ingredient>Indian meal,</ingredient> and half a pint of good <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient> Put into a warm place--and when light, bake well on a hot griddle.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To Make Anchovy Sauce.</purpose>



--Strip an <ingredient>anchovy,</ingredient> bruise it very fine, put it into half a pint of <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a spoonful of <ingredient>red wine,</ingredient> and a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>catchup.</ingredient> Boil all together till it is properly thick, and serve it up. Add a little <ingredient>lemon-juice,</ingredient> if you please.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To Make Bread or Pap Sauce.</purpose>



--Take a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> put in a good piece of <ingredient>crumb of bread,</ingredient> a blade of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>whole pepper.</ingredient> Boil it for eight or ten minutes, and then <pb n="106" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=112"/> pour the <ingredient>water</ingredient> off; take out the spice, and beat up the <ingredient>bread</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To melt Butter thick.</purpose>



--Your saucepan must be well tinned, and very clean. Just moisten the bottom with as small a quantity of <ingredient>water</ingredient> as possible, not above a spoonful to half a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> You may or may not dust the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> with <ingredient>flour</ingredient>--it is better not to <ingredient>flour</ingredient> it. Cut the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in slices, and put it into the pan a little before the <ingredient>water</ingredient> becomes hot. As it melts, keep the pan shaking one way frequently; and when it is all melted let it boil up, and it will be smooth, fine, and thick.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To burn Butter.</purpose>



--Put two ounces of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> over a slow fire, in a <implement>stew-pan</implement> or sauce-pan, without water. When the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is melted, dust on a little <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and keep it stirring till it grows thick and brown.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Brown Celery Sauce.</purpose>



--Stew the <ingredient>celery</ingredient> in little thin bits, then add <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> with a glass of <ingredient>red wine,</ingredient> a spoonful of <ingredient>catchup,</ingredient> and half a pint of good <ingredient>gravy;</ingredient> boil all these together, and pour into the dish. Garnish with <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">Gravy, to make Mutton eat like Venison.</purpose>



--Take a <ingredient>woodcock</ingredient> or <ingredient>snipe</ingredient> that is stale, (the staler the better) <pb n="108" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=114"/> pick it, cut it in two, and hack it with a knife; put it into a <implement>stew-pan,</implement> with as much <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> as you shall want, and let it simmer for half an hour; then strain the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> for use. This will give the mutton so true a flavor of game, that no one can tell it from venison.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Lobster Sauce.</purpose>



--Take a <ingredient>lobster,</ingredient> bruise the body and spawn, that is in the inside, very fine, with the back of a spoon; mince the <ingredient>meat of the tail and claws</ingredient> very small; melt your <ingredient>butter</ingredient> of a good thickness, put in the bruised part, and shake it well together; then put in the minced meat, with a little <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated, and a spoonful of <ingredient>white wine.</ingredient> Let it just <pb n="109" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=115"/> boil up, and pour it into boats, or over your <ingredient>fish.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Lemon Sauce for boiled Fowls.</purpose>



--Take a <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> pare off the <ingredient>rind,</ingredient> then cut it into slices, cut it small, and take all the kernels out; bruise the <ingredient>liver</ingredient> with two or three spoonfuls of good <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> then melt some <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> mix all together, give them a boil, and cut in a little <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> very small.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Oyster Sauce.</purpose>



--Take a pint of <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> that are tolerably large, put them into a sauce-pan with their own <ingredient>liquor,</ingredient> a blade of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>whole pepper,</ingredient> and a bit of <ingredient>lemon-peel;</ingredient> let them stew over the fire till the <pb n="110" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=116"/><ingredient>oysters</ingredient> are plump; pour all into a clean pan, and wash them carefully one by one, out of the liquor; strain about a gill of the liquor through a fine sieve, add the same quantity of good <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> cut half a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in pieces, roll up some in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and then put in all your <ingredient>oysters;</ingredient> set it over the fire, shake it round often till it boils, and add a spoonful of <ingredient>white wine;</ingredient> let it just boil, and pour it into your bason or boat. Many people add an <ingredient>anchovy,</ingredient> which greatly enriches the sauce.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Parsley Sauce.</purpose>



--Tie <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> up in a bunch, and boil it till soft; shred it fine, and mix it with <ingredient>melted butter.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">A pretty Sauce for boiled Fowls.</purpose>



--Take the <ingredient>liver of the fowl,</ingredient> bruise it with a little of the <ingredient>liquor,</ingredient> cut a little <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> fine, melt some good <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and mix the <ingredient>liver</ingredient> by degrees; give it a boil and pour it into the dish.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To roast Beef.</purpose>



--If it be a <ingredient>sirloin</ingredient> or <ingredient>chump,</ingredient> <ingredient>butter</ingredient> a piece of writing-paper, and fasten it on to the back of your meat with small <implement>skewers,</implement> and lay it down to a soaking fire, at a proper distance. As soon as your meat is warm, dust on some <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and baste it with <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> then sprinkle some <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and, at times, baste with what comes from it. About a quarter of an hour before you take it up, remove the paper, dust on a little <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and baste <pb n="112" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=118"/> it with a piece of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> that it may go to table with a good froth. Garnish your dish with scraped <ingredient>horse-radish;</ingredient> and serve it up with <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> <ingredient>brocoli,</ingredient> <ingredient>French beans,</ingredient> <ingredient>cauliflower,</ingredient> or <ingredient>celery.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To roast a Cod's Head.</purpose>



--Wash and scour the <ingredient>head</ingredient> very clean, scotch it with a knife, strew a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> on it, and lay it before the fire; throw away the <ingredient>water</ingredient> that runs from it the first half hour, then strew on it some <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and baste it often with <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Take all the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> of the <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> and <ingredient>meat gravy,</ingredient> some <ingredient>horse-radish,</ingredient> <ingredient>shallots,</ingredient> <ingredient>whole pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and a <ingredient>bay-leaf</ingredient> or two; boil this <pb n="113" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=119"/> liquor up with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>liver</ingredient> of the <ingredient>fish</ingredient> boiled, broke, and strained into it, with the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> of two or three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>oysters,</ingredient> shrimps, and balls made of <ingredient>fish;</ingredient> put fried <ingredient>fish</ingredient> around it. Garnish with <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> and horse-<ingredient>radish.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To roast a Turkey, Goose, Duck, Fowl, &amp;c.</purpose>



--When you roast a <ingredient>turkey,</ingredient> <ingredient>goose,</ingredient> <ingredient>fowl,</ingredient> or <ingredient>chicken,</ingredient> lay them down to a good fire. Singe them clean with <ingredient>white paper,</ingredient> baste them with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and dust on some <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> As to time, a large <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> will take an hour and twenty minutes--a middling one a full hour--a full grown <ingredient>goose,</ingredient> if young, an hour--a large <ingredient>fowl</ingredient> three quarters of an hour--a middling one half an hour, and a small <ingredient>chicken</ingredient> <pb n="114" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=120"/> twenty minutes; but this depends entirely on the goodness of your fire.</p><p>When your <ingredient>fowls</ingredient> are thoroughly plump, and the smoke draws from the breast to the fire, you may be sure they are very near done. Then baste them with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> dust on a very little <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and as soon as they have a good froth, serve them up.</p><p><ingredient>Geese</ingredient> and <ingredient>ducks</ingredient> are commonly seasoned with <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> <ingredient>sage,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></p><p>A <ingredient>turkey,</ingredient> when roasted, is generally stuffed in the craw with <ingredient>forc'd meat,</ingredient> or the following <ingredient>stuffing:</ingredient> take a pound of <ingredient>veal,</ingredient> as much <ingredient>grated bread,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>suet</ingredient> cut and beat very fine, a little <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> with a small bit of <ingredient>thyme</ingredient> or <ingredient>savory,</ingredient> two <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> half a <pb n="115" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=121"/><ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated, a tea-spoonful of shred <ingredient>lemon-peel,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>yolks of two eggs.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">Sauce for a Turkey.</purpose>



--Good <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> in a boat; and either <ingredient>bread, onion, or oyster sauce</ingredient> in a bason.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">Sauce for a Goose.</purpose>



--A little good <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> in a boat, <ingredient>apple sauce</ingredient> in a bason, and <ingredient>mustard.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">Sauce for a Duck.</purpose>



--A little <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> in the dish, and <ingredient>onions</ingredient> in a <implement>tea-cup.</implement></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">Sauce for Fowls.</purpose>



--<ingredient>Parsley</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> or <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> in the dish, and either <ingredient>bread sauce,</ingredient> <ingredient>oyster sauce,</ingredient> or <ingredient>egg sauce</ingredient> in a bason.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To roast Wild Ducks, Wigeons, or Teal.</purpose>



--<ingredient>Wild fowl</ingredient> are in general liked rather under done; and if your fire is <pb n="116" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=122"/> very good and brisk, a <ingredient>duck</ingredient> or <ingredient>wigeon</ingredient> will be done in a quarter of an hour; for as soon as they are well hot through they begin to lose their gravy, and if not drawn off, will eat hard. A <ingredient>teal</ingredient> is done in little more than ten minutes.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To roast an Eel.</purpose>



--Scour the <ingredient>eel</ingredient> well with <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> skin him almost to the tail; then gut, wash, and dry him. Take a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>suet</ingredient> shred as fine as possible, <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> and a <ingredient>shallot,</ingredient> and mix them together with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg;</ingredient> scotch your <ingredient>eel</ingredient> on both sides, wash it with <ingredient>yolks of eggs,</ingredient> lay some <ingredient>seasoning</ingredient> over it, then draw the skin over it, and tie it to the spit; baste it with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and <pb n="117" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=123"/> make the sauce of <ingredient>anchovies</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> melted.</p><p><variation>Any other <ingredient>river or sea fish,</ingredient> that are large enough, may be dressed in the same manner.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">A Fowl, or Turkey, roasted with Chesnuts.</purpose>



--Roast a quarter of a hundred of <ingredient>chesnuts,</ingredient> and peel them; save out eight or ten, the rest bruise in a <implement>mortar,</implement> with the <ingredient>liver of a fowl,</ingredient> a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>ham</ingredient> well pounded, and <ingredient>sweet herbs</ingredient> and <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> chopped fine. Season it with <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Mix all these together, and put them into the belly of your <ingredient>fowl:</ingredient> spit it, and tie the neck and vent close. For sauce, take the rest of the chesnuts, cut them <pb n="118" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=124"/> in pieces, and put them into a strong <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> with a glass of <ingredient>white wine;</ingredient> thicken with a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Pour the <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> in the dish, and garnish with <ingredient>orange</ingredient> and <ingredient>water-cresses.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="german"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">The German way of dressing Fowls.</purpose>



--Take a <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> or <ingredient>fowl,</ingredient> stuff the breast with what <ingredient>force-meat</ingredient> you like, fill the body with <ingredient>roasted chesnuts</ingredient> peeled, and lay it down to roast; take half a pint of good <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> with a little piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> boil these together, with some small <ingredient>turnips</ingredient> and <ingredient>sausages</ingredient> cut in slices, and fried or boiled. Garnish with chesnuts.</p><p><variation>You may dress 



<purpose><alt synonym1="the german way of dressing ducks">ducks</alt></purpose>



the same way.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To roast a green Goose with green Sauce.</purpose>



--Roast your <ingredient>goose</ingredient> nicely; in the mean time, make your sauce thus: take half a pint of the <ingredient>juice of sorrel,</ingredient> a spoonful of <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> a little grated <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and some <ingredient>grated bread;</ingredient> boil this over a gentle fire, and sweeten it with <ingredient>pounded sugar</ingredient> to your taste; let your <ingredient>goose</ingredient> have a good froth on it before you take it up; put some good strong <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> in the dish, and the same in a boat. Garnish with <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To roast a Hare.</purpose>



--Case and truss your <ingredient>hare,</ingredient> and then make a pudding thus: a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>beef suet</ingredient> minced fine; as much <ingredient>bread crumbs;</ingredient> the <ingredient>liver</ingredient> chopped fine; <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> <pb n="120" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=126"/> and <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> shred fine, seasoned with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient> Moisten it with an <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> and put it into the <ingredient>hare;</ingredient> sew up the belly, and lay it down to a good fire. Let your <implement>dripping-pan</implement> be very clean; put into it a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and six ounces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and baste it with this till the whole is used. About five minutes before you take it up, dust on a little <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and baste with fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> that it may go to table with a good froth. Put a little <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> in the dish, and the rest in a boat. Garnish your dish with <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To roast Lamb.</purpose>



--Lay it down to a clear good fire, that will want little stirring; then baste it with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and <pb n="121" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=127"/> dust on a little <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> baste it with what falls from it: and a little before you take it up, baste it again with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and sprinkle on a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> shred fine. Send it up to table with a nice <ingredient>salad,</ingredient> <ingredient>mint sauce,</ingredient> <ingredient>green peas,</ingredient> <ingredient>French beans,</ingredient> or <ingredient>cauliflower.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To roast Larks.</purpose>



--Truss your <ingredient>larks</ingredient> with the legs across, and put a <ingredient>sage leaf</ingredient> over the breast; put them upon a long fine <implement>skewer,</implement> and between every <ingredient>lark</ingredient> a little piece of thin <ingredient>bacon;</ingredient> then tie the <implement>skewer</implement> to a spit, and roast them at a quick, clear fire; baste them with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and strew over them some crumbs of <ingredient>bread</ingredient> mixed with <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> fry some <ingredient>bread crumbs</ingredient> of a nice brown, <pb n="122" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=128"/> in a bit of <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> lay your <ingredient>larks</ingredient> round in your dish, the <ingredient>bread</ingredient> crumbs in the middle, with sliced <ingredient>orange</ingredient> for garnish. Send good <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> in a boat.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To roast a Shoulder or Leg of Mutton stuffed.</purpose>



--Stuff a <ingredient>leg of mutton</ingredient> with <ingredient>mutton-suet,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>grated bread,</ingredient> and <ingredient>yolks of eggs;</ingredient> then stick it all over with <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> and roast it; when it is about half done cut off some of the under side of the fleshy end in little bits; put those into a <implement>pipkin</implement> with a pint of <ingredient>oysters, liquor and all,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> and half a pint of <ingredient>hot water;</ingredient> stew them till half the liquor is wasted, then put in a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> shake all together, and when the <ingredient>mutton</ingredient> <pb n="123" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=129"/> is done enough take it up; pour the sauce over it, and send it to table.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To roast Mutton, Venison fashion.</purpose>



--Take a hind quarter of <ingredient>fat mutton,</ingredient> and cut the leg like a haunch; lay it in a pan with the back side of it down, pour a bottle of <ingredient>red wine</ingredient> over it, and let it lie twenty-four hours; then spit it, and baste it with the same liquor and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> all the time it is roasting, at a good quick fire, and two hours and a half will do it. Have a little good <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> in a boat, and <ingredient>currant jelly</ingredient> in another.</p><p><variation>A good fat <ingredient>neck of mutton</ingredient> eats finely done thus.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To fry Eggs as round as Balls.</purpose>



--Having a deep frying pan, and three pints of <ingredient>clarified butter,</ingredient> heat it as hot as for fritters, and stir it with a stick till it runs round like a whirlpool; then break an <ingredient>egg</ingredient> into the middle, and turn it round with your stick, till it be as hard as a poached egg; the whirling round of the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> will make it as round as a ball; then take it up with a <implement>slice,</implement> and put it in a dish before the fire; they will keep hot half an hour, and yet be soft; so you may do as many as you please. You may poach them in <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> in the same manner.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To fry Mutton Cutlets.</purpose>



--Take a handful of <ingredient>grated bread,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>thyme</ingredient> <pb n="125" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=131"/> and <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon peel</ingredient> shred very small, with some <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> then take a <ingredient>loin of mutton,</ingredient> cut it into <ingredient>steaks,</ingredient> and let them be well beaten; then take the <ingredient>yolks of two eggs,</ingredient> and rub the <ingredient>steaks</ingredient> all over. Strew on the <ingredient>grated bread</ingredient> with these ingredients mixed together. For the sauce take <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> with a spoonful or two of <ingredient>claret,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>anchovy.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To fry Sweetbreads and Kidneys.</purpose>



--After splitting the <ingredient>kidneys,</ingredient> fry them and the <ingredient>sweetbreads</ingredient> in <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Serve them up with a <ingredient>brown ragout sauce,</ingredient> and <ingredient>mushrooms;</ingredient> garnish with <ingredient>fried parsley</ingredient> and <ingredient>sliced lemon.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To broil Pigeons.</purpose>



--Put a bit of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> some shred <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> in the bellies of the <ingredient>pigeons,</ingredient> and tie them up neck and vent. Set your <implement>gridiron</implement> high, that they may not burn; and send them up with a little <ingredient>melted butter</ingredient> in a cup. You may split them, and broil them with a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> or you may roast them, and serve them up with a little <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in a boat.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To broil Cod, Salmon, Whiting, or Haddock.</purpose>



--<ingredient>Flour</ingredient> them, and have a quick clear fire; set your <implement>gridiron</implement> high, broil them of a fine brown, and lay them in a dish. For sauce take good <ingredient>melted butter,</ingredient> with the body of <pb n="127" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=133"/> a <ingredient>lobster</ingredient> broiled therein; cut the meat small, put all together into the <ingredient>melted butter,</ingredient> make it hot, and pour it into the dish, or into basons. Garnish with <ingredient>horse-radish</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To stew Beef Steaks.</purpose>



--Half broil the <ingredient>beef steaks;</ingredient> then put them into a <implement>stew-pan,</implement> season them with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> according to your palate; just cover them with <ingredient>gravy.</ingredient> Also put in a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Let them stew gently for half an hour, then add the <ingredient>yolks of two eggs</ingredient> beat up, and stir all together for two or three minutes, and serve it up. Garnish with <ingredient>pickles</ingredient> and <ingredient>horse-radish</ingredient> scraped.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To stew Brisket of Beef.</purpose>



--Having rubbed the <ingredient>brisket</ingredient> with common <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>saltpetre,</ingredient> let it lie four days. Then lard the skin with <ingredient>fat bacon,</ingredient> and put it into a <implement>stew-pan</implement> with a quart of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>red wine</ingredient> or strong <ingredient>beer,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> a bunch of <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> three or four <ingredient>shallots,</ingredient> some <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and half a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated. Cover the pan very close. Then fry some square pieces of boiled <ingredient>turnips</ingredient> very brown. Strain the liquor the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> was stewed in, thicken it with <ingredient>burnt butter,</ingredient> and having mixed the <ingredient>turnips</ingredient> with it, pour all together over the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> in a large dish. Serve it up hot, and garnish with <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> sliced. An <ingredient>ox cheek,</ingredient> or a <ingredient>leg of beef,</ingredient> may be served up in the same manner.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To stew Red Cabbage.</purpose>



--Take a <ingredient>red cabbage,</ingredient> lay it in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> for an hour, cut it into thin slices across, and then into little pieces. Put it into a <implement>stew-pan,</implement> with a pound of <ingredient>sausages,</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> a little bit of <ingredient>ham</ingredient> or <ingredient>lean bacon;</ingredient> cover it close, and let it stew half an hour; then take the pan off the fire and skim away the fat, shake in a little <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and set it on again. Let it stew two or three minutes, then lay the <ingredient>sausages</ingredient> in the dish and pour the rest all over. You may, before you take it up, put in half a spoonful of <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy" class2="fruitvegbeans"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To stew Spinach and Eggs.</purpose>



--Pick and wash your <ingredient>spinach</ingredient> very clean, put it into a sauce-pan without <ingredient>water,</ingredient> <pb n="130" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=136"/> throw in a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> cover it close, and shake the pan often; when it is just tender, and whilst it is green, put it into a sieve to drain, and lay it in your dish. In the mean time have a <implement>stew-pan</implement> of <ingredient>water</ingredient> boiling, break as many <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> in separate cups as you would poach. When the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils put in the <ingredient>eggs;</ingredient> have an <implement>egg-slice</implement> ready to take them out with, lay them on the <ingredient>spinach,</ingredient> and garnish the dish with <ingredient>orange</ingredient> cut in quarters, and send up <ingredient>melted butter</ingredient> in a cup.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To stew a Turkey or Fowl.</purpose>



--Take a <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> or <ingredient>fowl,</ingredient> put it into a sauce-pan or pot, with a sufficient quantity of <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> or good <ingredient>broth;</ingredient> a bunch of <ingredient>celery</ingredient> cut small, and a muslin rag, <pb n="131" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=137"/> filled with <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> tied loose, with an <ingredient>onion</ingredient> and a sprig of <ingredient>thyme.</ingredient> When these have stewed softly till enough, take up the <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> or <ingredient>fowl,</ingredient> thicken the liquor it was stewed in with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and having dished the <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> or <ingredient>fowl,</ingredient> pour the <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> into the dish.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To stew Giblets.</purpose>



--Let the <ingredient>giblets</ingredient> be clean picked and washed, the <ingredient>feet</ingredient> skinned, and the bill cut off, the <ingredient>head</ingredient> split in two, the <ingredient>pinion bones</ingredient> broken, the <ingredient>liver</ingredient> and <ingredient>gizzard</ingredient> cut in four, and the <ingredient>neck</ingredient> in two pieces: put them into half a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a small <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> and <ingredient>sweet herbs.</ingredient> Cover the sauce-pan close, and let them stew till enough, upon a slow fire. Then <pb n="132" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=138"/> season them with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> take out the <ingredient>onion</ingredient> and <ingredient>herbs,</ingredient> and pour them into a dish with all the liquor.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To stew a Hare.</purpose>



--Beat it well with a rolling-pin in its own blood. Cut it into little bits and fry them. Then put the <ingredient>hare</ingredient> into a <implement>stew-pan,</implement> with a quart of strong <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> according to the palate, and let it stew till tender. Thicken it with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Serve it up in its <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> with <ingredient>sippets</ingredient> in the dish, and <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> sliced for garnish.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To stew Oysters or Muscles.</purpose>



--Plump them in their own liquor; then, having drained off the liquor, wash them clean in <ingredient>fair water.</ingredient> Set the <pb n="133" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=139"/><ingredient>liquor drained from the oysters,</ingredient> or as much as necessary, (with the addition of an equal quantity of <ingredient>water</ingredient> or <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>whole pepper,</ingredient> and a blade of <ingredient>mace</ingredient>) over the fire, and boil it well. Then put in the <ingredient>oysters,</ingredient> and let them just boil up, and thicken with a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour:</ingredient> some will add the <ingredient>yolk of an egg.</ingredient> Serve them up with <ingredient>sippets</ingredient> and the liquor, and garnish the dish with <ingredient>grated bread</ingredient> or <ingredient>sliced lemon.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Gravy Soup.</purpose>



--Take the <ingredient>bones of a rump of beef,</ingredient> and a piece of the <ingredient>neck,</ingredient> and boil it till you have all the goodness of it; then strain it off, and take a good piece of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> put it in a <implement>stew-pan,</implement> and brown it, <pb n="134" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=140"/> then put to it an <ingredient>onion</ingredient> stuck with <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> some <ingredient>celery,</ingredient> <ingredient>endive,</ingredient> <ingredient>spinach,</ingredient> and three <ingredient>carrots;</ingredient> put to your <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> some <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> and let it boil all together: then put in some <ingredient>sippets of bread</ingredient> dried by the fire; and you may add a glass of <ingredient>red wine.</ingredient> Serve it up with a <ingredient>French roll</ingredient> toasted and laid in the middle.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a rich Giblet Soup.</purpose>



--Take four pounds of <ingredient>gravy beef,</ingredient> two pounds of <ingredient>scrag of mutton,</ingredient> two pounds of <ingredient>scrag of veal;</ingredient> stew them well down in a sufficient quantity of <ingredient>water</ingredient> for a strong broth; let it stand till it is quite cold, then skim the fat clean of. Take two pair of <ingredient>giblets</ingredient> well scalded and cleaned, put them into your broth, <pb n="135" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=141"/> and let them simmer till they are stewed tender; then take out your <ingredient>giblets,</ingredient> and run the soup through a fine sieve to catch the small bones; then take an ounce of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and put it into a <implement>stew-pan,</implement> mixing a proper quantity of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> to make it of a fine light brown. Take a small handful of <ingredient>chives,</ingredient> the same of <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> and a very little of <ingredient>sweet marjoram;</ingredient> chop all these <ingredient>herbs</ingredient> together excessively small; set your soup over a slow fire, put in your <ingredient>giblets,</ingredient> <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and small <ingredient>herbs;</ingredient> then take a pint of <ingredient>Madeira wine,</ingredient> some <ingredient>Cayenne pepper,</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to your palate. Let them all simmer together, till the <ingredient>herbs</ingredient> are tender, and the soup is finished. Send it up to table with the <ingredient>giblets</ingredient> in it.</p> <pb n="136" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=142"/><p>The <ingredient>livers</ingredient> must be stewed in a sauce-pan by themselves, and put in the dish when you serve it up.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a good Pea Soup.</purpose>



--Take a quart of <ingredient>split peas,</ingredient> put them into a gallon of <ingredient>soft water,</ingredient> with a bunch of <ingredient>herbs,</ingredient> some <ingredient>whole Jamaica and black pepper,</ingredient> two or three <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> a pound of <ingredient>lean beef,</ingredient> a pound of <ingredient>mutton,</ingredient> and a pound of the <ingredient>belly-piece of fat pork;</ingredient> boil all together, till your meat is thoroughly tender, and your soup strong; then strain it through a sieve, and pour it into a clean sauce-pan; cut and wash three or four large heads of <ingredient>celery,</ingredient> some <ingredient>spinach,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>dried mint,</ingredient> rubbed fine; boil it till your <ingredient>celery</ingredient> is tender, then serve it up with <ingredient>bread</ingredient> cut in dice and fried brown.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Green Pea Soup.</purpose>



--Have a <ingredient>knuckle of veal</ingredient> of four pounds, a pint and a half of the oldest <ingredient>green peas</ingredient> shelled, set them over the fire with five quarts of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> add two or three blades of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> a quarter of an ounce of <ingredient>whole pepper,</ingredient> a small <ingredient>onion</ingredient> stuck with three <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> and a bunch of <ingredient>sweet herbs;</ingredient> cover it close, and let it boil till half is wasted; strain it off, and pass your liquor through a sieve, put it into a clean sauce-pan, with a pint of the youngest <ingredient>peas,</ingredient> the <ingredient>heart of a cabbage,</ingredient> a <ingredient>lettuce</ingredient> or two, and the white part of three or four heads of <ingredient>celery</ingredient> cut small; cover it close, and let it stew for an hour. If you think it is not thick enough, take some of your soup, and put in half a spoonful <pb n="138" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=144"/> of <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> stir it in a bason till it is smooth, pour it into your soup, stir it well together, and let it boil for ten minutes; then dish it up with the <ingredient>crust of a French roll.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a White Portable Soup.</purpose>



--Take a <ingredient>leg of veal,</ingredient> bone it, and take off all the skin and fat; take likewise two dozen of <ingredient>fowl's or chicken's feet,</ingredient> washed clean, and chopped to pieces; put all into a large <implement>stoving-pot,</implement> with three gallons of <ingredient>soft water,</ingredient> and let it stove gently, till the meat is so tender as to separate. You must keep your pot tight covered, and a constant fire during the time of its stoving; in about seven or eight hours try your jelly in a cup, and when quite cold, if <pb n="139" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=145"/> it is so stiff as that you can cut it with a knife, take it off, and strain it through a sieve, and take off all the fat and scum first with a spoon, and then with a <implement>filtering paper.</implement> Provide china cups, and fill them with the clear jelly; set them in a <implement>gravy-pan,</implement> or a large <implement>stew-pan</implement> of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> over a stove; in this <ingredient>water</ingredient> boil your jelly in the cups, till it is as thick as glue. After which let them stand in the <ingredient>water</ingredient> till they are quite cold. Before you turn them out of your cups run the edge of a knife round to loosen them; then turn them upon a piece of new flannel, which will draw out all the moisture gradually. Turn them every six or eight hours, till they are perfectly dry, and like a piece of glue; keep them <pb n="140" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=146"/> in as dry a place as you can, and in a little time they will be so hard that you may carry them in your pocket, without the least inconvenience. When you want to use it take a piece about the bigness of a walnut, and pour a pint of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> on it, stirring it till it is dissolved; season it with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to your taste, and you will have a bason of strong broth. If you want a dish of soup, boil <ingredient>vermicelli</ingredient> in <ingredient>water;</ingredient> then to a <ingredient>cake of your soup</ingredient> pour a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> so that four cakes will make two quarts; when it is thoroughly melted, set it over the fire just to simmer; pour it into the dish, put in thin slices of <ingredient>bread</ingredient> hardened before the fire, and the <ingredient>vermicelli</ingredient> upon them. Thus you have a dish of soup in about <pb n="141" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=147"/> half an hour. Whilst this is doing, you may have any thing dressed to follow, which will not only be a good addition to your dinner, but saving time.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Vermicelli Soup.</purpose>



--Take two quarts of strong <ingredient>veal broth,</ingredient> put it into a clean sauce-pan, with a piece of <ingredient>bacon</ingredient> stuck with <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> and half an ounce of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> then take a small <ingredient>fowl</ingredient> trussed to boil, break the breast bone, and put it into your soup; stove it close, and let it stew three quarters of an hour; take about two ounces of <ingredient>vermicelli,</ingredient> and put to it some of the <ingredient>broth;</ingredient> set it over the fire till it is quite tender. When your soup is ready take out the <ingredient>fowl,</ingredient> and <pb n="142" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=148"/> put it into the dish; take out your <ingredient>bacon,</ingredient> skim your soup as soon as possible, then pour it on the <ingredient>fowl,</ingredient> and lay your <ingredient>vermicelli</ingredient> all over it; cut some <ingredient>French bread</ingredient> thin, put it into your soup, and send it to table.</p><p><variation>If you choose, you may make your soup with a <ingredient>knuckle of veal,</ingredient> and send a handsome piece of it in the middle of the dish, instead of the fowl.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Soup Lorraine.</purpose>



--Have ready a strong <ingredient>veal broth</ingredient> that is white, and clean scummed from all fat; blanch a pound of <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> beat them in a <implement>mortar</implement> with a little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> to prevent their oiling, and the <ingredient>yolks of four poached eggs,</ingredient> the <ingredient>lean part of the legs, and all the white part of a <pb n="143" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=149"/> roasted fowl;</ingredient> pound all together, as fine as possible; then take three parts of the <ingredient>veal broth,</ingredient> put it into a clean <implement>stew-pan,</implement> put your ingredients in, and mix them well together; chip in the <ingredient>crust of two French rolls</ingredient> well rasped; boil all together over a stove, or a clear fire. Take a <ingredient>French roll,</ingredient> cut a piece out of the top, and take out all the crumb; mince the <ingredient>white part of a roasted fowl</ingredient> very fine, season it with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and a little beaten <ingredient>mace;</ingredient> put in about an ounce of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and moisten it with two spoonfuls of your soup strained to it; set it over the stove to be thorough hot. Cut some <ingredient>French rolls</ingredient> in slices and set them before the fire to crisp; then strain off your soup through a <pb n="144" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=150"/> <implement>tammy</implement> or a <implement>lawn strainer</implement> into another clean stew-pot; let it stew till it is as thick as cream; then have your dish ready, put in some of your crisp <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> fill your roll with the mince, and lay on the top as close as possible; put it in the middle of the dish, and pour a ladleful of your soup over it; put in your <ingredient>bread</ingredient> first, then pour in the soup till the dish is full. Garnish with <ingredient>petty patties,</ingredient> or make a rim for your dish, and garnish with <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> raced.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Sorrel Soup, with Eggs.</purpose>



--Take the <ingredient>chump end of a loin of mutton,</ingredient> and part of a <ingredient>knuckle of veal,</ingredient> to make your stock with; season it with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> and a bunch of <ingredient>sweet herbs;</ingredient> boil it till it is as rich <pb n="145" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=151"/> as you would have it; strain it off, and put it into a clean sauce-pan; put in a young <ingredient>fowl,</ingredient> cover it over and stove it; then take three or four large handfuls of <ingredient>sorrel</ingredient> washed clean; chop it grossly, fry it in <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> put it to your soup, and let it boil till your <ingredient>fowl</ingredient> is thoroughly done; skim it clean, and send it to table with the <ingredient>fowl</ingredient> in the middle, and six <ingredient>poached eggs</ingredient> placed around about it. Garnish the dish with <ingredient>sippets,</ingredient> and <ingredient>stewed sorrel.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Asparagus Soup.</purpose>



--Take five or six pounds of <ingredient>lean beef</ingredient> cut in lumps, and rolled in <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> put it in your <implement>stew-pan,</implement> with two or three slices of <ingredient>fat bacon</ingredient> at the bottom; then put it over a slow fire, and cover it close, <pb n="146" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=152"/> stirring it now and then till the gravy is drawn; then put in two quarts of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and half a pint of <ingredient>ale.</ingredient> Cover it close, and let it stew gently for an hour, with some <ingredient>whole pepper,</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to your mind: then strain off the liquor, and take off the fat; put in the <ingredient>leaves of white beets,</ingredient> some <ingredient>spinach,</ingredient> some <ingredient>cabbage lettuce,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>mint,</ingredient> some <ingredient>sorrel,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>sweet marjoram</ingredient> powdered; let these boil up in your liquor, then put in the <ingredient>green tops of asparagus</ingredient> cut small, and let them boil till all is tender. Serve it up hot, with a <ingredient>French roll</ingredient> in the middle.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a Craw-Fish Soup.</purpose>



--Cleanse them, and boil them in <ingredient>water,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice;</ingredient> pull off their feet and <pb n="147" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=153"/> tails and fry them; break the rest of them in a <implement>stone mortar,</implement> season them with <ingredient>savory spice,</ingredient> and an <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> a <ingredient>hard egg,</ingredient> <ingredient>grated bread,</ingredient> and <ingredient>sweet herbs</ingredient> boiled in good <ingredient>table beer;</ingredient> strain it, and put to it <ingredient>scalded chopped parsley,</ingredient> and <ingredient>French rolls;</ingredient> then put in the fried <ingredient>craw-fish,</ingredient> with a few <ingredient>mushrooms.</ingredient> Garnish the dish with <ingredient>sliced lemon,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>feet and tail of a craw-fish.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Oyster Soup.</purpose>



--Have ready a good <ingredient>fish stock,</ingredient> then take two quarts of <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> without the beards; bray the hard part in a <implement>mortar,</implement> with the <ingredient>yolks of ten hard eggs.</ingredient> Set what quantity of <ingredient>fish stock</ingredient> you shall want over the fire with your <ingredient>oysters;</ingredient> season it with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and grated <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient> <pb n="148" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=154"/> When it boils put in the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and let it boil till it is as thick as cream. Dish it up with <ingredient>bread</ingredient> cut in dice.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make an Eel Soup.</purpose>



--Take <ingredient>eels</ingredient> according to the quantity of soup you would make--a pound of <ingredient>eels</ingredient> will make a pint of soup; so to every pound of <ingredient>eels</ingredient> put a quart of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> a <ingredient>crust of bread,</ingredient> two or three blades of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>whole pepper,</ingredient> an <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> and a bundle of <ingredient>sweet herbs;</ingredient> cover them close, and let them boil till half the liquor is wasted; then strain it, toast some <ingredient>bread</ingredient> and cut it small, lay the <ingredient>bread</ingredient> in the dish, and pour in your soup. If you have a <implement>stew-hole,</implement> set the dish over it for a minute, and <pb n="149" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=155"/> send it to table. If you find your soup not rich enough, you must let it boil till it is as strong as you would have it, and add a piece of <ingredient>carrot</ingredient> to brown it.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a Brown Soup.</purpose>



--Into a clean sauce-pan put three quarts, or more, of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with <ingredient>raspings</ingredient> sufficient to thicken it, two or three <ingredient>onions</ingredient> cut across, two or three <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> some <ingredient>whole pepper,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> cover it close and let it boil about an hour and a half, then strain it through a sieve; have <ingredient>celery,</ingredient> <ingredient>carrots,</ingredient> <ingredient>endive,</ingredient> <ingredient>lettuce,</ingredient> <ingredient>spinach,</ingredient> and what other <ingredient>herbs</ingredient> you like, not cut too small, and fry them in <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> take a clean <implement>stew-pan,</implement> that is large enough for your ingredients, <pb n="150" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=156"/> put in a good piece of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> dust in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and keep it stirring till it is of a fine brown; then pour in your <ingredient>herbs</ingredient> and soup, boil it till the <ingredient>herbs</ingredient> are tender, and the soup of a proper thickness. Have <ingredient>bread</ingredient> cut in dice, and fried brown; pour your soup into the dish, put some of the <ingredient>bread</ingredient> into the soup, the rest in a plate, and serve it up.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a White Soup.</purpose>



--Put in a clean sauce-pan two or three quarts of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> the <ingredient>crumb of a two-penny loaf,</ingredient> with a bundle of <ingredient>herbs,</ingredient> some <ingredient>whole pepper,</ingredient> two or three <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> an <ingredient>onion</ingredient> or two cut across, and a little <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> let it boil covered till it is quite smooth; take <ingredient>celery, endive and lettuce, <pb n="151" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=157"/> only the white parts,</ingredient> cut them in pieces, not too small, and boil them till they are very tender, strain your soup off into a clean <implement>stew-pan;</implement> put your <ingredient>herbs</ingredient> in, with a good piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> stirred in it till the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is melted, and let it boil for some time, till it is very smooth. If any scum arises, take it off very clean. Soak a small <ingredient>French roll,</ingredient> nicely rasped, in some of the soup; put it in the middle of the dish, pour in the soup, and send it to table.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Onion Soup.</purpose>



--First put a tea-kettle of <ingredient>water</ingredient> on to boil, then slice six <ingredient>Spanish onions,</ingredient> or some of the largest <ingredient>onions</ingredient> you have got; <ingredient>flour</ingredient> them pretty well, then put them into <pb n="152" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=158"/> a <implement>stew-pan</implement> that will hold about three quarts, fry them in <ingredient>butter</ingredient> till they are of a fine brown, but not burnt; pour in <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> sufficient to fill the <implement>soup dish</implement> you intend; let it boil, and take half a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> break it in, and keep it stirring till your <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is melted: as it boils, skim it very well, and put in a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> cut a <ingredient>French roll</ingredient> into slices, and set it before the fire to crisp; poach seven or eight <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very nicely, cut off the ragged part of the whites, drain the <ingredient>water</ingredient> from them, and lay them upon every slice of roll; pour your soup into the dish, and put the <ingredient>bread</ingredient> and <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> carefully into the dish with a <implement>skimmer.</implement> If you have any <ingredient>spinach</ingredient> boiled, lay a <pb n="153" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=159"/> leaf between every piece of roll, and send it to table.</p><p>If you have any <ingredient>Parmesan cheese,</ingredient> scrape about an ounce very fine, and put it in when you pour on your <ingredient>boiling water;</ingredient> it gives it a very high flavor, and it is not to be perceived by the taste what it is.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a Rice Soup.</purpose>



--To two quarts of <ingredient>water</ingredient> put three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>rice,</ingredient> clean picked and washed, with a stick of <ingredient>cinnamon;</ingredient> let it be covered very close, and simmer till your <ingredient>rice</ingredient> is tender; take out the <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> and grate half a <ingredient>nutmeg;</ingredient> beat up the <ingredient>yolks of four eggs,</ingredient> and strain them to half a pint of <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> and as much <ingredient>pounded sugar</ingredient> as <pb n="154" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=160"/> will make it palatable; put this to your soup, and stir it very well together: set it over the fire, stirring it till it boils, and is of a good thickness; then send it to table.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Turnip Soup.</purpose>



--Pare a bunch of <ingredient>turnips,</ingredient> (save out three or four) put them into a gallon of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with half an ounce of <ingredient>white pepper,</ingredient> an <ingredient>onion</ingredient> stuck with <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> three blades of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> half a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> bruised, a good bunch of <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> and a large <ingredient>crust of bread.</ingredient> Boil them an hour and a half, then pass them through a sieve; clean a bunch of <ingredient>celery,</ingredient> cut it small, and put it into your <ingredient>turnips</ingredient> and liquor, with two of the <ingredient>turnips</ingredient> you saved, and two young <pb n="155" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=161"/><ingredient>carrots</ingredient> cut in dice; cover it close, and let it stew; then cut two <ingredient>turnips</ingredient> and <ingredient>carrots</ingredient> in dice, <ingredient>flour</ingredient> them, and fry them brown in <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> with two large <ingredient>onions</ingredient> cut thin, and fried likewise; put them all into your soup, with some <ingredient>vermicelli;</ingredient> let it boil softly, till your <ingredient>celery</ingredient> is tender, and your soup is good. Season it with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to your palate.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="soups"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Soup Meagre.</purpose>



--Take a bunch of <ingredient>celery</ingredient> washed clean, and cut in pieces a large handful of <ingredient>spinach,</ingredient> two <ingredient>cabbage lettuces,</ingredient> and some <ingredient>parsley;</ingredient> wash all very clean, and shred them small; then take a large clean <implement>stew-pan,</implement> put in about half a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and when it is quite <pb n="156" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=162"/> hot, slice four large <ingredient>onions</ingredient> very thin, and put into your <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> stir them well together for two or three minutes; then put in the rest of your <ingredient>herbs;</ingredient> shake all well together for near twenty minutes; dust in some <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and stir them together; pour in two quarts of <ingredient>boiling water;</ingredient> season with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and beaten <ingredient>mace;</ingredient> chip a handful of <ingredient>crust of bread,</ingredient> and put in; boil it half an hour, then beat up the <ingredient>yolks of three eggs</ingredient> in a spoonful of <ingredient>vinegar;</ingredient> pour it in, stir it for two or three minutes, and then send it to table.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Icing for Tarts.</purpose>



--Beat and sift a quarter of a pound of fine <ingredient>loaf sugar.</ingredient> Put it into a <implement>mortar</implement> with <pb n="157" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=163"/> the <ingredient>white of one egg</ingredient> that has been well beat up. Add to these two spoonfuls of <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> and beat all together till it be so thick as just to run, observing to stir it all one way. It is laid on the tart with a brush or small bunch of feathers dipped in the icing. Set the tarts, when so done, into a very gentle oven to harden. But take care not to let them stand too long, for that will discolor them.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make an Almond Tart very good.</purpose>



--To half a pound of <ingredient>almonds</ingredient> blanched, and very finely beat with <ingredient>orange-flower water,</ingredient> put a pint of <ingredient>thick cream,</ingredient> two large <ingredient>Naples biscuits</ingredient> grated, and five <ingredient>yolks of eggs,</ingredient> with near half a pound of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> put <pb n="158" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=164"/> all into a dish garnished with <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> and lay slips in diamonds across the top; bake it in a cool oven; and when drawn out, stick slips of <ingredient>candied citron</ingredient> in each diamond.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Apple or Pear Tarts.</purpose>



--Pare them first, then cut them into quarters, and take the cores out; in the next place, cut each quarter across again; throw them so prepared into a saucepan, with no more <ingredient>water</ingredient> in it than will just cover the <ingredient>fruit;</ingredient> let them simmer over a slow fire till they are perfectly tender. Before you set your <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> on the fire, take care to put a good large piece of <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> into the <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Have the <implement>patty-pans</implement> in readiness, and strew fine <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> at the <pb n="159" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=165"/> bottom; then lay in the <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> and cover them with as much of the same <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> as you think convenient. Over each tart pour a teaspoonful of <ingredient>lemon-juice,</ingredient> and three spoonfuls of the liquor in which they were boiled. Then lay the lid over them, and put them into a slack oven.</p><p>If the tarts be made of <ingredient>apricots,</ingredient> &amp;c. you must neither pare them, nor cut them, nor stone them, nor use <ingredient>lemon juice,</ingredient> which is the only material difference between these and other fruit.</p><p><variation>Observe, with respect to 



<purpose rend="italic">preserved tarts,</purpose>



only lay in the <ingredient>preserved fruit,</ingredient> and put a very thin crust over them, and bake them as short a time as possible.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Orange or Lemon Tarts.</purpose>



--Take six large <ingredient>lemons,</ingredient> rub them very well with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and put them into <ingredient>water</ingredient> with a handful of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> in it, for two days; then change them into <ingredient>fresh water</ingredient> every day, without salt, for a fortnight; after this boil them two or three hours till they are tender, cut them into half quarters, and then again three-quarter-ways, as thin as you can. Take six <ingredient>pippins</ingredient> pared, cored, and quartered, and a pint of <ingredient>fair water,</ingredient> in which let them boil till the <ingredient>pippins</ingredient> break; put the liquor to your <ingredient>orange</ingredient> or <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> with half the pulp of the <ingredient>pippins</ingredient> well broken, and a pound of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Boil these together <pb n="161" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=167"/> a quarter of an hour, then put it in a <implement>gallipot,</implement> and squeeze an <ingredient>orange</ingredient> in it; if it be a lemon tart, squeeze a <ingredient>lemon;</ingredient> two spoonfuls is enough for a tart. Your <implement>patty-pans</implement> must be small and shallow. Use fine <ingredient>puff-paste,</ingredient> and very thin. A little baking will do. Just as your tarts are going into the oven, with a feather or brush do them over with <ingredient>melted butter,</ingredient> and then sift <ingredient>double refined sugar</ingredient> over them. This is a pretty icing.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Orange Puffs.</purpose>



--Pare off the <ingredient>rinds from Seville oranges,</ingredient> then rub them with <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> let them lie twenty-four hours in <ingredient>water,</ingredient> then boil them in four changes of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> making the first <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> drain them dry, and <pb n="162" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=168"/> beat them fine to a pulp; bruise in the pieces of all that you have pared, make it very sweet with <ingredient>fine sugar,</ingredient> and boil it till it is thick; let it stand till it is cold, and then it will be fit to put into the <ingredient>paste.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Lemon Puffs.</purpose>



--Take a pound and a quarter of <ingredient>double refined sugar</ingredient> beaten and sifted, and grate the <ingredient>rinds of two lemons,</ingredient> and mix well with the <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> then beat the <ingredient>whites of two new-laid eggs</ingredient> very well, and mix them well with the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon-peel;</ingredient> beat them together an hour and a quarter, then make them up in what form you please; be quick to set them in a moderate oven; do not take off the papers till cold.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Buns.</purpose>



--Take two pounds of <ingredient>fine flour,</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>ale-yeast,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>sack,</ingredient> and three <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> beaten; knead all these together with a little <ingredient>warm milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Lay it before the fire, till it rise very light. Then knead into it a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and a pound of <ingredient>round carraway comfits,</ingredient> and bake them in a quick oven on floured papers in what shape you please.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Maccaroons.</purpose>



--Take a pound of <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> let them be scalded, blanched, and thrown into <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> then dry them in a cloth, and pound them in a <implement>mortar;</implement> moisten them with <ingredient>orange-flower water,</ingredient> or the <ingredient>white of an egg,</ingredient> lest they turn to an oil; <pb n="164" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=170"/> after this take an equal quantity of fine <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> with three or four <ingredient>whites of eggs;</ingredient> beat all well together, and shape them on wafer paper with a spoon. Bake them on tin plates in a gentle oven.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make good Fritters.</purpose>



--Mix half a pint of good <ingredient>cream</ingredient> very thick with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> beat six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> leaving out four whites; add six spoonfuls of <ingredient>sack,</ingredient> and strain them into the <ingredient>cream;</ingredient> put in a little grated <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> then put in another half pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and beat the batter near an hour; pare and slice your <ingredient>apples</ingredient> thin, dip every piece in the batter, and throw them into a pan with <ingredient>boiling lard.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Paste for Raised Pies.</purpose>



--To half a peck of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> take two pounds of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and put it in pieces in a sauce-pan of <ingredient>water</ingredient> over the fire, and when the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is melted, make a hole in the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> skim off the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and put it in the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> with some of the <ingredient>water;</ingredient> then make it up in a stiff paste, and if you do not use it presently, put it before the fire in a cloth.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Paste for Custards.</purpose>



--Lay down <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and make it into a stiff paste with <ingredient>boiling water;</ingredient> sprinkle it with a little <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> to keep it from cracking.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a Chicken Pie.</purpose>



--Take six small <ingredient>chickens,</ingredient> roll a piece of <pb n="166" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=172"/><ingredient>butter</ingredient> in <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> season and lay them into a cover, with the <ingredient>marrow of two bones</ingredient> rolled up in the <ingredient>batter of eggs,</ingredient> a dozen of <ingredient>yolks of eggs boiled hard,</ingredient> and two dozen of <ingredient>savory balls;</ingredient> when you serve it up, pour in a quart of good <ingredient>gravy.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Minced Pies.</purpose>



--Shred a pound of <ingredient>neat's tongue</ingredient> parboiled, with two pounds of <ingredient>beef suet,</ingredient> five <ingredient>pippins,</ingredient> and a <ingredient>green lemon-peel;</ingredient> season it with an ounce of <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> two pounds of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>sack,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> the <ingredient>juice of a lemon,</ingredient> a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>citron, lemon and orange-peel.</ingredient> Mix these together, and fill the pies.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make an Oyster Pie.</purpose>



--Parboil a quart of large <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> in their own liquor, mince them small, and pound them in a <implement>mortar,</implement> with <ingredient>Pistachio nuts,</ingredient> <ingredient>marrow</ingredient> and <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> an <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> <ingredient>savory seeds,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>grated bread;</ingredient> or season as aforesaid whole. Lay on <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> close it, and serve it up hot.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Artichoke or Potatoe Pies.</purpose>



--Take <ingredient>artichoke bottoms,</ingredient> season them with a little <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> sliced, eight ounces of <ingredient>candied lemon</ingredient> and <ingredient>citron</ingredient> sliced, <ingredient>eringo-roots</ingredient> and <ingredient>prunellas,</ingredient> a slit of each, two ounces of <ingredient>barberries,</ingredient> eight ounces of <ingredient>marrow,</ingredient> eight ounces of <ingredient>raisins of the sun</ingredient> stoned, and two ounces of <pb n="168" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=174"/><ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> <ingredient>butter</ingredient> the bottom of the pie, put these in mixed together, adding eight ounces of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> on the top lid; bake it, and then put on a lear, made as for the chicken pie.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a Veal Pie.</purpose>



--Raise a high round pie, then cut a <ingredient>fillet of veal</ingredient> into three or four fillets, season it with <ingredient>savory seasoning,</ingredient> and a little minced <ingredient>sage</ingredient> and <ingredient>sweet herbs;</ingredient> lay it in the pie with slices of <ingredient>bacon</ingredient> at the bottom, and between each piece lay on <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and close the pie. When it is baked, and half cold, fill it up with <ingredient>clarified butter.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a plain Boiled Pudding.</purpose>



--Take a pint of <ingredient>new milk,</ingredient> mix with <pb n="169" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=175"/> it six <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beaten, two spoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> half a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated, a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Put this mixture into a cloth or bag. Put it into <ingredient>boiling water;</ingredient> and half an hour will boil it. Serve it up with <ingredient>melted butter.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a Light Pudding.</purpose>



--Take a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> or <ingredient>new milk</ingredient> from the cow; in which boil a little <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace</ingredient> in a fine linen rag. Take out the <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> and beat up the <ingredient>yolks of eight eggs,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> of four, with a glass of <ingredient>mountain wine;</ingredient> to which add a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> then mix them with the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Put in a <ingredient>halfpenny roll,</ingredient> a spoonful of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>rose-water;</ingredient> and having beat them well <pb n="170" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=176"/> together, tie all up in a thick cloth, and boil it for an hour. Melt <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>white wine</ingredient> for sauce, and pour it over the pudding when dished.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a Quaking Pudding.</purpose>



--Take a <ingredient>penny white loaf</ingredient> grated, two spoonfuls of <ingredient>flour of rice,</ingredient> and seven <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> beaten up. Put them in a quart of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> or <ingredient>new milk.</ingredient> Season them with <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated, and <ingredient>white rose-water.</ingredient> Tie it up, boil it an hour, and then serve it up with plain <ingredient>melted butter,</ingredient> and with <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>wine.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a fine Biscuit Pudding.</purpose>



--Grate three <ingredient>Naples biscuits,</ingredient> and <pb n="171" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=177"/> pour a pint of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> or <ingredient>milk</ingredient> over them hot. Cover it close till cold, then add a little grated <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> the <ingredient>yolks of four eggs</ingredient> and two <ingredient>whites</ingredient> beaten, a little <ingredient>orange flower or rose water,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> and half a spoonful of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Mix these well, and boil them in a China bason, tied in a cloth, for an hour. Turn it out of the bason, and serve it up in a dish with <ingredient>melted butter,</ingredient> and some fine <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> sprinkled over it.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make boiled Plum Pudding.</purpose>



--Shred a pound of <ingredient>beef suet</ingredient> very fine, to which add three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> stoned, a little grated <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> a large spoonful of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> some <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> <pb n="172" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=178"/> beaten, three spoonfuls of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and five spoonfuls of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Mix them well, and boil them in a cloth three hours. Pour over this pudding <ingredient>melted butter,</ingredient> when dished.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a boiled Suet Pudding.</purpose>



--Take a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> a pound of <ingredient>suet</ingredient> shred small, four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> two spoonfuls of <ingredient>grated ginger,</ingredient> or one of <ingredient>beaten pepper,</ingredient> and a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Mix the <ingredient>seasoning</ingredient> and <ingredient>suet</ingredient> first in one pint of the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and make a thick batter with <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Then mix in the rest of the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> with the <ingredient>seasoning</ingredient> and <ingredient>suet</ingredient> till it becomes a pretty thick batter. Boil it two hours. Serve it up with plain <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a boiled Potatoe Pudding.</purpose>



--Boil two pounds of <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> and beat them in a <implement>mortar</implement> fine; beat in half a pound of <ingredient>melted butter,</ingredient> and boil it half an hour. Pour <ingredient>melted butter</ingredient> over it, with a glass of <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> or the <ingredient>juice of a Seville orange,</ingredient> and throw <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> all over the pudding and dish.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a boiled Almond Pudding.</purpose>



--Beat a pound of <ingredient>sweet almonds</ingredient> as small as possible, with three spoonfuls of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> and a gill of <ingredient>sack</ingredient> or <ingredient>white wine;</ingredient> mix in half a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> melted, with five <ingredient>yolks of eggs,</ingredient> and two <ingredient>whites,</ingredient> a quart of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated, <pb n="174" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=180"/> one spoonful of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and three spoonfuls of crumbs of <ingredient>white bread;</ingredient> mix all well together, and boil it. It will take half an hour boiling.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a Prune or Damson Pudding.</purpose>



--Take a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> beat six <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and half the <ingredient>whites,</ingredient> with half a pint of the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and four spoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and two spoonfuls of beaten <ingredient>ginger;</ingredient> then by degrees mix in all the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and a pound of <ingredient>prunes.</ingredient> Tie it in a cloth, boil it an hour, melt <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and pour over it. <ingredient>Damsons</ingredient> eat well this way.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make an Apple Pudding.</purpose>



--Make a good <ingredient>puff paste,</ingredient> roll it out half an inch thick; pare and core <pb n="175" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=181"/><ingredient>apples</ingredient> enough to fill the crust, and close it up. Tie it in a cloth, and boil it; (if a small pudding two hours; if a large one, three or four hours.) When it is enough, turn it into a dish; cut a piece of crust out of the top, <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> it to the palate; lay on the crust again, and send it to table hot.</p><p><variation>N.B. A 



<purpose><alt synonym1="pear pudding, damson pudding, plum pudding, apricot pudding, cherry pudding, mulberry pudding">pear pudding, and a damson pudding, or any sort of plum, apricots, cherries, or mulberries,</alt></purpose>



may be made the same way.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a plain Baked Pudding.</purpose>



--Boil a quart of <ingredient>milk;</ingredient> then stir in <ingredient>flour</ingredient> till thick; add half a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> six ounces of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated, a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> ten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> but not <pb n="176" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=182"/> all the whites. Mix them well, put it into a dish buttered, and it will be baked in three quarters of an hour.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a baked Bread Pudding.</purpose>



--Take a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> set it on the fire, and keep it stirring; when the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is melted, put in as much grated <ingredient>stale bread</ingredient> as will make it pretty light, a <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> a sufficient quantity of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> three or four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Mix all together, butter a dish, put it in, and bake it half an hour.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a Rice Pudding.</purpose>



--Beat half a pound of <ingredient>rice</ingredient> to powder. Set it with three pints of <ingredient>new milk</ingredient> upon <pb n="177" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=183"/> the fire, let it boil well, and when it grows almost cold, put to it eight <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beaten, and half a pound of <ingredient>suet</ingredient> or <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and a sufficient quantity of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace.</ingredient> Half an hour will bake it.</p><p>You may add a few <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> <ingredient>candied lemon,</ingredient> <ingredient>citron-peel,</ingredient> or other <ingredient>sweetmeats;</ingredient> and lay a <ingredient>puff-paste</ingredient> first all over the sides and rim of the dish.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a Baked Apple Pudding.</purpose>



--Scald three or four <ingredient>codlins,</ingredient> and bruise them through a sieve. Add a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>biscuit,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and ten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> but only half the <ingredient>whites.</ingredient> Sweeten to your taste, and bake it.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a Norfolk Dumpling.</purpose>



--Make a batter as for pancakes, with a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and as much <ingredient>flour</ingredient> as is needful. Drop this batter in pieces, into a pan of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> And if the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils fast, they will be sufficiently done in three minutes. Throw them into a sieve or <implement>cullender</implement> to drain. Then lay them in a dish. Stir a slice of fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into each, and heat them hot.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a Hard Dumpling.</purpose>



--Mix <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> like a paste. Roll it into balls, as big as a turkey's egg. Have a pan of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> ready. Throw the balls of paste into the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> having first <pb n="179" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=185"/> rolled them in <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> They eat best boiled in a beef pot; and a few <ingredient>currants</ingredient> added make a pretty change. Eat them with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> as above.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Apple Dumplings.</purpose>



--Pare and core as many <ingredient><alt synonym1="codlins">codlings</alt></ingredient> as you intend to make dumplings. Make a little <ingredient>cold butter paste.</ingredient> Roll it to the thickness of one's finger, and wrap it round every <ingredient>apple</ingredient> singly; and if they be bound singly in pieces of cloth, so much the better. Put them into <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and they will be done in half an hour. Serve them up with <ingredient>melted butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>white wine;</ingredient> and garnish with grated <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> about the dish.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a fine Cream.</purpose>



--Take a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> sweeten to your palate; grate in a little <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> add a spoonful of <ingredient>orange-flower water,</ingredient> or <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> and two spoonfuls of <ingredient>sack;</ingredient> beat up four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and two <ingredient>whites,</ingredient> stir it all together over the fire, till it is thick; have cups ready, and pour it in.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Lemon Cream.</purpose>



--Take the <ingredient>juice of four large lemons,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> a pound of <ingredient>double refined sugar</ingredient> beaten fine, the <ingredient>whites of seven eggs,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>yolk</ingredient> of one beaten very well; mix all together, strain it, set it on a gentle fire, stirring it all the while, and skim it clean; put into it the <ingredient>peel of one lemon</ingredient> when <pb n="181" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=187"/> it is very hot, but not to boil; take out the <ingredient>lemon-peel,</ingredient> and pour it into china dishes.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Raspberry Cream.</purpose>



--Take a quart of <ingredient>thick sweet cream,</ingredient> and boil it two or three wallops; then put it off the fire, and strain the <ingredient>juice of raspberries</ingredient> into it to your taste; stir it a good while before you put your juice in, that it may be almost cold when you mix it, and afterwards stir it one way for almost a quarter of an hour; then sweeten it to your taste, and when cold you may send it up.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Whipt Cream.</purpose>



--Take a quart of <ingredient>thick cream,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>whites <pb n="182" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=188"/> of eight eggs</ingredient> beaten with half a pint of <ingredient>sack;</ingredient> mix it together, and sweeten to your taste with <ingredient>double refined sugar;</ingredient> you may perfume it (if you please) with <ingredient>musk</ingredient> or <ingredient>ambergris</ingredient> tied in a rag, and steeped a little in the <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Whip it up with a <implement>whisk</implement> that has a bit of <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> tied in the middle. Take off the froth with a spoon, and lay it in your glasses or basons.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make a Trifle.</purpose>



--Cover the bottom of a dish or bowl with <ingredient>Naples biscuits</ingredient> broke in pieces, <ingredient>macaroons</ingredient> in halves and <ingredient>ratifia cakes.</ingredient> Just wet them through with <ingredient>sack;</ingredient> then make a good <ingredient>boiled custard</ingredient> not too thick, and when cold pour it over, then put <pb n="183" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=189"/> a <ingredient>syllabub</ingredient> over that.--You may garnish with <ingredient>ratifia</ingredient> cakes, <ingredient>currant jelly,</ingredient> and <ingredient>flowers.</ingredient></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Calf's Feet Jelly.</purpose>



--Cut four <ingredient>calf's feet</ingredient> in pieces, put them into a <implement>pipkin,</implement> with a gallon of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> cover them close, and boil them softly till almost half be consumed, then run the liquor through a sieve, and let it stand till it be cold. With a knife take off the fat, at top and bottom, melt the fine part of the jelly in a <implement>preserving-pan</implement> or skillet, and put in a pint of <ingredient>Rhenish wine,</ingredient> the <ingredient>juice of four or five lemons,</ingredient> <ingredient>double refined sugar</ingredient> to your taste, the <ingredient>whites of eight eggs</ingredient> beaten to a froth; stir and boil all these together near half an hour; <pb n="184" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=190"/> then pass it through a sieve into a <implement>jelly-bag;</implement> put into your <implement>jelly-bag</implement> a very small sprig of <ingredient>rosemary,</ingredient> and a piece of <ingredient>lemon-peel;</ingredient> pass it through the bag till it is as clear as water.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Boiled Custards.</purpose>



--Put into a pint of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> blanched and beaten very fine, with <ingredient>rose or orange flower-water,</ingredient> or a little <ingredient>mace;</ingredient> let them boil till the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is a little thickened, then sweeten it, and stir in the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and keep it stirring over the fire till it is as thick as you would have it; then put to it a little <ingredient>orange-flower water,</ingredient> stir it well together, and put it into china cups.</p><p><variation>N.B. You may make them without almonds.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Rice Custards.</purpose>



--Boil a quart of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> with a blade of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> and a quartered <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> put thereto <ingredient>boiled rice,</ingredient> well beat with the <ingredient>cream;</ingredient> mix these together, stirring them all the while they boil. When enough, take it off, and sweeten it to your taste; put in a little <ingredient>orange-flower water</ingredient> or <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> then pour it into dishes. When cold, serve it up.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To preserve Apricots.</purpose>



--Pare your <ingredient>apricots,</ingredient> divide them in halves to take out the stones, and give them a light boiling in a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> or according to your quantity of fruit; then add to the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> after taking out the fruit, the weight of your <ingredient>apricots</ingredient> in <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and boil it till it comes to a <pb n="186" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hote&#38;PageNum=192"/> syrup; put in the <ingredient>apricots</ingredient> again, and give them a light boiling, taking off the scum as it rises. When the syrup jellies, it is enough; then take up the <ingredient>apricots,</ingredient> and cover them with the jelly; put cut paper over them, and lay them down when cold.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>



<purpose rend="italic">To make Marmalade.</purpose>



To two pounds of <ingredient>quinces,</ingredient> add three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and a pint of <ingredient>spring water;</ingredient> put them over the fire, and boil them till they are tender; drain off the liquor, and bruise them; then put them into it again, let it boil three quarters of an hour, and put it into your pots or saucers.</p></recipe>



