<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">36.--A MOST DELICIOUS SALAD SAUCE, BY J.R.W.</purpose>



Take the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> of four <ingredient>hard-boiled eggs,</ingredient> rub them through a sieve, and add to them one teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> mix well up, then add two tablespoonsful of <ingredient>made mustard,</ingredient> stir well up, then add by one spoonful at each time, six spoonfuls of <ingredient>salad oil;</ingredient> mix this well together until it becomes as smooth as <ingredient>mustard,</ingredient> then put in one teaspoonful of <ingredient>anchovy sauce,</ingredient> and one gill of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> or <ingredient>new milk,</ingredient> and stir well together; and last of all put in by degrees some good <ingredient>vinegar;</ingredient> I don't state the quantity of this, as some is much stronger than others, this must lay in your own taste. Should you make it too sharp with <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> add one tablespoonful of fine <ingredient>white sugar</ingredient> in powder, this will soften it, and give it an excellent flavour. Bottle it for use. This will keep for any length of time, in the hottest weather; and is excellent with any kind of salad or boiled slaw, and is a fine relish with <ingredient>fish.</ingredient> Shake it well up before you put it on your salad.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">40.--TO MAKE LIQUID CURRANT JAM, OF THE FIRST QUALITY.</purpose>



Take four pounds of clean picked <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> put aside two and a half pounds of them, and squeeze the remainder; then put this in a <implement>preserving pan,</implement> with four pounds of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> when come to a <ingredient>syrup,</ingredient> put in the remainder of the whole <ingredient>currants</ingredient> along with the one and a half pounds of <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> and boil it to the greatest perfection.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">42.--HOW TO MAKE ALL KINDS OF SYRUPS, WITH ALL SORTS OF FLOWERS.</purpose>



Heat in a pan half a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> then put into it <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to the quantity of flowers; boil, skim, and thicken it to a proper consistency; when done, put it into a glazed pot or pan and cover it over with a linen cloth, through which pour the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient>



 



<pb n="98" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hous&#38;PageNum=104"/>



upon the flowers; these being deadened, put altogether again into the same piece of linen, and squeeze them; strain it into another vessel, then bottle and cork it close; the quantity of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> requisite for this <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> is generally one pound and a half to every four ounces of flowers. Observe that all kinds of flowers must be picked and cleaned of their cups and stems, and nothing but their leaves made use of.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">44.--A MOST DELICIOUS LEMONADE, TO BE MADE THE DAY BEFORE WANTED.</purpose>



Take and pare two dozen of good sized <ingredient>lemons</ingredient> as thin as you possibly can; put eight of the <ingredient>rinds</ingredient>



 



<pb n="99" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hous&#38;PageNum=105"/>



into three quarts of <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> but not boiling, cover it close over for four hours, then rub some <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to the <ingredient>rinds</ingredient> to attract the essence, and put it into a bowl, and into which squeeze the <ingredient>juice of the lemons;</ingredient> to which add one pound and a half of fine <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> then put the <ingredient>water</ingredient> to the above, and three quarts of <ingredient>boiling milk,</ingredient> mix and run through a <implement>jelly bag</implement> until clear; bottle it, if you choose, and cork close; this will be most excellent, and will keep.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">52.--TO CORRECT A BAD TASTE OR SOURNESS IN WINE.</purpose>



Put into a clean linen bag one or two roots of wild <ingredient>horseradish</ingredient> cut in fine pieces, let it hang down through the bung hole into the <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> by a piece of twine, let it stay there for two days, then take that out, and put in another in the same manner, and repeat until the <ingredient>wine</ingredient> is perfectly restored.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">55.--TO MAKE RASPBERRY, STRAWBERRY, CHERRY, AND ALL KINDS OF WATERS.</purpose>



Take any quantity of the ripest <ingredient>raspberries,</ingredient> squeeze them through a linen cloth, to extract the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> from them, put this in a glass bottle uncorked



 



<pb n="103" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=hous&#38;PageNum=109"/>



placed in the sun or on a stove until it is cleared down, then pour it gently into another bottle without disturbing the sediment, to half a pint of this put one quart of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to your taste, pour it from one vessel to the other, strain it, and put it in ice to cool, this will be a most delicious cool drink in hot weather, and extremely safe in perspirations.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">59.--A COOLING CINNAMON WATER IN HOT WEATHER.</purpose>



Boil one gallon of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> pour it into a gallon <implement>demijohn,</implement> set this before the fire, then put into it twelve <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> two ounces of whole <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> then stop up your bottle and put it in a cool place; when you want to mix your liquor, put half a pint into two quarts of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with one quarter of a pound of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> cool it in ice before you serve it, and it is a most wholesome and delicious drink as you can take in hot weather.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">61.--A STRONG ANISE-SEED WATER.</purpose>



Take half a pint of the best essential <ingredient>spirits of anise seeds,</ingredient> put this into three quarts of the best <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> with one quart of <ingredient>boiled water;</ingredient> if not sweet enough, add some <ingredient>clarified sugar,</ingredient> and strain through a <implement>jelly bag,</implement> this is a most delicious and wholesome <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and a fine stomachic.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">77.--TO MAKE THE BEST GINGER BEER.</purpose>



Take one ounce of <ingredient>powdered ginger,</ingredient> half an ounce of <ingredient>cream tartar,</ingredient> one large <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> cut in slices, two pounds of <ingredient>loaf-sugar,</ingredient> and one gallon of <ingredient>soft water,</ingredient> let them be well mixed together, let them simmer over the fire for half an hour, then put in one table-spoonful of <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> and let it stand to ferment, and when done, bottle it and tie the corks with twine, put it in a cool place, and it will be fit for use in five or six days. This is delicious in hot weather.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



<recipe class1="medhealth">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">89.--TO CURE THOSE THAT ARE GIVEN TO DRINK.</purpose>



Put, in a sufficient quantity of <ingredient>rum,</ingredient> <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> <ingredient>gin,</ingredient> or whatever liquor the person is in the habit of drinking, three large live <ingredient>eels,</ingredient> which leave until quite dead, give this liquor unawares to those you wish to reform, and they will get so disgusted against it, that, though they formerly liked it, they will now have quite an aversion to it afterwards; this I have seen tried and have the good effect on the person who drank it.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">97.--TO REFINE CIDER, FOR ONE BARREL.</purpose>



Take one pint of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> four ounces of rock <ingredient>alum,</ingredient> the <ingredient>whites of six eggs,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>coarse sand,</ingredient> and two pounds of <ingredient>coarse sugar.</ingredient></p>



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose align="center" placement="heading">100.--EXCELLENT JUMBLE BEER.</purpose>



Take four table-spoonsful of ground <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> one quart of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> ten gallons of <ingredient>water.</ingredient> N.B. First mix the ingredients in a little <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> then add the whole complement of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and shake it briskly, and in eight hours it will be sufficiently fermented, and is a wholesome and pleasant <ingredient>beer.</ingredient></p>



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



