<recipe class1="soups" occasion="spring">



<p><purpose>SPRING SOUP.</purpose>--Unless your dinner hour is very late, the <ingredient>stock</ingredient> for this soup should be made the day before it is wanted, and set away in a stone pan, closely covered. To make the <ingredient>stock,</ingredient> take a <ingredient>knuckle of veal,</ingredient> break the <ingredient>bones,</ingredient> and cut it into several pieces. Allow a quart of <ingredient>water</ingredient> to each pound of <ingredient>veal.</ingredient> Put it into a <implement>soup-pot,</implement> with a set of <ingredient>calves-feet,</ingredient> and some bits of <ingredient>cold ham,</ingredient> cut off near the hock. If you have no <ingredient>ham,</ingredient> sprinkle in a table-spoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and a salt-spoon of <ingredient>cayenne.</ingredient> Place the pot over a <emph rend="italic">moderate</emph> fire, and let it simmer slowly (skimming it well) for several hours, till the <ingredient>veal</ingredient> is all to rags and the flesh of the <ingredient>calves-feet</ingredient> has dropped in, shreds from the <ingredient>bones.</ingredient> Then strain the soup; and if not wanted that day, set it away in a stone pan, as above mentioned.</p>



<p>Next day have ready-boiled two quarts or more of <ingredient>green peas,</ingredient> (they must on no account be old,) and a pint of the green tops cut off from <ingredient>asparagus</ingredient> boiled for the purpose. Pound a handful of raw <ingredient>spinach</ingredient> till you have extracted a teacup-full of the juice. Set the soup or <ingredient>stock</ingredient> over the fire; add the <ingredient>peas,</ingredient> <ingredient>asparagus,</ingredient> and <ingredient>spinach-juice,</ingredient> stirring them well in; also a quarter of a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> divided into four bits, and rolled in <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Let the whole come to a boil; and then take it off and transfer it to a <implement>tureen.</implement> It will be found excellent.</p>



 



<pb n="8" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=lady&#38;PageNum=14"/>







<p>In boiling the <ingredient>peas</ingredient> for this soup, you may put with them half a dozen sprigs of <ingredient>green mint,</ingredient> to be afterwards taken out.</p>



<p>Late in the spring you may add to the other vegetables two <ingredient>cucumbers,</ingredient> pared and sliced, and the whitest part or <ingredient>heart of a lettuce,</ingredient> boiled together; then well-drained, and put into the soup with the <ingredient>peas</ingredient> and <ingredient>asparagus.</ingredient> It must be very thick with vegetables.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="soups" occasion="summer">



</recipe><recipe class1="soups" occasion="fall">



</recipe><recipe class1="soups" occasion="winter">



</recipe><recipe class1="soups">



</recipe><recipe class1="soups">



</recipe><recipe class1="soups">



</recipe><recipe class1="soups">



</recipe><recipe class1="soups">



</recipe><recipe class1="soups">



</recipe><recipe class1="soups" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="soups">



</recipe><recipe class1="soups">



</recipe><recipe class1="soups">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



<recipe class1="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="french">



<p><purpose>FRESH SALMON STEWED.</purpose>--Having cleaned and washed the <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> cut it into round slices or fillets, rather more than an inch in thickness. Lay them in a large dish; sprinkling a very little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> evenly over the slices; and in half an hour turn them on the other side. Let them rest another half hour; then wash, drain, and wipe them dry with a clean towel. Spread some of the best fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> thickly over the strainer of a large <implement>fish-kettle;</implement> and lay the pieces of <ingredient>salmon</ingredient> upon it. Cover them nearly all over with very thin slices of fresh <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> from which the seeds have been removed. Intersperse among the <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> a few slices of <ingredient>shalots,</ingredient> or very small mild <ingredient>onions;</ingredient> a few sprigs of <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> and some <ingredient>whole pepper-corns.</ingredient> Set the kettle over a large bed of live coals; and spread very hot ashes thickly over the lid; which must be previously well-heated on the <emph rend="italic">inside</emph> by standing it up before the fire. The heat should be regularly kept up, while the <ingredient>fish</ingredient> is stewing, both above and below it. It will require an hour to cook thoroughly. When dishing it, remove the sliced <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> shalots, <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> &#38;c., leaving them in the bottom of the kettle. Put a cover over the <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> and set the dish that contains it over a large vessel of <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> while you are preparing the <ingredient>sauce.</ingredient> For this <ingredient>sauce,</ingredient> mix thoroughly a quarter of a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> with a table-spoonful of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Put it into a quart tin vessel with a lid, and add a table-spoonful of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>seasoning</ingredient> that was left in the bottom of the <implement>fish-kettle.</implement> Cover the vessel closely, and set it in a larger sauce-pan or pot of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Shake it about over the fire till it comes to a boil. If you <emph rend="italic">set it down</emph> on hot coals the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> will oil. When it has boiled, remove the 



 



<pb n="20" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=lady&#38;PageNum=26"/>







<ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> &#38;c.; pour the <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> into a <implement>sauce-boat,</implement> and send it to table with the stewed <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> garnished with sprigs of curled <ingredient>parsley.</ingredient></p>



<p>This is a French mode of cooking <ingredient>salmon.</ingredient> <variation><purpose><alt synonym1="fresh cod stewed" synonym2="fresh halibut stewed">Fresh cod, or halibut,</alt></purpose> may be stewed in the same manner.</variation></p>



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose>AN EXCELLENT WAY OF BOILING CABBAGE.</purpose>--Having trimmed the <ingredient>cabbage,</ingredient> and washed it well in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> (examining the leaves to see that no insects are lurking among them,) cut it almost into quarters, but do not divide it entirely down at the stem, which should be cut off just below the termination of the leaves. Let it lie an hour in a pan of <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Have ready a pot <emph rend="italic">full</emph> of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> seasoned with a small tea-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Put the <ingredient>cabbage</ingredient> into it, and let it boil for an hour and a half, skimming it occasionally. Then take it out; put it into a <implement>cullender</implement> to drain, and when all the <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> has drained off, set it under the <implement>hydrant.</implement> Let the <implement>hydrant</implement> run on it, till the <ingredient>cabbage</ingredient> has become perfectly cold all through. If you have no <implement>hydrant,</implement> set it under a pump, or keep pouring <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> on it from a pitcher. Then, having thrown out all the first <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and washed the pot, fill it again, and let the second <ingredient>water</ingredient> boil. During this time the <ingredient>cabbage</ingredient> under the <implement>hydrant</implement> will be growing cold. Then put it on again in the second <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and boil it two hours, or two and a half. Even the thickest part of the stalk must be perfectly tender all through. When thoroughly done, take up the <ingredient>cabbage,</ingredient> drain it well through the <implement>cullender,</implement> pressing it down with a broad ladle to squeeze out all the moisture; lay it in a deep dish, and cut it <emph rend="italic">entirely</emph> apart, dividing it into quarters. Lay some bits of fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> among the leaves, add a little <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> cover the dish, and send it to table hot.</p>



<p>This receipt for boiling <ingredient>cabbage</ingredient> was obtained from a physician, and on trial has been found very superior to any other. <ingredient>Cabbage</ingredient> cooked in this manner loses its unpleasant 



 



<pb n="39" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=lady&#38;PageNum=45"/>







pleasant odour, and its unwholesome properties, and may be eaten without apprehension, except by persons decidedly dyspeptic. The usual cabbage-smell will not be perceptible in the house--either while the <ingredient>cabbage</ingredient> is boiling or afterwards.</p>



<p>If you like it boiled with <ingredient>corned pork</ingredient> or <ingredient>bacon,</ingredient> the <emph rend="italic">second boiling</emph> (after the <ingredient>cabbage</ingredient> has been made cold under the <implement>hydrant</implement>) may be in the pot with the <ingredient>meat</ingredient>--skimming it well.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans" class2="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose>TO IMPROVE OLD POTATOES.</purpose>--In the spring when the <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> of the preceding autumn have become old, and deteriorated in quality, they will be greatly improved if, previous to boiling, a piece about the size of a shilling or a twelve-cent-piece, is cut off from each end; like "topping and tailing" them. Afterwards boil these <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> with the skins on, and see that they are thoroughly done. <emph rend="italic">Old</emph> <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> require very long boiling, and are unfit to eat if hard in the centre, being then extremely indigestible. Their specks and blemishes make them so unsightly when sent to table whole, that it is best when sufficiently boiled, to peel and mash them. Mash them with <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> if you cannot obtain good fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Salt butter will spoil their flavour instead of improving it, and all bad <ingredient>butter</ingredient> (whether salt or fresh) is unwholesome, as well as unpalatable, and should never be used for any purpose.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="italian">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy" ethnicgroup="french">



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose>STEWED LAMB.</purpose>--Take a fine quarter of <ingredient>lamb,</ingredient> and for a large dish, cut the whole of it into steaks; for a small dish, cut up the <ingredient>loin</ingredient> only; or slice only the <ingredient>leg.</ingredient> Remove the skin, and all the fat. Place at the bottom of a large stew-pot a fresh <ingredient>lettuce</ingredient> split into long quarters. Having seasoned the <ingredient>steaks</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>cayenne,</ingredient> and some powdered <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> lay them upon the <ingredient>lettuce,</ingredient> pour on just sufficient <ingredient>water</ingredient> to cover the whole, and let it stew gently for an hour, skimming it occasionally. Then put in a quart or two of young <ingredient>green peas,</ingredient> (in proportion to the quantity of <ingredient>meat,</ingredient>) a sprig of fresh <ingredient>green mint,</ingredient> a lump of <ingredient>loaf-sugar,</ingredient> and some bits of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Let it cook slowly about half an hour longer, or till the <ingredient>peas</ingredient> are all soft and well-done. In sending it to table, place the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> upon the <ingredient>lettuce,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>peas</ingredient> round it.</p>



<p><variation>Cold <purpose><alt synonym1="stewed ham">ham</alt></purpose> sliced, and stewed in this manner, will be found excellent. The <ingredient>ham</ingredient> having been already cooked, half an hour will be sufficient to stew it with the <ingredient>lettuce,</ingredient> and another half-hour after the <ingredient>peas</ingredient> are in.</variation></p>



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose>STEWED MUTTON CUTLETS.</purpose>--Having removed all the fat and the bone, beat the cutlets to make them tender, and season them with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient> Put them into a circular tin kettle, with some bits of fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> that have been rolled in <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Set the kettle (closely covered) upon a <implement>trivet</implement> inside of a flat-bottomed pot or <implement>stew-pan.</implement> Pour <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> all round, but not so as to come up to the top of the inner kettle. Set the pot over a slow fire, and let the stew simmer for two hours. Then lift up the <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> and put under it a <ingredient>lettuce</ingredient> cut in four; and three <ingredient>cucumbers,</ingredient> pared, split, and quartered; two <ingredient>onions</ingredient> sliced; and four young <ingredient>turnips</ingredient> cut small. Add a few blades of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> a salt-spoon of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and a little more <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Set it again in <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> taking care that the <ingredient>water</ingredient> does not reach the top of the inner kettle, the lid of which must be kept very tight. Let it boil slowly, or rather simmer, two hours longer. Then dish it, placing the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> upon the vegetables, and laying all round a ridge of <ingredient>green peas</ingredient> that have been boiled in the usual way.</p>



<p>The <ingredient>bone</ingredient> (nicely trimmed and scraped) may be left in each <ingredient>cutlet;</ingredient> in which case, when dishing them, stand them up in a circle, with the ends of the <ingredient>bones</ingredient> leaning against each other at the top, somewhat as we see poles placed in circles for lima-bean vines.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame" class2="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose>TO STEW SMOKED BEEF.</purpose>--The <ingredient>dried beef,</ingredient> for this purpose, must be fresh and of the very best quality. Cut it (or rather shave it) into very thin, small slices, with as little fat as possible. Put the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> into a skillet, and fill up with <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Cover it, and let it soak or steep till the <ingredient>water</ingredient> is cold. Then drain off that <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and pour on some more, but merely enough to cover the chipped <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> which you may season with a little <ingredient>pepper.</ingredient> Set it over the fire, and (keeping on the cover) let it stew for a quarter of an hour. Then roll a few bits of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in a little <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and add it to the <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> with the <ingredient>yolk of one or two beaten eggs.</ingredient> Let it stew five minutes longer. Take it up on a hot dish, and send it to the breakfast or tea-table.</p>



<p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="to stew cold ham">Cold ham</alt></purpose> may be sliced thin, and stewed in the same manner.</variation> <variation><purpose><alt synonym1="to stew dried venison">Dried venison</alt></purpose> also.</variation></p>



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame" occasion="fall">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="italian">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose>CHICKENS STEWED WHOLE.</purpose>--Having trussed a pair of fine fat young <ingredient>fowls</ingredient> or <ingredient>chickens,</ingredient> (with the <ingredient>liver</ingredient> under one wing, and the <ingredient>gizzard</ingredient> under the other,) fill the inside with large <ingredient>oysters,</ingredient> secured from falling out, by fastening tape round the bodies of the <ingredient>fowls.</ingredient> Put them into a tin <implement>butter-kettle</implement> with a close cover. Set the kettle into a larger pot or sauce-pan of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> (which must not reach quite to the top of the kettle,) and place it over the fire. Keep it boiling till the <ingredient>fowls</ingredient> are well done, which they should be in about an hour after they begin to simmer. Occasionally take off the lid to remove the scum; and be sure to put it on again closely. As the <ingredient>water</ingredient> in the outside pot boils away, replenish it with more <ingredient><emph rend="italic">hot</emph> water</ingredient> from a tea-kettle that is kept boiling hard. When the <ingredient>fowls</ingredient> are stewed quite tender, remove them from the fire; take from them all the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> that is about them, and put it into a small sauce-pan, covering closely the kettle in which they were stewed, and leaving the <ingredient>fowls</ingredient> in it to keep warm. Then add to the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> two table-spoonfuls of chopped <ingredient>oysters;</ingredient> the <ingredient>yolks of three hard-boiled eggs</ingredient> minced fine; half a grated <ingredient>nutmeg;</ingredient> four blades of <ingredient>mace;</ingredient> and a small  tea-cup of <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Boil this <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> about five minutes. Put the <ingredient>fowls</ingredient> on a dish, and send them to table, accompanied by the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> in a <implement>sauce-boat.</implement> This is an excellent way of cooking <ingredient>chickens.</ingredient></p>



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="french" occasion="Christmas">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">



</recipe><recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy" occasion="patriotic">



<p><purpose>COLUMBIAN PUDDING.</purpose>--Tie up closely in a bit of very thin white muslin, a <ingredient>vanilla bean</ingredient> cut into pieces; and a broken-up stick of <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient> Put this bag with its contents into half a pint of <ingredient>rich milk,</ingredient> and boil it a long time till very highly flavoured. Then take out the bag; set the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> near the fire to keep warm in the pan in which it was boiled, covering it closely. Slice thin a pound of <ingredient>almond sponge-cake,</ingredient> and lay it in a deep dish. Pour over it a quart of <ingredient>rich cream,</ingredient> with which you must mix the vanilla-flavoured <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and leave the cake to dissolve in it. Blanch, in scalding <ingredient>water,</ingredient> two ounces of shelled <ingredient>bitter almonds</ingredient> or <ingredient>peach-kernels;</ingredient> and pound them (one at a time) to a smooth paste in a <implement>marble mortar;</implement> pouring on each a few drops of <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> or <ingredient>peach-water</ingredient> to prevent their oiling. When the <ingredient>almonds</ingredient> are done, set them away in a cold place till wanted. Beat eight <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> till very light and thick; and having stirred together, hard, the dissolved cake and the <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> add them, gradually, to the mixture in turn with the <ingredient>almond,</ingredient> and half a pound of <ingredient>powdered loaf sugar,</ingredient> a little at a time of each. <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> a deep dish, and put in the mixture. Set the pudding into a brisk oven and bake it well. Have ready a star nicely cut out of a large piece of <ingredient>candied citron,</ingredient> a number of small stars all of equal size, as many as there are states in the Union: and a sufficiency of rays or long strips also cut out of <ingredient>citron.</ingredient> The rays should be wide at the bottom and run to a point at the top. As soon as the pudding comes out of the oven, while it is smoking, arrange these decorations. Put the large star in the centre, then the rays so that they will diverge from 



 



<pb n="108" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=lady&#38;PageNum=114"/>







it, widening off towards the edge of the pudding. Near the edge place the small stars in a circle.</p>



<p><variation><ingredient>Preserved citron-melon</ingredient> will be still better for this purpose than the dry <ingredient>candied citron.</ingredient></variation></p>



<p>This is a very fine pudding; suitable for a dinner party, or a Fourth of July dinner.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy" class2="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy" ethnicgroup="turkish">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



<p><purpose>AN ALMOND RICE PUDDING.</purpose>--Blanch, in <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> three ounces of shelled <ingredient>bitter almonds,</ingredient> afterwards throwing them into <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Pound them, one at a time, in a <implement>mortar,</implement> till they become a smooth paste; adding frequently, as you pound them, a few drops of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> to make them white and light, and to prevent their oiling. Take a quart of rich, unskimmed <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and stir into it, gradually, three large, heaping table-spoonfuls of ground <ingredient>rice flour,</ingredient> alternately with the pounded <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> and four heaping table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>powdered loaf-sugar.</ingredient> Set the mixture over the fire, and boil and stir it till very thick. Then put it into a deep dish, and set it away to cool. When cold, have ready the <ingredient>whites of two eggs</ingredient> beaten to a stiff froth, and thickened with <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> that has been melted in <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient> Cover with this the surface of the pudding. Set it in an oven just long enough to be slightly coloured of a light brown. Send it to table cold.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



<p><purpose>MARROW PUDDING.</purpose>--Grate a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>sponge-cake,</ingredient> and mix with it a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>beef-marrow,</ingredient> finely minced. Add the <ingredient>grated peel and the juice of a large lemon or orange;</ingredient> half a grated <ingredient>nutmeg;</ingredient> and four table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Stone half a pound of very good fresh <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> cut them in half, and dredge them well with <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Beat four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light, and stir them gradually into half a pint of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> or <ingredient>rich milk.</ingredient> Mix it, by degrees, with the other ingredients. Lastly add the <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> a few at a time; and stir the whole very hard. <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> a deep dish; put in the mixture; bake it an hour or more, and send it to table warm, with slips of <ingredient>candied citron</ingredient> stuck all over the top, so as to stand upright. For <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> have <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> mixed with <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon juice.</ingredient></p>



<p>This pudding may be boiled in a cloth. It will require three hours' boiling.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" ethnicgroup="german">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" ethnicgroup="italian">



<recipe class1="breadsweets" ethnicgroup="french">



<p><purpose>A FRENCH CHARLOTTE.</purpose>--Lay in a deep dish or pan half a pound of <ingredient>bitter almond maccaroons</ingredient> (<ingredient>chocolate maccaroons</ingredient> will be still better) and pour on sufficient <ingredient>white wine</ingredient> to cover them well, and let them stand till entirely dissolved. Whip to a stiff froth a pint of <ingredient>rich cream,</ingredient> sweetened with <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and flavoured with <ingredient>rose</ingredient> or <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient> Have ready a large circular <ingredient>almond sponge cake</ingredient> with the inside cut out, so as to leave the sides and bottom standing in the form of a mould, not quite an inch thick. Ornament the edge with a handsome border of <ingredient>icing.</ingredient> In the bottom of this mould put the dissolved maccaroons; over them a layer of thick <ingredient>jelly,</ingredient> made of some very nice <ingredient>fruit;</ingredient> and fill up with the <ingredient>whipped cream,</ingredient> heaping it high in the centre.</p>



<p>This is a very fine Charlotte, and is easily made, no cooking being required, after the materials are collected.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" ethnicgroup="spanish">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose>PEACH ICE-CREAM.</purpose>--Take fine soft <ingredient>free-stone peaches,</ingredient> perfectly ripe. Pare them, and remove the stones. Crack about half the stones, and extract the <ingredient>kernels,</ingredient> which must be blanched by putting them into a bowl, and pouring on <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> to loosen the skins. Then break them up, or pound them slightly; put them into a little sauce-pan, and boil the kernels in a small quantity of <ingredient>rich milk,</ingredient> till it is highly flavoured with them; keeping the sauce-pan covered. Strain out the kernels, and set the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> to cool. Cut up the <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> in a large, broad, shallow pan, or a flat dish, and chop them very small. Mix with the chopped <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> sufficient <ingredient>powdered loaf-sugar</ingredient> to make them very sweet, and then mash them to a smooth jam with a silver spoon. Measure the peach jam; and to each quart allow a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and a pint of rich unskimmed <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Mix the whole well together, and put it into the freezer; adding when the mixture is about half-frozen, the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> in which you boiled the kernels, and which will greatly improve the peach-flavour. When well frozen, turn out the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> and serve it in a glass bowl. If you wish to have it in a shape, transfer it to a mould, and give it a second freezing. Before you turn it out, wash the outside of the mould all over with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> or wrap a wet cloth round it. Then open it, and the ice-cream will come out easily.</p>



<p><variation><purpose>Apricot ice-cream</purpose> may be made as above.</variation></p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" occasion="summer">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose><alt synonym1="citron sweetmeats">AMERICAN CITRON.</alt></purpose>--Pare a sufficient number of <ingredient>citron-melons,</ingredient> and cut each <ingredient>melon</ingredient> into four thick quarters. Weigh them, and put them over-night into a <implement>tureen,</implement> or a large <implement>white-ware pan</implement> or basin. Prepare some very weak <ingredient>brine,</ingredient> allowing a table-spoonful of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to a quart of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> for every pound of <ingredient>citron.</ingredient> Pour the <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> over the <ingredient>citron;</ingredient> cover it, and let it stand all night to draw out the sliminess. Prepare some <ingredient>alum-water,</ingredient> allowing to each quart of <ingredient>water</ingredient> a bit of <ingredient>alum</ingredient> about the size of a grain of Indian corn. In the morning, drain the <ingredient>citron</ingredient> from the <ingredient>brine,</ingredient> and wash every piece separately in the <ingredient>alum-water,</ingredient> which will green and clear it. After it has lain half an hour in the <ingredient>alum-water,</ingredient> drain the <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> and put it into a porcelain <implement>preserving-kettle,</implement> allowing to every four pounds of the <ingredient>citron</ingredient> a large half pint of clear fresh <ingredient>water.</ingredient> There must be <ingredient>water</ingredient> enough to cover the <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> and keep it from burning. Add to every four pounds, the <ingredient>yellow rind of a large lemon,</ingredient> grated, or pared off very thin, and cut into shreds. Set the kettle over a clear fire, and boil it slowly, till the <ingredient>citron</ingredient> is tender enough to be easily pierced through with a large needle. If it seems to be boiling dry, add a little more <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> When all are quite tender, take out each piece separately with a fork. Spread them out on a large dish. Then strain and measure the liquid; and to each pint allow a pound of the best <ingredient>double-refined <emph rend="italic">loaf-sugar;</emph></ingredient> not the sugar that is sold ready-powdered, as that is so adulterated with ground starch, that it has little or no strength, and sweetmeats made with it are sure to spoil, unless four times the usual quantity is put in.</p>



 



<pb n="166" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=lady&#38;PageNum=172"/>







<p>Having broken up the <ingredient>loaf-sugar,</ingredient> add it to the liquid in the <implement>preserving-kettle,</implement> and let it boil (skimming it well) till it becomes a thick, rich, jelly-like syrup. It will most probably be boiled sufficiently in about half an hour. Next put in the pieces of <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> one at a time, and boil them ten minutes, or more, in the <ingredient>syrup,</ingredient> till it has thoroughly penetrated them. Afterwards take out the <ingredient>citron;</ingredient> spread it on a dish to cool; and transfer the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> to a large pitcher. When cold, put the <ingredient>citron</ingredient> into glass jars, and pour the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> over it. Cover the tops with white paper, dipped in brandy, and tie closely over each another covering of bladder, that has been previously soaked in <ingredient>water.</ingredient> The covers of lacquered tin, that belong to glass jars, seldom fit perfectly tight, and are not to be trusted without another covering over them.</p>



<p>This will be found a very fine sweetmeat. To dry it, in imitation of foreign <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> select some of the finest pieces; spread them on a dish; and set them for three days in the hot sun, turning each piece several times a-day. Then make a hole near the end of each piece; run a twine string through them, and hang them on lines, across an open, sunny window. When sufficiently dry, put them into tight jars, or boxes, and keep them to use, as <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> in cakes or mince-pies.</p>



<p><variation>Preserved <purpose><alt synonym1="candied citron">citron</alt></purpose> may be candied, (after it has lain five or six months in the <ingredient>syrup,</ingredient>) by taking out the pieces, spreading them on a dish, and boiling the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> again, till it is as thick as possible. It may require some additional <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Then pour it on the <ingredient>citron;</ingredient> and when it has grown cold, and has dried on the pieces, put them into a jar.</variation></p>



<p>When giving the <ingredient>citron</ingredient> its first boiling, in the <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> you may add, to every four pounds of <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> half an ounce of <ingredient>root-ginger,</ingredient> (if green and tender, it will be better,) or else a few pieces of <ingredient>preserved ginger.</ingredient></p>



 



<pb n="167" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=lady&#38;PageNum=173"/>







<p>To increase the lemon-flavour, rub off, upon some lumps of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> (before you make the <ingredient>syrup,</ingredient>) the <ingredient>yellow rind of two or three other lemons.</ingredient></p>



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose>EXCELLENT CURRANT-JELLY.</purpose>--The <ingredient>currants</ingredient> should be quite ripe, but not <emph rend="italic">over</emph>-ripe. Having picked them from the stems, put the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> into a large stone jar, or pitcher, and tie closely over the top a very thick paper, (for instance, <implement>sugar-loaf paper,</implement> or coarse brown.) Set the jar into a kettle of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> the <ingredient>water</ingredient> not quite reaching the top of the jar; and let the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> remain over a moderate fire an hour after they have begun to boil. Then pour them into a linen bag, and let the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> drip into a vessel beneath. Do not squeeze the bag, or the jelly will not be clear. When the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> has ceased to drip, measure it; and to each quart allow a pound of the best <ingredient>double-refined loaf-sugar,</ingredient> broken up. Crush the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> small, by rolling it on a clean <implement>paste-board,</implement> with a rolling-pin. Put the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> (<emph rend="italic">without the sugar</emph>) into a <implement>preserving-kettle,</implement> and let it just come to a boil. Then take it off; and, while it is very hot, immediately stir into it the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a handful at a time, using a wooden spoon to stir it with. If the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is of the best sort, it will require no skimming, and will have no sediment. Therefore, as nothing of it will be lost or wasted, it is more economical than <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> of inferior quality. Put the jelly immediately into <implement>tumblers,</implement> or white jars, and cover it at once; first, with double white tissue-paper, cut to fit exactly the inside of the top; and then with writing-paper, cut larger, so as to turn downward, round the outside of the top. Paste the paper firmly on, and set the jelly away in a dry, cool place. Notch the edge of the paper, with scissors.</p>



<p><variation><purpose>White currant-jelly</purpose> may be made as above. It will be a clear, bright, amber colour.</variation></p>



<p><variation><purpose>Raspberry, strawberry, grape, gooseberry, and cranberry-jelly,</purpose> can be made in this manner. For the <ingredient>gooseberry,</ingredient> allow a pound and a half of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to every pint of <ingredient>juice;</ingredient> for the <ingredient>cranberry,</ingredient> a pound and a half, also.</variation></p>



</recipe> 



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose>FINE BLACK CURRANT-JELLY.</purpose>--Make black currant-jelly according to the above receipt; except that when you have stemmed the <ingredient>black currants,</ingredient> and put them into the jar, to boil, you must add a little <ingredient>water;</ingredient> allowing a small half-pint of <ingredient>water</ingredient> to each quart of the stemmed <ingredient>currants.</ingredient> The <ingredient>juice of black currants</ingredient> is so very thick, that, if undiluted, the jelly would be tough and ropy.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans" ethnicgroup="french">



<p><purpose>BRANDY PEACHES THE FRENCH WAY.</purpose>--Put large <ingredient>white peaches</ingredient> (a few at a time) into scalding <ingredient>lye.</ingredient> Let them rest for a minute or two, till the skin loosens so that it can be easily peeled off. Next put the <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> into <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and let them remain till you have <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> ready to scald them. After scalding, put into a large, broad <implement>preserving kettle</implement> as many <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> as will lie side by side in the bottom. Pour on as much <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> as will rather more than cover them; set the kettle over a clear fire; and let them boil till they are soft enough to be easily dented when pressed by your finger. Take them out; place them with the stem end downward, on an <implement>inverted sieve</implement> set on a large dish. Then put some more <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> into the kettle; add more <ingredient>cold water;</ingredient> boil them; and put them to drain afterwards. Repeat this till all your <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> have had a boil. Spread them on large dishes, and let them stand all night in a cold place. Mix together some of the best <ingredient>white brandy</ingredient> and the best <ingredient>loaf-sugar,</ingredient> powdered fine,--allowing a pound of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to every pint of <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient> Stir it well while the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is dissolving; and when melted, set it also in a cold place, and let it stand all night. In the morning, put the <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> into glass jars, which should be all of the same size, and fill them up with the brandy syrup; allowing an equal portion to each jar. Cover the jars closely, and paste white paper over their tops.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose>INDIANA BATTER CAKES.</purpose>--Sift into a pan three large pints of <ingredient>yellow corn-meal;</ingredient> and add a large table-spoonful of fresh <ingredient>lard;</ingredient> or of nice <ingredient>drippings of roast beef,</ingredient> well cleared from fat. Add a small tea-spoonful of <ingredient>sal-eratus,</ingredient> or a large one of <ingredient>soda,</ingredient> dissolved in a little <ingredient>warm water.</ingredient> Next make the whole into a soft dough, with a pint of <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Afterwards thin it to the consistence of a moderate batter, by adding, gradually, not quite a pint and a half of <ingredient>warm water.</ingredient> When it is all mixed, continue to stir it well for half an hour. Have ready a griddle heated over the fire, and bake the batter in the manner of buckwheat-cakes; send them to table hot, and eat them with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> or <ingredient>molasses.</ingredient></p>



<p>These cakes are very light and good, and convenient to make; as they require neither eggs, milk, nor yeast. They may either be baked as soon as mixed, or they may stand for an hour or more.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose>LONG ROLLS.</purpose>--Sift three quarts of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into a large pan, and mix with it a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Warm half a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> but do not let it become hot. Mix with it six table-spoonfuls of strong, fresh <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient> Make a deep hole in the middle of the pan of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Pour in the liquid, and, with a spoon, work into it the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> round the edge of the hole; proceeding gradually till you have all the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> mixed in, so as to form a batter. Stir it well, for two or three minutes. Then strew the top all over with a handful of dry <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Cover the dough with a thick, double cloth, and set it in a warm place, to rise. When it is quite light, and the surface cracked all over, mix in three table-spoonfuls (not more) of <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> or fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Knead it long and hard, and make it into long, oval-shaped rolls, making, with a knife, a cleft in the top of each. Sprinkle some square <implement>baking-pans</implement> with <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> lay the rolls in them, at equal distances; cover them, as before; and set them in a warm place, for half an hour. In the meantime, have the oven ready; put in the rolls, and bake them brown.</p>



<p>Their lightness may be improved by mixing in (while kneading the dough, previous to forming it into cakes) a heaping tea-spoonful of <ingredient>soda,</ingredient> or <ingredient>sal-eratus,</ingredient> dissolved in as much <ingredient>warm water</ingredient> as will cover it.</p>



<p>In cold weather, you may mix these rolls with <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> instead of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> but in summer the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> may turn sour, and spoil the dough. This, however, may be corrected, by adding the <ingredient>soda,</ingredient> or <ingredient>sal-eratus;</ingredient> always a good remedy for sour dough or batter.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



<p><purpose>TO BEAT EGGS.</purpose>--In making cakes it is of the utmost importance that the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> should be properly and sufficiently beaten; otherwise the cakes will most certainly be deficient in the peculiar lightness characterizing those that are made by good confectioners. Home-made cakes, if good in other respects, are too frequently (even when not absolutely heavy or streaked) hard, solid and tough. This often proceeds from too large a portion of flour, and too small an allowance of butter and <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient> The richest cake that can be made (provided it is light and well baked) is less unwholesome than what are called plain cakes, if they are solid or leathery. Cakes cannot be crisp and light without a due proportion of the articles that are to make them so; and even then, the ingredients must be thoroughly stirred or beaten; and of course thoroughly baked afterwards.</p>



<p>Persons who do not know the right way, complain much of the fatigue of beating <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and therefore leave off too soon. There will be no fatigue, if they are beaten with the proper stroke, and with <emph rend="italic">wooden</emph> rods, and in a shallow, flat-bottomed <emph rend="italic">earthen</emph> pan. The coldness of a tin pan retards the lightness of the <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient> For the same reason do not use a metal <implement>egg-beater.</implement> In beating them do not move your elbow, but keep it close to your side. Move only your hand at the wrist, and let the stroke be quick, short, and horizontal; putting the <implement>egg-beater</implement> always down to the bottom of the pan, which should therefore be shallow. Do not leave off as soon as you have got the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> into a foam; they are then only <emph rend="italic">beginning</emph> to be light. But persist till after the foaming has ceased, 



 



<pb n="194" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=lady&#38;PageNum=200"/>







and the bubbles have all disappeared. Continue till the surface is smooth as a mirror, and the beaten <ingredient>egg</ingredient> as thick as a rich boiled custard; for till then it will not be really light. It is seldom necessary to beat the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> and <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> separately, if they are afterwards to be put together. The article will be quite as light, when cooked, if the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> and <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> are beaten together, and there will then be no danger of their going in streaks when baked. The justly-celebrated Mrs. Goodfellow, of Philadelphia, always taught her pupils to beat the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> and <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> together, even for sponge-cake; and lighter than hers no sponge-cake could possibly be.</p>



<p>When <ingredient>white of egg</ingredient> is to be used without any <ingredient>yolk,</ingredient> (as for lady-cake, maccaroons, meringues, icing, &#38;c.,) it should be beaten till it stands alone on the rods; not falling when held up.</p>



<p><implement>Hickory rods</implement> for egg-beating are to be had at the wooden-ware shops, or at the turner's. For stirring butter and sugar together, nothing is equal to a <implement>wooden spaddle.</implement> It should be about a foot long, and flattened at the end like that of a <implement>mush-stick,</implement> only broader. Spoons are very tedious and inconvenient either for beating <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> or stirring butter and sugar, and do not produce the proper lightness.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" ethnicgroup="austrian">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose>WEST INDIA COCOA-NUT CAKE.</purpose>--Cut up and peel some pieces of a very ripe <ingredient>cocoa-nut.</ingredient> Lay the pieces for awhile in <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Then take them out; wipe them very dry; and grate, very finely, as much as, when grated, will weigh half a pound. Powder half a pound of the best <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient> Beat eight <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> till very light, thick, and smooth. Then stir the grated <ingredient>cocoa-nut</ingredient> and the <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> alternately, into the pan of beaten <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> a little at a time of each; adding a handful of sifted <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a powdered <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and a glass of <ingredient>sweet wine.</ingredient> Stir the whole very hard. <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> a square tin pan. Put in the mixture, set it immediately into a quick oven, and bake it well; seeing that the heat is well kept up all the time. When cool, cut it into squares. Have ready a thick <ingredient>icing,</ingredient> made of <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>white of egg,</ingredient> flavoured with <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> or <ingredient>extract of roses.</ingredient> Ice each square of the cake, all over the top and sides.</p>



<p>You may bake it in a loaf, in a deep, circular pan. Ice the whole surface, and ornament it.</p>



<p>For a large cake, baked in a loaf, allow a pound of grated <ingredient>cocoa-nut;</ingredient> a pound of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> sixteen <ingredient>eggs;</ingredient> two handfuls of <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> two <ingredient>nutmegs,</ingredient> and two glasses of <ingredient>wine.</ingredient> It will require very long baking.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose>COCOA-NUT PUFFS.</purpose>--Break up a large ripe <ingredient>cocoa-nut.</ingredient> Pare the pieces, and lay them awhile in <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Then wipe them dry, and grate them as finely as possible. Lay the grated <ingredient>cocoa-nut</ingredient> in well-formed heaps on a large handsome dish. It will require no cooking. The heaps should be about the circumference of a dollar, and must not touch each other. Flatten them down in the middle, so as to make a hollow in the centre of each heap; and upon this pile some very nice <ingredient>sweetmeat.</ingredient> Make an excellent <ingredient>whipped cream,</ingredient> well sweetened and flavoured with <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> and <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> and beat it to a stiff froth. Pile some of this <ingredient>cream</ingredient> high upon each cake over the <ingredient>sweetmeats.</ingredient> If on a supper-table you may arrange them in circles round a glass stand.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose>NOTIONS.</purpose>--Put into a sauce-pan a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and two table-spoonfuls of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Set it over the fire, and when the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> begins to melt, stir it well through the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> As soon as it comes to a boil, begin to stir in a pint of sifted <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a little at a time; making the mixture very smooth, and pressing out all the lumps. Let it continue to boil five minutes after the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> is all in. Then pour it into a deep pan, and set it to cool. In another pan beat six <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light. When it is nearly cool, stir the beaten <ingredient>egg</ingredient> into the mixture, a little at a time; stirring the whole very hard, till it is as light as possible.</p>



<p>Have ready, over the fire, a pot with a pound or more of fresh <ingredient>lard</ingredient> melting in it. When the <ingredient>lard</ingredient> comes to a boil, take up portions of the batter in a large spoon, or a small ladle, and drop them into the boiling <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> so as to form separate balls. When they are well browned, take them out with a <implement>perforated skimmer,</implement> draining the <ingredient>lard</ingredient> from them back into the pot. Lay them on a flat dish, and when all are done, sift over them a mixture of <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> and powdered <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> or <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient> They should be eaten quite fresh.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" occasion="other">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" ethnicgroup="german">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets" ethnicgroup="german">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="medhealth">



<p><purpose>SEA-VOYAGE GINGERBREAD.</purpose>--Sift two pounds of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into a pan, and cut up in it a pound and a quarter of fresh <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> rub the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> well into the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and then mix in a pint of <ingredient>West India molasses</ingredient> and a pound of the best <ingredient>brown sugar.</ingredient> Beat eight <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> till very light. Stir into the beaten <ingredient>egg</ingredient> two glasses or a jill of <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient> Add also to the <ingredient>egg</ingredient> a teacup-full of ground <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> and a table-spoonful of powdered <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> with a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>soda</ingredient> melted in a little <ingredient>warm water.</ingredient> Wet the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> &#38;c., with this mixture till it becomes a soft dough. Sprinkle a little <ingredient>flour</ingredient> on your <implement>paste-board,</implement> and with a broad knife spread portions of the mixture thickly and smoothly upon it. The thickness must be equal all through; therefore spread it carefully and evenly, as the dough will be too soft to roll out. Then with the edge of a <implement>tumbler</implement> dipped in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> cut it out into round cakes. Have ready square pans, slightly buttered; lay the cakes in them sufficiently far apart to prevent their running into each other when baked. Set the pans into a brisk oven, and bake the cakes well, seeing that they do not burn.</p>



<p>You may cut them out small with the lid of a cannister (or something similar) the usual size of gingerbread nuts.</p>



<p>These cakes will keep during a long voyage, and are frequently carried to sea. Many persons find highly-spiced gingerbread a preventive to sea-sickness.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose>BREAD MUFFINS.</purpose>--Take some <ingredient>bread dough</ingredient> that has risen as light as possible, and knead into it some well-beaten <ingredient>egg</ingredient> in the proportion of two <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> to about a pound of dough. Then mix in a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>soda</ingredient> that has been dissolved in a very little <ingredient>lukewarm water.</ingredient> Let the dough stand in a warm place for a quarter of an hour. Then bake it in <implement>muffin-rings.</implement> You can thus, with very little trouble, have muffins for tea whenever you bake bread in the afternoon.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">



<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



<p><purpose>GOOSEBERRY CHAMPAGNE.</purpose>--Take large, fine <ingredient>gooseberries,</ingredient> that are full-grown, but not yet beginning to turn red; and pick off their tops and tails. Then weigh the <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> and allow a gallon of clear, <ingredient>soft water</ingredient> to every three pounds of <ingredient>gooseberries.</ingredient> Put them into a large, clean tub; pour on a little of the <ingredient>water;</ingredient> pound and mash them, thoroughly, with a <implement>wooden beetle;</implement> add the remainder of the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and give the whole a hard stirring. Cover the tub with a cloth, and let it stand four days; stirring it frequently and thoroughly, to the bottom. Then strain the liquid, through a coarse linen cloth, into another vessel; and to each gallon of liquid add four pounds of fine <ingredient>loaf-sugar;</ingredient> and to every five gallons a quart of the best and clearest <ingredient>French brandy.</ingredient> Mix the whole well together; and put it into a clean <implement>cask,</implement> that will just hold it, as it should be filled full. Place the <implement>cask</implement> on its side, in a cool, dry part of the cellar; and lay the bung loosely on the top. Secure the <implement>cask</implement> firmly in its place, so that it cannot, by any chance, be shaken or moved; as the least disturbance will injure the wine. Let it work for a fortnight, or more; till the fermentation is quite over, and the hissing has ceased. Then bottle it; driving in the corks tightly. Lay the bottles on their sides. In six months, it will be fit for drinking, and will be found as brisk as real champagne.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



<p><purpose>DOMESTIC TOKAY.</purpose>--Take fine <ingredient>grapes,</ingredient> that are all <emph rend="italic">perfectly</emph> ripe; pick them carefully from the stalks, omitting all that are blemished; put them into a large <implement>hair sieve,</implement> placed over a large, deep pan, or a clean tub. Mash the <ingredient>grapes,</ingredient> with your hand, squeezing and pressing out all the <ingredient>juice.</ingredient> To every quart of <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> allow a pound of <ingredient>sultana raisins,</ingredient> chopped small, or of <ingredient>bloom raisins,</ingredient> seeded and chopped. Let the <ingredient>grape-juice</ingredient> and <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> stand twelve days; stirring it twice or three times every day. Then strain the liquor into a <implement>cask;</implement> but do not stop it closely till after three days. Let it stand eight months; then bottle it. If it is not clear, take out a pint of the wine; mix with it half an ounce of <ingredient>isinglass,</ingredient> shaved fine, or an ounce of powdered <ingredient>gum-arabic.</ingredient> Set it in a warm place, and, when dissolved, add an ounce of fine <ingredient>chalk.</ingredient> This will be sufficient to fine a barrel of wine. Stir it lightly into the rest. Let it stand three or four days, and then bottle it.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments" class2="medhealth">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments" class2="medhealth" ethnicgroup="french">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" class2="medhealth">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" class2="medhealth">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose>COCOA.</purpose>--The <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> which is put up solid in close packages, and usually sold at a shilling a paper, is far superior to the chocolate that is manufactured into squares or cakes, and which is too frequently adulterated with lard and meal. <ingredient>Baker's prepared cocoa</ingredient> is excellent. When you intend having it for drinking, shave down, or cut fine a sufficient quantity of the <ingredient>cocoa;</ingredient> allowing about half the contents of a paper to a quart of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> if you wish it very strong, and three pints of <ingredient>water</ingredient> for moderate strength. Then put the <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> into a clean sauce-pan or a tin pot with a spout. Measure the <ingredient>water</ingredient> from a kettle that is boiling hard at the time; and when you have the proper quantity pour it scalding hot on the <ingredient>cocoa.</ingredient> Cover it closely; place it over the fire; and let it boil till it is all dissolved into the same consistence, and quite smooth, and free from the smallest lumps. While boiling, you must several times take off the lid, and with a spoon stir the <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> down to the bottom. Then transfer it to your <implement>chocolate pot,</implement> which must be twice scalded with <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Send it to table as hot as possible, adding <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to the cups when poured out. Eat with it dry toast; <emph rend="italic">unbuttered</emph> rolls; milk-biscuit; or sponge-cake.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



<p><purpose>TO KEEP CIDER SWEET.</purpose>--When barreling the <ingredient>cider,</ingredient> put into each barrel or keg a jill (eight large table-spoonfuls) of <ingredient>white mustard-seed.</ingredient> This will retard its becoming hard or sour.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose>TO KEEP APPLES.</purpose>--Wipe every <ingredient>apple</ingredient> dry with a cloth, and see that no blemished ones are left among them. Have ready a very dry tight barrel, and cover the bottom with <ingredient>dry pebbles.</ingredient> These will attract the damp of the <ingredient>apples.</ingredient> Then put in the <ingredient>fruit;</ingredient> head up the barrel; and plaster the seams with <implement>mortar,</implement> taking care to have a thick rim of <implement>mortar</implement> all round the top. Let the barrel remain undisturbed in the same place till you want the <ingredient>apples</ingredient> for use. <ingredient>Pippins, bell-flowers, or other apples of the best sorts,</ingredient> may be kept in this way till July.</p>



</recipe><recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments" occasion="winter">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p><purpose>BERGAMOT WATER.</purpose>--Melt a pound of the best broken-up <ingredient>loaf-sugar</ingredient> in a pint of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> add the <ingredient>yellow rind of six lemons or oranges,</ingredient> pared very thin. Set it over the fire, and boil and skim it till the scum ceases to rise. Then add the <ingredient>juice of the lemons or oranges;</ingredient> having squeezed it through a strainer into a bowl. After stirring in the <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> take the syrup from the fire, remove the pieces of <ingredient>rind,</ingredient> and stir in a tea-spoonful of genuine <ingredient>essence of bergamot.</ingredient> Bottle it, and it will be immediately 



 



<pb n="255" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=lady&#38;PageNum=261"/>







fit for drinking. Pour some of it into a glass, and add a little <ingredient>ice-water.</ingredient> It will be found very fine.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose>PUMPKIN MUSH.</purpose>--Pour into a clean pot, two quarts or more of good <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and set it over the fire. Have ready some <ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient> stewed very soft and dry; mashed smooth, and pressed in a <implement>cullender</implement> till all the liquid has drained off. Then measure a large pint of the stewed <ingredient>pumpkin;</ingredient> mix with it a piece of fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and a teaspoonful of ground <ingredient>ginger.</ingredient> Stir it gradually into the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> as soon as it has come to a boil. Add, by degrees, a large pint or more of <ingredient>indian-meal,</ingredient> a little at a time, stirring it in, very hard, with the <implement>mush-stick.</implement> If you find the mush too thin, as you proceed, add, in equal portions, more <ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient> and more <ingredient>indian-meal,</ingredient> till it becomes so thick you can scarcely stir it round. After it is all thoroughly mixed, and has boiled well, it will be greatly improved by diminishing the fire a little, or hanging the pot higher up, so as to let it simmer an hour or more. Mush can scarcely be cooked too much. Eat it warm with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> or with <ingredient>rich milk.</ingredient> It is very good at luncheon in cold weather.</p></recipe>



