<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p>The principal dish, from time immemorial, for the sovereigns of England at their Christmas dinner is the <purpose>"Royal Baron of Beef."</purpose>







In an English print I read that "it was this year (1854) cut from a fine <ingredient>Highland ox,</ingredient> fed by Prince Albert, and weighed eight hundred and forty pounds. It was put down before an enormous fire on Saturday afternoon, and for fourteen hours was watched and basted by relays of assistants under the head cook, after which it was trimmed and decorated, with the holly and mistletoe apparently sprouting from the outside fat of the meat."</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose>Broiling Steaks.</purpose>







--In the early part of the nineteenth century, when travelling by the stage-coaches was the fashion, Mr. Southmayd, my neighbor, says: "Travellers going to the eastern cities and towns--Boston, New Haven, etc.--and those who travelled much, were always anxious to<pb n="45" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=53"/>







reach New Haven, to enjoy a good broiled <ingredient rend="italic">beefsteak.</ingredient> A man, by the name of Butler, kept a public house in that town, in Chapel-street, and, about that time, was famous for his delicious steaks, which he always cooked or attended to himself. You would find him, with his white cap and apron on, before a heap of live hickory coals, in front of the great wide old-fashioned chimney, having a long handle attached to a large double (hinged) <implement>gridiron,</implement> and a <ingredient>fine steak</ingredient> fastened up in it, so that he could keep the steak turning, first on the one side then on the other, that not a drop of the <ingredient>fine gravy</ingredient> should drip off. When done, it was dished up, and placed steaming hot before the hungry travellers, who never failed to do ample justice to the efforts of the cook, who, by these means, built a reputation, as well as a fortune, by the knowledge of <emph rend="italic">broiling</emph> a beefsteak."</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p>The rules adopted by the celebrated "Beefsteak Club," organized in England, in 1734, were thus represented:</p>



<p>



<list><purpose align="center" size="smaller" placement="heading">"HOW TO COOK A BEEFSTEAK.</purpose>







<item align="indent2" size="smaller">"Pound well your <ingredient>meat</ingredient> until the fibres break;</item>



<item align="indent2" size="smaller">Be sure that next you have, to broil the <ingredient>steak,</ingredient></item>



<item align="indent2" size="smaller">Good coal in plenty; nor a moment leave,</item>



<item align="indent2" size="smaller">But turn it over this way and then that.</item>



<item align="indent2" size="smaller">The lean should be quite rare--not so the fat:</item>



<item align="indent2" size="smaller">The platter now and then the juice receive.</item>



<item align="indent2" size="smaller">Put on your <ingredient>butter</ingredient>--place it on your meat--</item>



<item align="indent2" size="smaller"><ingredient>Salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper;</ingredient> turn it over, serve and eat."</item>



</list>



</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p>The buttock is often prepared by some "old-country men" for a <purpose>Scotch ham,</purpose>by taking off the flank, the veiny piece, and removing the whole of the leg-bone; it is then<pb n="52" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=60"/>







cured in a <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice pickle,</ingredient> after which it is bound hard with cord, when it is either hung to dry or lightly smoked, and is then generally used as smoked beef.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p>The <emph rend="bold">plate-piece</emph> (in Boston called <emph rend="italic">rattle-ran)</emph> is commonly used for <purpose>corned or salted beef,</purpose>







and the best for pressing. Many butchers roll it--after taking all the bones out--with <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> etc., then tie or skewer it up in a round form. After being well cured it is known as Scotch roll, a name given it by the author. It is an excellent dish when cold.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p>The <emph rend="bold">hind-quarter</emph> (represented in the preceding figure, including Nos. 1, 2, and 5) is first divided by taking off the leg of pork, which is generally used fresh for roasting, after having the boneneatly taken out and finely scored; but when intended for <purpose>corning,</purpose>







it should be kept in <ingredient>pickle</ingredient> ten or twelve days before use.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Ox feet, or cow heels.</purpose>







These are principally used by foreigners in making fricassee, stews, bake, jellies, etc.,<pb n="90" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=98"/>







after having been scalded and dressed as the calves' feet. They require five or six hours' boiling. <variation>The <ingredient>fat skimmings of ox feet or cow heels</ingredient> is called "neat's foot oil."</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Calves' entrails</emph> and <emph rend="bold">fat</emph> or <emph rend="bold">chitterlings.</emph></purpose>







--This part of the calf, prepared by the Germans and French, is made into an excellent dish, which I have eaten with a good relish. They are taken from the calf while warm, then the entire <ingredient>gut</ingredient> is slit or cut open, well cleaned and soaked, and they are ready for use.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Calves' melt.</purpose>







--This <ingredient>small, dark piece, attached to the lights,</ingredient> is seldom used in this country, but it is said to make a very good dish when prepared by the English cook. I give one receipt for cooking it: After soaking three or four hours in a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and also a little <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> wipe dry, <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> it well, and boil it.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Lambs'</emph> or <emph rend="bold">sheep's trotters.</emph></purpose>







--Prepared like calves' feet, then soaked in <ingredient>water</ingredient> until quite white, when they are ready for use. They are best stewed.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Lambs'</emph> or <emph rend="bold">sheep's melt.</emph></purpose>







--Prepared in the same manner as the calves' melt, but not quite so good eating.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Sheep's paunch,</emph> or <emph rend="bold">stomach.</emph>--An excellent dish is made of this article by the Scotch, called "Scotch haggis."</purpose>







The following was furnished to me by <attribution>Mrs. John Duncan:</attribution></p>



<p>"Procure the <ingredient>large stomach-bag (paunch) of a sheep, also one of the smaller bags,</ingredient> called the king's hood, together with the pluck, which is the <ingredient>lights,</ingredient> the <ingredient>liver,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>heart.</ingredient></p>



<p>"The bags must be well washed, first in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> then plunged in <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and scraped. Great care must be taken of the large bag; let it lie and soak in cold water, with a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> all night. Wash also the pluck. You will now boil the small bag along with the pluck; in boiling leave the windpipe attached, and let the end of it hang over the edge of the pot, so that impurities may pass freely out. Boil for an hour and a half, and take the whole from the pot. When cold, cut away the windpipe, and any bits of skin or gristle that seem improper. Grate the quarter of the liver (not using the remainder of the haggis), and mince the heart, lights, and small bag very small, along with half a pound of <ingredient>beef suet.</ingredient> Mix all this mince with two small teacupfuls of <ingredient>oatmeal</ingredient>--previously dried before the fire--<ingredient>black and Jamaica pepper</ingredient> and salt; also add half a pint of the <ingredient>liquor in which the pluck was boiled,</ingredient> or <ingredient>beef gravy.</ingredient> Stir all together into a consistency. Then take the large bag, which has been thoroughly cleaned, and put the mince<pb n="95" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=103"/>







into it. Fill it only a little more than half full, in order to leave room for the meal and meat to expand. If crammed too full it will burst in boiling. Sew up the bag with a needle and thread. The haggis is now complete. Put it in a pot with boiling water, and prick it occasionally with a large needle, as it swells, to allow the air to escape. If the bag appears thin, tie a cloth outside the skin. There should be a plate placed beneath it to prevent its sticking to the bottom of the pot. Boil it for three hours. It is served on a dish without garnish, and requires no gravy, as it is sufficiently rich in itself."</p>



<p><variation><emph rend="italic">Another way.</emph> Procure a good thick <purpose>sheep's paunch,</purpose>







without holes or thin parts, and have it well cleaned. Clean a <ingredient>sheep's pluck, or haslet,</ingredient> thoroughly, make incisions in the <ingredient>heart</ingredient> and <ingredient>liver</ingredient> to allow the blood to flow out, and parboil the whole, letting the windpipe lie over the side of the pot to permit the phlegm and blood to disgorge from the <ingredient>lungs</ingredient>: the <ingredient>water</ingredient> may be changed after a few minutes' boiling for fresh water. A half hour's boiling will be sufficient; but throw back the half of the liver, to boil until it will grate easily; take the heart, the half of the liver, and part of the <ingredient>lights,</ingredient> trimming away all skins and black-looking parts, and mince them together. Mince also a pound of good <ingredient>beef suet,</ingredient> and four or more <ingredient>onions.</ingredient> Grate the other half of the liver. Half a dozen of <ingredient>small onions,</ingredient> peeled and scalded in two waters, to mix with this mince. Have ready some <ingredient>finely-ground oatmeal,</ingredient> toasted slowly before the fire for four hours, till it is of a light brown color and perfectly dry. Less than two teacupfuls of meal will do for this quantity of meat. Spread the mince on a board and strew the meal lightly over it, with a high seasoning of <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>cayenne,</ingredient> first well mixed. Put in the meat with a half-pint of good <ingredient>beef gravy,</ingredient> or as much strong <ingredient>broth</ingredient> as will make it a very thick stew. Be careful not to fill the bag too full, but allow the meat room to swell; add the <ingredient>juice of a lemon,</ingredient> or a little good <ingredient>vinegar;</ingredient> press out the air and sew up the bag; prick it with a large needle when it first swells in the<pb n="96" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=104"/>







pot, to prevent bursting; let it boil slowly for three hours, if large.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Time for salting meat.</purpose>







--<ingredient>Meat</ingredient> should be salted in cool weather, as soon as it shall stiffen or become rigid. If in warm or hot weather, the animal should be killed in the afternoon, and the next morning salted, and placed in an ice-house. If in freezing weather, it should be salted before freezing, as I have known frozen beef to lay in <ingredient>strong pickle</ingredient> two weeks, and then salted only on the surface--the inside being still frozen and fresh.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Jerked beef.</purpose>







--This name was early given to the following process of curing <ingredient>beef</ingredient>: first, all the bones are taken out; then the flesh is cut into sheets, or thin pieces, put into a <ingredient>strong pickle,</ingredient> or rubbed with dry <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and packed away for two or three days, when it is thoroughly salted; then spread out in the sun to dry hard, gathered together, and dry packed in boxes of two and three hundred pounds each, and generally sent to some of the West India islands.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Cured and smoked meats.</purpose>







--In <ingredient>beef, three pieces are taken from the buttock</ingredient> (for particulars see <emph rend="italic">buttock</emph>)--the inside, outside, and veiny pieces. These are generally used for smoking after having been salted from three to four weeks. <variation>The <purpose>plates, navels, briskets, and tongues</purpose>







(see <ingredient rend="italic">tongues</ingredient>), are also excellent, when prepared in the above manner, to boil with greens.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Bacon.</purpose>







--The <ingredient>part of the shoat or hog commonly used here for bacon is the thin part of the ribs and belly,</ingredient> salted, and either dried or slightly smoked; some also use <ingredient>spices,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> etc. If it be not too thick and fat, it is generally preferred. <variation>The <purpose>regular bacon of England, however, is differently prepared; and there it is usually called "flitch of bacon,"</purpose>







when cured in the following manner. The <ingredient>hog</ingredient> having been slaughtered, instead of scalding the hair off, it is burned off with straw, then shaven clean with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and dressed. When cooled through, it is divided, the <ingredient>hams</ingredient> and <ingredient>head</ingredient> taken off, and the bloody veins carefully removed. The spare-ribs and other bones are then taken out, and the whole covered with <ingredient>fine salt</ingredient> and a small quantity of <ingredient>salt-petre,</ingredient> with also a little <ingredient>brown sugar,</ingredient> which gives a pleasant flavor to the bacon. The flitches are laid down upon one another and re-salted daily, when the top one is put under, for about three weeks. They are then hung up to dry, or very slightly and slowly smoked.</variation> <variation><purpose>The Irish singed bacon</purpose><pb n="100" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=108"/>







is cured here, by some of our large packers, in pretty much the same manner.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Cheeks or Chops.</purpose>







--These are cured with the <ingredient>hams and shoulders,</ingredient> and are very fine when boiled with <ingredient>greens</ingredient> in the spring of the year. Select those which have the most flesh on.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Bologna Sausages.</purpose>







--There are many receipts for making these fine sausages, of which there appears to be two different kinds--the fresh bologna and dried bologna sausages.</p>



<p><variation><purpose>Fresh bologna sausages</purpose>







are prepared usually for immediate use. They are sometimes made of <ingredient>fresh lean beef and pork,</ingredient> having all the fat and sinews extracted and finely chopped; after which, <ingredient>thin strips of cured back fat</ingredient> are interspersed through, and nicely seasoned. This is forced into <ingredient>cleansed beef casins</ingredient> of different lengths. Smoked (say one night), and boiled, or rather simmered, from one to two hours. When pork is high it is sometimes left out, but retaining the back fat to relieve the lean look, and also to add to their flavor. The other kind,</variation></p>



<p><variation><purpose>Dried bologna sausages,</purpose>







are made for long keeping. They are prepared with <ingredient>salt pork or ham,</ingredient> with the <ingredient>lean fresh beef,</ingredient> and more highly seasoned; instead of being smoked, they are hung up and dried. But otherwise prepared as the fresh bolognas.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Rolliches</emph> (from the Dutch word <emph rend="italic">rolletje</emph>).</purpose>







--This peculiar meat preparation was once a famous dish among the ancient Dutch settlers of New Amsterdam, and although the making of it has almost been discontinued in our (New York) State, yet there are many old families in New Jersey and other places, who continue on from year to year, in preparing this as one of their principal dishes, to be used throughout the winter months, especially where fresh meat is only occasionally to be procured. It is found to be a wholesome article of food when properly prepared, and for the following receipt I am indebted to <attribution>Mrs. Ann Hill,</attribution> who<pb n="103" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=111"/>







has prepared and assisted in its preparation for about twenty years. She says: "Take the <ingredient>fresh, uncooked, but well-cleaned tripe,</ingredient> cut it into eight or ten as near square pieces as possible; then cut up the <ingredient>flanks and tops of sirloin pieces of beef,</ingredient> in strips, about as large as a good-sized finger, and lay them so as fat and lean will mix throughout, and enough to fill each piece of the <ingredient>tripe;</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> should be well sprinkled between each layer of meat (some also add <ingredient>herbs</ingredient> to give peculiar flavors); then sew them up tightly and put them into a large pot, and boil slowly, until a broom-wisk or rye-straw can be pushed into them without breaking; they are then taken out, put under a weight, and left so all night; next morning the fat is skimmed off from the liquor, when the rolliches are put into a tight tub or pot, and a <ingredient>mixture of half vinegar and half pot-liquor</ingredient> is poured over, and enough to cover them; then a weight placed on top to keep them under. When wanted, one or more is taken out, cut up into thin slices, and warmed up in the liquor in a frying-pan, when they are found to be excellent eating."</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Lard.</purpose>







--Among the many preparations made, no doubt lard is one of the most important in the culinary art. The <ingredient>fat cut from the various parts of the hog--consisting of the leaf fat and the meat fat</ingredient>--is cut into very small pieces, then boiled until quite rendered, that the pieces begin to look quite brown, when it is taken out, and the pieces or scraps heavily pressed. The melted fat, after having passed through a strainer into pots, etc., becomes lard when cool. The best should be white, without a disagreeable smell.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Sausages.</purpose>







--The best sausages are prepared altogether from <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> chopped small, seasoned, and run or stuffed into <ingredient>casins.</ingredient> Those made in the city are usually quite small in size, as the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> is run into the <ingredient>lamb casins.</ingredient></p>



<p><variation><purpose rend="bold">Country sausages.</purpose>--Those sausages usually made in<pb n="104" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=112"/>







the neighboring country towns are prepared in the same way, but run into <ingredient>beeves' or hogs' casins.</ingredient> Some of the latter are cleanly and well made, and some again are almost as dangerous as some of our city sausages. </variation><variation>One plan of deceit is to add a <ingredient>large percentage of water</ingredient> in mixing the <ingredient>meat;</ingredient> some will add one-eighth or more before it is pressed into the <ingredient>casins,</ingredient> which gives them a very moist, soft, and flabby appearance, while good sausages are firm, and also quite dry on the outside.</variation> <variation>There is danger, also, in the kind and quality of the flesh which some use, it being almost impossible to tell, from outward appearance, of what animal or in what condition the flesh was, when hid in those skins; and the only protection for the buyer is to purchase of those dealers who are certainly known to you, or else to buy the meat and prepare it yourself.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Sausage meat.</purpose>







--This <ingredient>meat</ingredient> is prepared as that for sausages, but not put into casins, and, of course, more open for inspection. Both this and sausages are excellent eating when you feel satisfied that they have been cleanly and properly made; if not, you had better have nothing to do with them. In fact, the same will apply to all of the prepared meats.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Head-cheese.</purpose>







-This article is made usually of <ingredient>pork, or rather from the meat off of the pig's head, skins, and coarse trimmings.</ingredient> After having been well boiled, the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> is cut up in pieces, seasoned well with <ingredient>sage,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and pressed a little, so as to drive out the extra fat and <ingredient>water.</ingredient> <variation>Some add the <ingredient>meat from off a cow or ox head,</ingredient> to make it lean, or not so luscious.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Spiced puddings.</purpose>







--These puddings are made somewhat like head-cheese, and generally prepared by the German dealers, some of whom make large quantities. They are also made of the <ingredient>meat from the pig's chops or cheeks,</ingredient> etc., well spiced and boiled. <variation>Some smoke them.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Blood puddings</purpose>







are usually made from the <ingredient>hog's blood</ingredient> with chopped <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> and seasoned, then put in <ingredient>casins</ingredient> and cooked. <variation>Some make them with <ingredient>beef's blood,</ingredient> adding a<pb n="105" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=113"/>







little <ingredient>milk;</ingredient> but the former is the best, as it is thought to be the richest.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Common puddings.</purpose>







--These puddings are made of the <ingredient>pork skins,</ingredient> <ingredient>beeves' head meat,</ingredient> <ingredient>pigs' liver,</ingredient> etc., seasoned and stuffed into <ingredient>beef's casins,</ingredient> and cooked. Sold at low prices. <variation>These puddings, like the preceding, were more generally used many (forty) years ago by the poorer classes, and especially the hungry laborer, who would take a pair of these puddings (which then weighed one pound) at the cost of three or four cents, and the same amount spent in <ingredient>butter-crackers</ingredient> (nearly or quite as much weight), which would give him a cheap, wholesome, and hearty meal. But of late years the character and reputation of many of these prepared meats have been, except in some instances, any thing but "first rate."</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Brawn.</purpose>







--I have no knowledge of brawn being used in this country, although prepared from <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> or, properly, from the <ingredient>wild-boar.</ingredient> The old-country method of making it appears in <attribution>Willich's Dom. Ency.,</attribution> and is as follows:</p>



<p>"The bones being taken out of the flitches (sides) or other parts, the flesh is sprinkled with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and laid on a tray, that the blood may drain off, after which it is salted a little and rolled up as hard as possible. The length of the collar of brawn should be as much as one side of the boar will bear; so that when rolled up it may be nine or ten inches in diameter. After being thus rolled up, it is boiled in a copper or large kettle, till it is so tender that you may run a stiff straw through it; when it is set by till it is thoroughly cold, and then put into a <ingredient>pickle</ingredient> composed of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and <ingredient>wheat-bran,</ingredient> in the proportion of two handfuls of each of the latter to every gallon of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> which, after being well boiled together, is strained off as clear as possible from the <ingredient>bran,</ingredient> and, when quite cold, the brawn is put into it."</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Pemmican.</purpose>







--One of the most useful applications of <ingredient>buffalo meat</ingredient> consists in the preparation of pemmican, an article of food of the greatest importance, from its portability<pb n="106" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=114"/>







and nutritious qualities. This is prepared by cutting the <ingredient>lean meat</ingredient> into thin slices, exposing it to the heat of the sun or fire, and, when dry, pounding it to a powder. It is then mixed with an equal weight of <ingredient>buffalo suet,</ingredient> and stuffed into <ingredient>bladders.</ingredient> <variation>Sometimes <ingredient>venison</ingredient> is used instead of buffalo beef.</variation> <variation><attribution>Sir John Richardson,</attribution> while preparing for his Arctic Expedition, found it necessary to carry with him pemmican from England. This he prepared by taking a <ingredient>round or buttock of beef</ingredient> cut into thin steaks, from which the fat and membranous parts were pared away, and dried in a kiln until the fibres of the meat became friable. It was then ground in a malt-mill, and mixed with nearly an equal weight of <ingredient>beef suet</ingredient> or <ingredient>lard.</ingredient> This completed the preparation of the plain pemmican;</variation> <variation>but to a portion <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> were added, and another portion was sweetened with <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> These latter changes were subsequently highly approved of by the voyagers.</variation> The pemmican was then placed in tin canisters and well rammed down, and after the cooling and contraction of the mass, these were filled up with <ingredient>melted lard</ingredient> through a small hole left in the end, which was then covered with a piece of tin and soldered up."</p>



<p><variation><emph rend="bold"><ingredient>Meat biscuit.</ingredient></emph>--A valuable preparation for long voyages, etc., prepared by <attribution>Mr. G. Borden, jr.,</attribution> was introduced here a few years ago. He says: "The <ingredient>meat biscuit</ingredient> contains, in a concentrated and portable form, all the nutriment of meat combined with <ingredient>flour</ingredient> . . . . by drying or baking the mixture in an oven, in the form of a biscuit or cracker."</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Rennet.</purpose>







--To prepare this article for use, take the <ingredient>stomach of an unweaned calf, lamb, kid, or pig</ingredient> (the calf's preferred), empty it of its contents (some preserve the contents, curds, for use, but they are generally somewhat offensive), wash it slightly with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> let it lie ten days in <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> spread it out, and dry it quite hard. To prepare it for use take one quart of <ingredient>soft water,</ingredient> and add salt enough to make a strong pickle; boil, and let it stand until cold; break your dry rennet in small pieces, put it in a jar with<pb n="107" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=115"/>







this pickle; in three days it will be fit for use. Strain, bottle, and cork it, and set it in a cool place.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">A quick mode of curing meats.</purpose>--The <ingredient>meat</ingredient> to be cured is placed in a strong iron vessel connected by a pipe and stop-cock with the brine-tub, also with an exhausting-pump. The cover having been screwed down on the iron vessel, the air is extracted and a vacuum established; whereupon the stop-cock being turned, the <ingredient>brine</ingredient> rushes in and takes the place of the air, filling the pores and penetrating the meat.</p>



<p>If some of the parts should not be impregnated with the pickle, more is pumped in by a small condensing engine (connected with the iron vessel), until a pressure of from one hundred and fifty to two hundred pounds on the square inch be attained. It is then allowed to remain ten or fifteen minutes under pressure, when the meat will be found to be fully salted or well cured.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Preserving meat in a fresh state.</purpose>--A <attribution>Doctor Londe, of France,</attribution> a few years ago, presented a plan for keeping <ingredient>meats</ingredient> in a fresh state for a long period. The process, is to "bone the meat, as far as practicable, plunge it into a kettle of <ingredient>gelatine,</ingredient> at about the temperature of boiling water, where it is held about six minutes, and then hung up to dry. Forty-eight hours later, it is again plunged, with its gelatinous envelope, into a solution of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and then hung up to dry."</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Curing hams and shoulders.</purpose>--Rub the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> well with <ingredient>fine salt,</ingredient> when perfectly cool; lay it in a <implement>sweet cask</implement> for two days. Then, to every hundred pounds of meat, take eight pounds of <ingredient>ground rock-salt,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>salt-petre,</ingredient> two pounds of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one and a half ounces of <ingredient>pot-ash,</ingredient> and four gallons of <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Mix these well together until quite dissolved; skim it and pour it over the meat, when it should be kept under this brine about six weeks (some boil this pickle, and, when cool, pour it over the meat); after which, take out the meat, soak it in <ingredient>cool water</ingredient> for about four to five hours, string the several pieces and hang them up to dry for two days, when they are ready for the smoke-house.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Tainted meat</emph> or <emph rend="bold">game</emph> may be restored as follows:</purpose>







wrap it up in a fine linen cloth, closely, so as to prevent dust or cinders getting in; have ready a pail, or larger vessel of <ingredient>cold water;</ingredient> take a shovelful, or larger quantity of <ingredient>live wood-coals,</ingredient> and throw in; then put the <ingredient>meat or game</ingredient> in, and let it lie under the <ingredient>water</ingredient> for five or ten minutes (according to the size). After taking it out, all the offensive smell will be removed; but it must be immediately cooked.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Fly-blown meats.</purpose>







--The fly which usually blows the meat is known as the green or meat fly. They are always, in the warm weather, found wherever there is <ingredient>fish</ingredient> or flesh, slaughter-houses, markets, larders, pantries, etc., which they frequent for the purpose of "blowing," or leaving their eggs in some moist crevice in the meat. These eggs will hatch in a few hours, so that live maggots are seen to creep.<pb n="109" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=117"/>







Many housekeepers imagine that <ingredient>meats</ingredient> in this state are spoiled, and unfit to be used; but such is not the fact, as a little <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> or <ingredient>salt and water</ingredient> will wash all signs away. Some also think the fly will not blow the newly-killed meats. I have known them to blow in fifteen minutes after the animal has been dressed, and in four hours afterwards found them creeping.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Frozen meat and poultry.</purpose>







--<ingredient>Meat and poultry,</ingredient> of all kinds, should never be frozen, if it is possible to avoid it; it changes the flavor of the flesh, as well as the juices, as it does vegetables and fruit. Nor will meats ripen, or, rather, grow tender, in that state. But, if frozen, it should not be thawed until ready for use, and then not in a warm room gradually, as that will make it flabby and very soon become putrid or spoiled, and, when cooked, be deficient in its flavor. The proper way is to place it in a vessel, cover it with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and there keep until the ice is thawed out, which will be found to form around it.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">To make beef tender.</purpose>







--If the weather is cool enough to keep the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> over-night, it should be cut into slices (about two inches thick); then rub over each piece a small quantity of <ingredient>carbonate of soda,</ingredient> and lay it down on dishes until just before cooking, when it should be washed off, and cut into pieces or steaks of suitable thickness, and cooked as wanted. This process will answer for any kind of flesh or fowl. In some of the Southern States, where little else than poor, tough beef is seen, this "tendering" method is adopted, but at the expense of the natural sweetness of the beef.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p>Codfish, no doubt, is one of the best fish known to make the excellent fisherman's dish called "chowder," and for the following preparation -- which I think is the best one I ever ate -- I am indebted to <attribution>the late Michael Burnham, Esq.,</attribution> by whom it was sent to me:</p><pb n="216" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=224"/>







<p><purpose rend="italic">Fish-chowder.</purpose>







-- Take a <ingredient>codfish</ingredient> about six or seven pounds, cut in slices about one inch thick; take six or seven medium-sized <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> and cut in slices; take one pound <ingredient>salt pork,</ingredient> cut in slices, and fried brown; when sufficiently done, take out the pork from the pot with one half the <ingredient>fat.</ingredient> Now put in a layer of <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> then some of the potatoes and pork, with some <ingredient>pilot-bread;</ingredient> and so on, alternately, until all is in the pot. Pour over the whole quart of <ingredient>water</ingredient> and one pint of <ingredient>milk;</ingredient> add salt and <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> to your taste, and boil twenty minutes. A few <ingredient>onions</ingredient> improve it for those who are fond of them.</p>



<p>P.S. -- To the above I add one hundred <ingredient>clams or oysters,</ingredient> in layers with the rest, and a half <implement>tumbler</implement> of <ingredient>port</ingredient> or a <implement>tumbler</implement> of <ingredient>claret wine</ingredient> two or three minutes before taking off the fire, stirring it up well.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Sturgeon.</purpose>







-- The flesh of this large peculiar-looking fish, when found in our markets for sale, is always with the skin off, and cut up as the halibut. The <ingredient>young fat fish</ingredient> are considered the best, when its flesh has a light red or "beefy" appearance and the fat of a pale yellow color. Its flesh is considered wholesome, and, when properly prepared, it is really good eating. Some soak the flesh in <ingredient>scalding water</ingredient> long enough to take away the fatty substance, which is strong if the fish is large; then cut it in steaks and fry it, when it tastes much like veal cutlets. <variation>It is much better to roast or bake, than to boil; in fact, sturgeon-eaters seldom boil it.</variation> <variation>Many also prefer it salted and smoked, when to be had in that state.</variation> In season all through the summer months, when it is taken in the North River. They commence to take them about the middle of April and continue until the 1st of September, and are principally of that variety called the sharp-nosed sturgeon, ranging in length from four to nine feet, and in weight from one hundred to above three hundred and fifty pounds.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p>In the north of Europe the flesh of the sturgeon furnishes acceptable food to a great many persons, while its airbladder is converted into isinglass, and its roe into <emph rend="italic">caviare.</emph>" This <purpose rend="italic">caviare</purpose>







is the <ingredient>roe of the sturgeon or other large fish,</ingredient> prepared by salting and pressing, and was considered a great delicacy when used with roast meats. There is also a very good oil extracted from the offal parts, which is used for the purposes of light."</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p>The <purpose rend="bold">Burlington herring</purpose>







have also had quite a reputation for the table. Large quantities were caught at Dunk's Ferry, says the <emph rend="italic">Burlington Gazette</emph> (of 1845), many of which were cured by a <attribution>Mr. Mitchell, at his establishment in Burlington.</attribution> His method for curing was as follows: "The <ingredient>fish</ingredient> are brought to Mr. Mitchell directly from the nets -- all Delaware River fish, and therefore perfectly fresh. They are then cleaned of scales and thrown into <ingredient>pickle,</ingredient> where they remain some hours, whence they are taken and strung on sticks containing a dozen, allowed to dry, and then suspended in the smoke-house, where a choking fog is raised by means of burning sawdust; and, after a week of such fumigation, they are taken down, packed in boxes, and are<pb n="228" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=236"/>







ready for market. There is a peculiar flavor imparted to the Burlington herring by the pickle in which they are soaked previous to smoking." </p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Porpoises.</purpose>







-- These large fish are sometimes caught especially by sailors who have been long without fresh provisions. They harpoon them, and cut out the choice fleshy parts, enough for a day or two's use, and throw the balance overboard. The flesh is nearly the color of venison, and from a small fish is quite tender, with the flavor resembling beef, but fishy, and, when fried or made into fish-balls, is considered good eating, and much enjoyed by them.</p>



<p><attribution>John Josselyn, gent.,</attribution> while on his passage to this country, in the month of May, 1638, writes -- "In the afternoon, the mariners struck a porpoise, called also a <emph rend="italic">marsovius,</emph> or seahogg, with an harping-iron, and hoisted her aboard. They cut some of it into thin pieces, and fryed. It tastes like rusty bacon, or hung beef -- if not worse; <variation>but the <ingredient>liver boiled,</ingredient> and soused sometimes in <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> is more grateful to the pallat."</variation> (The liver is much like a hog's, both in appearance and flavor.) Soon after "we took a sharke, a great one, and hoisted him on board. The seamen divided the sharke into quarters, and made more quarters about it than the pursuer, when he makes five quarters of an oxe; and, after they had cooked him, he proved very rough-grained, not worthy of wholesome preferment; but, in the afternoon, we took store of bonitoes, or Spanish dolphins -- a fish about the size of a large mackerel, beautiful with admirable varieties of glittering colours in the water, and was excellent food." (No doubt, the <emph rend="italic">Spanish mackerel.</emph>)</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Dog-fish.</purpose>







-- These fish are occasionally, and sometimes plentifully taken in our harbor, but seldom found for sale in our markets, although they are eatable. Large numbers are taken on the eastern coast, principally for the oil they furnish; and in Truro and Provincetown, Mass., the fish are dried for food for cattle. In Scotland, <ingredient>the flesh of this fish</ingredient> is eaten by the lower classes; there are also many people who eat them here when properly prepared, -- that is, they<pb n="232" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=240"/>







skin them first before cooking, or scald them so that the outside skin is removed easily. I had a piece of a small one (some fifteen inches in length) nicely fried, sent to me, and found it very much the taste of halibut; rather dry, but good. These fish have much of appearance of young shark (and I am inclined to think they are the young of the same fish), having a small mouth underneath their long upper jaw. The color of the back is of a dark lead-color, lighter on the sides and quite white underneath, and without scales, although the skin is quite rough when stroked backwards, and is considerably used for polishing certain articles.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><attribution>Charles Francis Hall,</attribution> in his "Arctic Researches, and Life among the Esquimaux," informs us that "the skin of <purpose>Greenland whale</purpose>







is a great treat to the Esquimaux, who eat it raw. The black skin is three-fourths of an inch thick, and looks like India-rubber. It is good eating in its raw state, even for a white man, as I know from experience; but when boiled and soused in <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> it is most excellent. </p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Snails.</purpose>







-- From the French journals, we learn that snails have become a fashionable article of diet in France. "That there are fifty restaurants, and more than twelve hundred private tables, in Paris, where snails are accepted as a delicacy by from eight to ten thousand consumers. The market price of the great vineyard snails is from 2f. 50c. to 3f. 50c. (forty-seven to sixty-six cents) per hundred, while those of<pb n="312" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=320"/>







the hedges, woods and forest bring only from 2f. to 2f. 25c. (thirty-eight to forty-three cents.)" Snails are, and have been for several years, imported from Europe, but are principally used by foreigners. They are generally stewed after having been scalded out of their shell.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Green turtle.</purpose>







-- This fine <ingredient>turtle</ingredient> is well known to the epicure for its delicious steaks and the savory soup which it affords. The flesh appears to be of three colors, and it is said to combine the taste of fish, flesh, and fowl, although one of the members of the "Turtle Club" (Denman), who appears well informed on the subject, says: "The dark red flesh is called beef, a lighter part veal, and the other part lamb." The fat is of a green color. The veal part is generally used for steaks, which are taken from the fore-quarter. Those under fifty pounds weight are called "chicken turtle," and from fifty to eighty pounds weight are considered the best.</p>



<p><variation>In preparing them, after having hung them up by the hindfins, and taken off the head, some five or six hours after, they should be taken down, and the shells, both under and top, nicely cut off, then drawn or emptied, and cut up as desired.</variation> They are found in our large markets, sometimes as early as May, and continue to cold weather; occasionally to be had in the winter months. They are kept alive in large cars, and fed with cabbage-leaves, beet-tops, etc., of which they appear to be fond. The dealers have them to weigh from ten to upwards of four hundred pounds.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Preparing fish for cooking.</purpose>







-- The great thing to be attended to in the preparation of <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> is to cleanse away every particle that is offensive, and yet to do this in such a manner that the fish may retain its stiffness, which is frequently destroyed by the knocking about and handling it while the process is going on. By this means the firmness and fine flavor, if not wholly destroyed, is in a great degree impaired. <variation>Another thing to be kept in mind is, that many different kinds of fish require to be opened in a different manner.</variation> <variation>Some require great pains to be taken in the scalding of them, or cleansing them from their slime; others may be dressed without undergoing this process at all, or even gutted; and some there are, as <ingredient>fresh-water eels,</ingredient> <ingredient>catfish,</ingredient> etc., for example, that require to be stripped of their external skins altogether.</variation> <variation>Fish which are taken from ponds, or stagnant waters, often have a muddy taste, which exists only in the skin, and in the process of cooking this flavor is communicated to the body. To remedy this, they ought to be skinned, as they do with cat-fish, <ingredient>bull-heads,</ingredient> <ingredient>eels,</ingredient> etc., or by soaking them in <ingredient>salt and water</ingredient> before cleaning them for half an hour, then rinsing them with <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> But never leave a good fish one moment in the<pb n="319" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=327"/>







<ingredient>water</ingredient> after it is thoroughly washed -- by this means the flavor is often materially injured.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Preserving fish fresh.</purpose>







-- Draw the <ingredient>fish</ingredient> and remove the gills, then insert pieces of <ingredient>charcoal</ingredient> in their mouths and bellies. <variation>If they are to be conveyed any distance, wrap each fish up separately in linen cloth, and place them in a box with <ingredient>cabbage-leaves</ingredient> above and below them.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><emph rend="bold"><ingredient>Artichoke.</ingredient></emph> -- There appears to be two distinct plants of this name used as food -- the top or head of one kind, and the root or tuber of the other. The best variety of the first kind, or that preferred here, is called the <purpose rend="italic">globe artichoke,</purpose>







although the <emph rend="italic">conical, oval, large flat,</emph> etc., have many friends, both here and in Europe. The part eaten is the <ingredient>fleshy portion of the leaf of the flower or head,</ingredient> before it blooms, which forms on the top of the stem. The plant itself much resembles the thistle. (The whole heads are, however, sometimes pickled.) The fleshy leaves are prepared as a salad, or are best when stewed or boiled, and are found in season from July to November. <variation>The French and Italians bend down the <ingredient>leaves and stalks,</ingredient> bind them together, then cover them with earth to blanch like celery, when it is known as <purpose rend="italic">artichoke-chards.</purpose>







These are eaten raw in winter, with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> or <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> <ingredient>oil,</ingredient> etc., as a salad or substitute for radishes.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>The other species, of which the tuber only is used, is called <purpose rend="italic">Jerusalem artichoke.</purpose>







The roots, or tubers, of this plant are much like small, ill-shaped potatoes, which grow in clusters of various sizes, forms, and colors, some of which are white, yellow, red, and purple skinned; but I believe that all the varieties usually boil watery; some, however,<pb n="323" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=331"/>







stew them afterwards with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> when they will be found as pleasant-tasted as the real artichoke.</p>



<p><variation>They are also very good cut up raw into thin slices, with <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> etc.</variation> They should be taken out of the ground in September or October, and preserved in sand for winter consumption.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Asparagus.</purpose>







-- This is one of the best and choicest luxuries of the vegetable kind, being a wholesome, digestible, and a light food. Among the best varieties the <ingredient>green giant asparagus</ingredient> is generally preferred, as its young shoots grow thick and very tender. I have known it to grow so large and fine that the cuttings from sixteen stalks weighed four pounds, and many of them, singly, eight inches of tender eating. Some prefer the white, others the purple top, but neither kind is so sweet or tender as the green giant, grown in the light sandy soil near the sea-shore. In boiling the shoots, all should be tied up in one bunch, put into the pot standing up, so that the <ingredient>water</ingredient> is up about half way; then boiled some ten to fifteen minutes; then laid on its side, so the water covers all, and thus finished, when principally all the parts may be eaten.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Cardoons.</purpose>







--This plant is a species of the artichoke, but much larger and taller; the stalk part of the leaf and mid-rib, when properly blanched, will be crisp and tender. They are used for soups, stews, salads, etc. The <emph rend="italic">Gardener's Chronicle</emph> says: "When a cardoon is to be cooked, the solid stalks of the leaves are to be cut in pieces, about six inches long, and boiled like any other vegetable, in <ingredient>pure water</ingredient> (not salt and water), till they are tender. They are then to be carefully deprived of the slime and strings that will be found to cover them; and, having been thus thoroughly cleansed, are to be plunged in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> where they must remain until they are wanted for the table. They are then taken out, and heated with <ingredient>white sauce</ingredient> or <ingredient>marrow.</ingredient> The process just described is for the purpose of rendering them white, and of depriving them of the bitterness which is peculiar to them. If this is neglected the cardoons will be black, not white, as well as disagreeable." In season from September until March.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans" class2="beverages">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Chicory,</emph> or <emph rend="bold">wild endive.</emph></purpose>







--The part of this plant used is the long root, which looks somewhat like salsify, and the leaves, when young, can be used as a salad. <variation>The root has a smell like liquorice, and is principally used in the making or mixing with coffee, when the root is properly prepared; that is, by cutting it up in half-inch pieces, then dried in the air, after which it is browned in an oven or kiln, then ground with either <ingredient>coffee,</ingredient> <ingredient>rye,</ingredient> <ingredient>beans,</ingredient> <ingredient>corn,</ingredient> <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> <ingredient>carrots,</ingredient> <ingredient>parsnips,</ingredient> <ingredient>acorns,</ingredient> or other cheap substances, when these mixtures are attractively placed before the public, and sold at high prices--often for pure coffee. Chickory mixed with either <ingredient>roasted rye</ingredient> or <ingredient>coffee,</ingredient> is considered wholesome; but as it is a cheap article, and when mixed with half coffee, should reduce the price to at least one-half--with rye, about one-quarter. Either article, however, should be purchased separately, then prepared to suit the taste, when the purchaser would know what he was using.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Indian corn,</emph> or <emph rend="bold">maize.</emph></purpose>







--The useful qualities of this important plant are very numerous, and easily prepared into a variety of forms fit for human food. <variation>Before it becomes hard and ripe the ears are fit for roasting or boiling; cut from the cob, and cooked with <ingredient>beans,</ingredient> makes the dish called "succotash;"</variation> or <variation>it can be dried and kept a long time for future uses.</variation> <variation>When ripe and hard, it is prepared by coarse or fine grinding for hominy, samp, mush, johnny cake, bread, etc.</variation> There are many varieties, of which the <emph rend="italic">sweet-corn</emph> is considered the best for boiling; and of this quality there are several kinds, caused from peculiar culture, soil, and climate. It begins to arrive from the South (Charleston), about the 1st of June; then from Philadelphia, say from the 10th to the 15th of July; from New York, about the 1st of August; and continues, by a succession of crops, to be soft and good until the 15th of October--although I have eaten it in a good condition on the 1st of December (1855). It was raised on Long Island, near Fort Hamilton,<pb n="334" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=342"/>







by Mr. Richard Bennett, and sold in the Jefferson and other markets. But a few years ago, it was the custom for colored women to sit around at the various corners of the market, with their pails and tubs of hot-corn, which had been previously boiled; and others, again, perambulating the streets half of the night, with the cry of "Hot corn! hot corn! hot! just come out of the <implement>boiling-pot.</implement>"</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Kohl rabi, turnip cabbage,</emph> or <emph rend="bold">Dutch turnip.</emph></purpose>







--This vegetable was formerly known as "Egyptian kale; is considered sweeter, more nutritious and solid than either the cabbage or white turnip. On a stem, just above the ground, it grows or swells out in a round, fleshy bulb, about the size and form of a large turnip, on the top of which it sends forth its leaves. Among the varieties, are the white, green, and purple stemmed--the latter usually preferred for winter use, as it can be kept sound and good until late in the spring. They are usually found in the market about the middle of June, and are best<pb n="335" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=343"/>







for the table when quite young, being then more tender and delicate. <variation>They may be cooked like the cabbage or turnip, and eaten with the same condiments;</variation> <variation>or they may be cut in half-inch slices to boil; then change the <ingredient>water</ingredient> once or twice, and then serve it up with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream</ingredient> poured over it.</variation> They should be preserved like a cabbage for winter use.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Leek,</emph> or <emph rend="bold">flag onion.</emph></purpose>







--This common plant of the onion tribe shows large flag-leaves running up from small, fine roots. They are generally found tied in bunches, or one or two with a <ingredient>small bunch of parsley,</ingredient> tied up, being a quantity sufficient for a soup or stew, etc., for a small family. <variation>The <ingredient>leeks,</ingredient> when properly blanched, are boiled, and served with <ingredient>toasted bread</ingredient> and <ingredient>white sauce,</ingredient> and eaten as asparagus.</variation> The young leeks are found in August, and continue throughout the winter.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose>The following test, in some occasions, may be found useful: "Sprinkle salt on the spongy part or gill of the mushroom to be tried.</purpose>







If they turn yellow they are poisonous; but if they turn black they are good. Allow the <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to act a little time before you decide the color." They are extensively used for making catsup, stewing, pickles, etc. They are in season during September and October, but by artificial culture may be had throughout the whole year.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Pumpkins.</purpose>







--There are several varieties of this vegetable much esteemed, and among the best is the cheese, West India, sugar, striped, etc., which are <variation>excellent for the famous <purpose>"pumpkin pies,"</purpose>







pumpkin bread, etc. Their season commences in September and lasts until January, when they generally disappear, although, if kept dry and from the frost, they will keep until spring. By cutting them in rings or pieces, and plain drying them, they will also keep well. <variation>Another process of drying them is noticed in the <emph rend="italic">Ohio<pb n="346" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=354"/>







Farmer,</emph> who tells us to "cut them up and stew until they are soft and dry; pound and strain through a <implement>cullender;</implement> then grease pie-pans, and spread it on about a quarter of an inch thick, and dry it; roll it up, and put it away, in a tight box or bag, from the insects. Each one of these rolls will make a pie."</variation></variation>I have tried what was called "pumpkin meal" or flour, but it did not give satisfaction.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Tuberous-rooted wood sorrel</emph> or <emph rend="bold">tuberous-rooted oxalis.</emph></purpose>







--The tubers as well as the leaves and flowers of this plant are used in various ways. Professor Morren says: "The uses of the <emph rend="italic">Oxalis</emph> are many. The young leaves are dressed like <emph rend="italic">Sorrel</emph> in soup, or as a vegetable. They have a fresh and agreeable acid, especially in the spring. <variation>The <purpose>flowers</purpose>







are excellent in salad alone, or mixed with <ingredient rend="italic">Corn Salad,</ingredient> <ingredient><emph rend="italic">Endive,</emph> of both kinds,</ingredient> <ingredient>red <emph rend="italic">Cabbage,</emph></ingredient> <ingredient rend="italic">Beet-root,</ingredient> and even with the <ingredient>petals of the <emph rend="italic">Dahlia,</emph></ingredient> which are delicious when thus employed.</variation> <variation>The <purpose>roots (or tubers)</purpose>







are gently boiled with <ingredient>salt and water,</ingredient> after having been washed and slightly peeled. They are then eaten like <emph rend="italic">Asparagus,</emph> in the Flemish fashion, with <ingredient>melted <emph rend="italic">Butter</emph></ingredient> and the <ingredient>yolk of <emph rend="italic">Eggs.</emph></ingredient> They are also served up, like <emph rend="italic">Scorzonera</emph> and <emph rend="italic">Endive,</emph> with <ingredient>white sauce,</ingredient></variation> and form, in whatever way dressed, a tender, succulent dish, easy to digest, agreeing with the most delicate stomach." It is not much cultivated here.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Vegetable marrow.</purpose>







--This vegetable is said to be a species of the gourd, but found useful for culinary purposes in every stage of its growth. <variation>When young, it is cut into slices and fried with <ingredient>butter;</ingredient></variation> <variation>when more mature it is cut into quarters, stewed in <ingredient>rich gravy,</ingredient> and seasoned to taste. It is said to be both wholesome and nutritious.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Japanese yam,</emph> or <emph rend="bold">Chinese potato,</emph></purpose>







has been introduced into our country through the Patent Office, in the early part of the year 1855. In the fall of the same year, Mr. Boll, a florist, exhibited at the Fair of the American Institute several fine roots, which had some the appearance of long white <emph rend="italic">sweet potatoes.</emph> <variation>When fully matured and plainly cooked--either boiled or roasted--with a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> its flavor is much like that of the common <emph rend="italic">potato,</emph> being quite dry and farinaceous.</variation> One drawback, however, to its large cultivation will be from the great depth it grows into the ground.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="medhealth">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Bene plant.</purpose>--This plant is much used in the South for culinary purposes. "The blacks in Georgia boil some of the <ingredient>seeds</ingredient> with their allowance of <ingredient>Indian Corn.</ingredient> <variation>A few leaves, when green, plunged a few times in a <implement>tumbler</implement> of<pb n="359" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=367"/>







<ingredient>water,</ingredient> make it a <purpose>thin jelly,</purpose>







without taste or color, which children afflicted with the summer-complaint will drink freely, and it is said to be the best remedy ever discovered." </variation> <variation>An <purpose>excellent oil</purpose>







is made from the <ingredient>seeds,</ingredient> after it has age.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Tarragon,</emph> or <emph rend="bold">dragon's wort.</emph></purpose>







--This plant, or rather the leaves and young tops, are frequently used in salads, soups, pickles, etc. <variation>They are of a hot and biting character, and when put in <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> (<emph rend="italic">tarragon vinegar</emph>), it is highly esteemed <purpose>as a fish-sauce.</purpose></variation> They are usually ready for use in the fall months.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Horse-chestnuts,</emph> or <emph rend="bold">buckeyes.</emph></purpose>







--The fruit grows in fleshy, prickly capsules, and ripens in the fall months. These nuts are not edible without some preparation. The <emph rend="italic">Cultivator</emph> says: "The bitter green oil is removed by first grating them to a pulp, then adding one fiftieth (1-50) by weight of <ingredient>carbonate of soda.</ingredient> The mixture then is thoroughly washed and racked by means of a clear fountain, and a white and agreeable paste subsides, which is manufactured into bread and cakes. <variation>In Paris they are manufactured into starch."</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Cream cheese.</purpose>







--Another article made from <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and is sometimes found in our markets, but more particularly in those of Philadelphia. It is made from <ingredient>rich sour cream</ingredient> tied up in linen cloth to drain, then laid on a deep dish, still covered around, and turned every day, and sprinkled with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> for ten days or a fortnight, until it is ripe. If wanted to ripen quick, cover it with <ingredient>mint</ingredient> or <ingredient>nettle leaves.</ingredient> This, however, is only one way. There is another article much used called</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">



<p><purpose rend="bold">How to preserve eggs.</purpose>







--Pour a gallon of <ingredient>water</ingredient> upon a pound of <ingredient>quick-lime</ingredient> in a jar. Let it remain about twenty-four hours to cool after its effervescence; procure <emph rend="italic"><ingredient>eggs</ingredient></emph> as fresh as you can, and drop them into the jar <emph rend="italic">gently;</emph> place the jar where you can take out the <emph rend="italic">eggs without disturbing it,</emph> so the <emph rend="italic">eggs</emph> will keep good for a twelvemonth. (Trans. Am. Inst., 1855.)</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Hominy.</purpose>







--There appears but two kinds of this excellent and healthy food prepared for sale, which are usually known as the <emph rend="italic">small</emph> and <emph rend="italic">great hominy,</emph> either of which are seldom or ever prepared or cooked ready for sale in the Boston or New York markets; but in the public markets of Philadelphia, Baltimore, and Washington it is sold in large quantities, not only to the poorer classes, but to all. There the people come as much prepared to purchase it and bring it in their kettles, or dishes, as they do their <emph rend="italic">Butter.</emph> Many families, no doubt, in either New York, Boston, or elsewhere, who have not the convenience, knowledge, or the time to cook it (and it requires a considerable time to do it properly), would purchase it as quickly as they would <emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Sausages,</ingredient></emph> <emph rend="italic">Head-cheese,</emph> or even <emph rend="italic">Butter</emph> itself. However, in point of 



 



<pb n="409" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=417"/>







economy for human food, it is said that one <emph rend="italic">Bushel of Hominy</emph> is equal to <emph rend="italic">Eight Bushels</emph> of <emph rend="italic">Potatoes.</emph> The "Plough" says, to prepare it: "Wash slightly in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and soak twelve hours in tepid <ingredient>soft water;</ingredient> then boil slowly from three to six hours in the same water, with plenty more added from time to time, with great care to prevent burning. Don't salt while cooking, as that or <ingredient>hard water</ingredient> will harden the <ingredient>corn.</ingredient> When done, add <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> or the better way is to let every one season to suit his taste. It is good hot or cold, and better when warmed over."</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>Since writing the above, I have found another kind, called <purpose rend="bold">lyed hominy,</purpose>







which is differently although easily prepared. That is, boil the <ingredient>white field <emph rend="italic">corn</emph></ingredient> in <ingredient><emph rend="italic">ashes</emph></ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> until the husk or skin of the grain is loosened, which takes place in a few minutes; care, however, must be taken that it does not remain too long in the <emph rend="italic">ashes,</emph> or it will taste of the lye. So soon as the husk is loosened, it must be washed and rubbed through the hands in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> until the grain is cleansed from the <emph rend="italic">ashes</emph> and husk or bran. When wanted to be cooked for the table, it must be scalded and then put to boil in plenty of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> having plenty of <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> to add to it as the first boils down. The grain will burst into a white ball, and become soft when sufficiently done, when it is ready to be eaten, either warm or cold, with <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> etc.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><attribution>Captain N. Uring</attribution> informs us how <purpose rend="italic">hominy</purpose>







was made in Virginia one hundred and forty years ago (1726). He says: "They put such a quantity of <ingredient>corn</ingredient> in steep (<emph rend="italic">soak</emph>) as they design to boil the next day; and then take a small quantity at a time, and beat it in a <implement>wooden mortar,</implement> which is made by hollowing a piece of tree, and, with a <implement>pestle,</implement> beat the corn till it is broken into small pieces, and the husk separated from the grain, which is facilitated by its being soaked in <ingredient>water</ingredient> all night; when they have beaten the quantity they design, they winnow the husk from the grain, and put it into a pot with some few <ingredient>kidney-beans,</ingredient> and a sufficient quantity of water, with a piece of <ingredient>beef</ingredient> or <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> and boil it, 



 



<pb n="410" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=418"/>







and it is excellent, hearty food, very wholesome and well-tasted, and is what most of the poorer sort of people in that country live upon."</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose rend="bold">Apple-butter</purpose>







is another domestic article which may be properly called a <emph rend="italic">sauce,</emph> being made of <ingredient>sweet cider,</ingredient> and <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> and is occasionally found in our markets. Large quantities are manufactured in some of the States, more especially in Pennsylvania, where its use is almost universal, being considered one of the necessaries of the table. In its preparation, "the <ingredient>cider</ingredient> is boiled in large kettles, holding from thirty to forty gallons, into which <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> properly pared and quartered, are thrown--say two bushels of prepared apples to twenty-five gallons of cider. After six to eight hours' boiling, during which the liquor is constantly stirred, it begins to thicken, and, when reduced to a tolerable paste, and about the color of chocolate, it is taken from the fire, deposited in earthen jars, and, after standing a few weeks, is of good flavor for use."</p>



<p><variation><purpose rend="bold">Apple-sauce</purpose>







is another similar-made article, except the mashing of the <ingredient>apple.</ingredient> Both of the above are made in large quantities by the Shakers, who put it up in neat and proper packages, when it is readily sold.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose><emph rend="bold">Saur-kraut,</emph> or <emph rend="bold">sour-krout.</emph></purpose>







--This article is found quite plentiful in our markets, usually prepared by the Germans. To make it, take as many <ingredient>hard, firm cabbages</ingredient> as you wish to preserve, tear off the loose leaves, then quarter them, cut out the hearts or stalks, and chop, with a machine or hand, the quarters into small pieces. Then, to every one hundred pounds of <ingredient>cabbage,</ingredient> take three pounds of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>caraway-seed,</ingredient> and two ounces of <ingredient>juniper-berries;</ingredient> mix them all together. Procure sweet, clean, <implement>iron-hooped casks,</implement> lay the chopped cabbage three inches deep, then sprinkle each layer, as it is pressed in, with the mixture of salt, caraway-seed, and juniper-berries. After each is full, it must be covered with a linen cloth, and wooden head, then pressed down with heavy weights, and allowed to ferment for a month. The cabbage produces a 



 



<pb n="411" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=mara&#38;PageNum=419"/>







great deal of water, which must be poured off, and its place supplied with a mixture of <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> <ingredient>whole black-pepper,</ingredient> and common <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> keeping the cabbage always well covered with <ingredient>brine,</ingredient> and have the <implement>casks</implement> placed in a cool situation as soon as a sour smell is perceived.</p></recipe>



