<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose>HULLED CORN.</purpose>







--<ingredient>Corn</ingredient> is probably <emph rend="italic">best</emph> adapted to the wants of the human system when boiled whole. The only difficulty in this mode of preparation, is with the cuticle or hull that covers the kernel, and the part from which, in germination, the chit is produced. These are not so easily disengaged as could be desired. Lye has commonly been used to separate them; but there are objections to its use. It is true, that subsequent boiling will remove the taste as well as the poisonous properties of the lye in part, but never entirely. Besides, too much boiling wastes, in some slight degree, the nutriment.</p><p>If <ingredient>corn</ingredient> is soaked or macerated in simple <ingredient>water</ingredient> of the temperature of about 100&#176; of F., for ten or twelve hours, and afterwards boiled a reasonable time, the hulls will be so far disengaged, that they may be easily separated on the plate, and with as much expedition as is consistent with healthful mastication or safe deglutition. If, however, any person wishes to eat more rapidly, and to save time at the expense of health and life, he can add a bag of <ingredient>ashes</ingredient> to the <ingredient>corn</ingredient> at the first boiling, which will disengage the hulls more effectually.</p> 



 



<pb n="120" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=youn&#38;PageNum=126"/>







<p>It is true, I have known the whole mass swallowed without any attempt to separate the cuticle, and without any apparent evil effects. Not, however, without great pains to masticate it perfectly and swallow it very slowly.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose>INDIAN CAKES.</purpose>







--This valuable article of human sustenance, known by the various names of "johnny cake," "hoe cake," &amp;c., is prepared differently by different persons; but in almost every way with which I am acquainted, it forms--to those who are trained to it--a very palatable, and if eaten at a proper temperature, an exceedingly rich and wholesome food.</p><p>The best way of preparation is probably the following:--The <ingredient>meal</ingredient> ground not too finely, should be wet with pure, <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> (though some use <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient>) and made into very thin cakes, which should be slowly baked till they become somewhat firm. These should be eaten without the addition of cream, butter, molasses, or any other condiment, and of the temperature of the surrounding atmosphere. Made in the common way, however, that is, of the ordinary thickness, and not baked very hard, and eaten with the usual additions, they cannot be said to be unwholesome, absolutely so; but only inferior to those which are made still more in accordance with the human constitution.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p>The best method of <purpose><alt synonym1="roasted potatoes">roasting the potatoe,</alt></purpose>







is to take away the ashes of a good fire quite to the hearth, lay down the <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> in a single layer, cover them with hot embers to the depth of an inch or so, and then build a good fire over them. In this way, and in a reasonable time, they will usually be found light and excellent. Once it was thought necessary, first to fill the interstices and just cover the surface with cold ashes, before putting on the hot embers; but the former mode is preferable.</p><p>Those who wish to be very nice, may find it pleasant to wrap each <ingredient>potatoe,</ingredient> when well washed, in a piece of brown paper, wetted just so that it will adhere, before committing it to the embers. In this way it comes forth in a more cleanly condition, and is sooner made ready for the table. This method is also preferable for those who eat the skins. The latter I do not recommend; but like the skins of apples, as well as many other vegetables, if not too much changed by cookery, and if well masticated, the skins cannot be particularly objectionable.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose><alt synonym1="boiled potatoes">Boiling is the most universal mode of cooking the potatoe.</alt></purpose>







It is, moreover, a very convenient process. More care, however, is required to render it dry and mealy than in roasting, steaming or baking; and strange as the assertion may seem, there are very many house-keepers who suppose themselves perfect in the art of cookery, who do not understand the art of boiling <ingredient>potatoes.</ingredient></p><p>Some do not boil them enough. This, however, is not so serious an evil; since we are not obliged to eat the inner, unboiled portion. But a still greater number do not boil them well.</p><p>One reason why boiled <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> sometimes are not good is, that they are unripe or otherwise imperfect. <ingredient>Potatoes,</ingredient> in order to be perfect, should be planted in a proper soil, and at a proper season; and if manure is used at all, it should be that sort of manure which is best adapted to the crop itself, and also to the kind of soil to which it is applied. There is a certain kind of relation, I should rather say opposition, in the character of soils and manures, which deserves to be attended to. For want of the necessary knowledge on this subject, or for want of a disposition to use the knowledge which is possessed, a large proportion of the <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> 



 



<pb n="155" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=youn&#38;PageNum=161"/>







which are used in our families are more or less watery, or at least far from being as mealy as they might be. The more mealy a <ingredient>potatoe</ingredient> is, as a general rule, the better flavored and more healthy it is; but of those which are truly mealy, there is a great difference in their flavor. A truly perfect <ingredient>potatoe,</ingredient> perfectly roasted, steamed or boiled, is almost as delicate an article of food as a loaf of bread, though not so nutritious.</p><p>The best and most perfect <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> may be so badly boiled as to be comparatively unfit for the table, while those which, though mealy, are somewhat inferior in richness and flavor, may, by superior cookery, be rendered vastly their superiors.</p><p><ingredient>Potatoes</ingredient> may be boiled either with or without the skin; but I prefer the former mode until some time in the winter, after which it is best to pare them. Great care should be taken to see that they are thoroughly washed in the first place. No judicious farmer will neglect this point, even in boiling them for his swine or cattle--how much more, then, should it be attended to in their preparation for the table!</p><p>The <ingredient>water</ingredient> should boil before the <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> are put into it; and the quantity of <ingredient>water</ingredient> should be so great, if practicable, that the boiling may continue, notwithstanding the quantity of heat suddenly abstracted by their addition and presence.</p> 



 



<pb n="156" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=youn&#38;PageNum=162"/>







<p>When they are boiled, the <ingredient>water</ingredient> should be suddenly poured off. Then they may be immediately taken up, or may remain in the covered pot a few moments till they become thoroughly dry. I believe they are rather more mealy in the latter case, than if taken up wet with the <ingredient>water</ingredient> in which they are boiled.</p></recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p>For those whose stomachs have preserved their original integrity, or who having once lost it have since regained it, <purpose><alt synonym1="boiled cabbage">cabbage</alt></purpose>







is best when boiled, with a little <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> It needs to boil about an hour. The addition of <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> after it is boiled, renders it more quickly digestible, but the <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> injures the stomach more than the <ingredient>cabbage</ingredient> would by digesting a little more slowly; and therefore I 



 



<pb n="182" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=youn&#38;PageNum=188"/>







cannot advise its use. <variation>For the stomach, as it is usually trained, and as we find it almost everywhere in life, weak and inefficient, and unable to work without the application of "whips and spurs," I suppose that raw <ingredient>cabbage,</ingredient> sliced fine and eaten with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> is the most useful form of this vegetable; and next to this, the German sour crout.</variation></p></recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages"><p><purpose>Egg cider</purpose>







is a favorite drink in some parts of New England. It is made in various ways; but the most common method is simply to break an <ingredient>egg</ingredient> or two into a quart of heated <ingredient>cider,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> or <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> if the <ingredient>cider</ingredient> is too sour, and stir it violently by means of a wooden instrument prepared for the purpose. I have seen a family of children brought up to relish this as one of the greatest treats. And yet it is, as it were, a parent of abominations. <ingredient>Cider</ingredient> is bad enough for the human stomach; but <ingredient>cider,</ingredient> <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> form a compound still worse, and one which deserves not to be named, except to expose its folly, in any decent circle or civilized society.</p></recipe>



