<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>



<illustration><description>The initial capital is ornate, and illustrated with a leaf motif.</description></illustration>



WATCHING one day a white-headed Zu&#241;i grandmother who was stirring vigorously some yellow batter with a bundle of splints, I asked her what she was making. <purpose>"Hoecakes," she answered, only she called it <emph rend="italic">mu'-we.</emph></purpose>







</p>



<p>"How do you make them?" I inquired.</p>



<p>"Sa-k'o, o'lut-si-na la k'ia'kok-shi, hi-ni-na h&#226; i'-ya si'; tem kwi'l-ip-nan, h&#226; ko-la ma-we ta i'-sha-nan wo-lu, sh&#233;l-an-an ul-&#252;p, he'-po-k'on wo'-tap, te'-na'-lap, u-li'-hap,-tchim i'-to-na-k'ia, a'ya-naie'l"-- replied the old woman.</p>



 



<pb n="18" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=25"/>







<p>This is as hard as Zu&#241;i milling; but I will try to grind it into English.</p>



<p>"Meal, soft <ingredient>corn-flour</ingredient> and good <ingredient>water,</ingredient> equally I mix; then stirring, <ingredient>red-pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and <ingredient>suet,</ingredient> I put in, into <ingredient>husks</ingredient> I roll this, into an oven all place shutting the hole; time passed, I take them out. Now then, for eating they are ready!"</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>As spring advanced and the chase yielded each day less and less, these stores so patiently garnered during a past year, so carefully guarded or concealed during a long winter's wanderings, were now drawn from in times of need; for although the snows disappeared and the sun glowed 



 



<pb n="224" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=249"/>







warmly by day, the hot winds drove the sands on the bare, dun plains and the clouds in the bright, dry skies hither and thither, so that "growing things dared not appear." Yet from among the barren wilds which environed him, this ancient knew how to seek for and find means of eking out his wasting substances. Among the high mountains grew many trees, which, stripped of their outer bark and scraped, yielded a <ingredient>snappy pulp and sweet fiber</ingredient>--hard of digestion, it is true, but none the less grateful to his meat-sated appetite. Most valued for this kind of food and easy of access with his rude instruments was the <purpose>yellow pine,</purpose>







thousands of the trunks of which were annually whitened on the southern sides by the scrapers of the ancient Zu&#241;is. Oftentimes only the <ingredient>pulp</ingredient> thus obtained was eaten raw, and the stringy, stringent fiber was wrapped into bundles--huge skeins--and carried home for cooking. Some of it was boiled with <ingredient>bony joints of dried meat.</ingredient> Thus were brought into use the huge, closely-plaited basket vessels mentioned at the outset; for, filled with 



 



<pb n="225" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=250"/>







<ingredient>water,</ingredient> into which the joints and <ingredient>well-pounded bark strings</ingredient> were thrown, these vessels were then set out in front of the huts near the fires and made to boil violently with numbers of the reddened stones, hot as flowing iron, which were dextrously transferred by means of flat <implement>pokers</implement> and cedar-bark holders from fire to basket, from broth to fireplace again, and so on, until the cooking was complete.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>Deep down in the sand which bordered, and for a time almost choked, the starved streams issuing from the mountains, were dug the <purpose>juicy roots of certain rushes</purpose>







which, sweet and earthy in taste, although scarcely more nutritious than the bark-pulp, were like the latter grateful for the variety they afforded. They were eaten raw, or else slightly toasted in the ashes, dipped in <ingredient>salted water,</ingredient> and used as relishes for <ingredient>roasts of jerked meat.</ingredient> <variation>Another root which every child sought and grubbed for with avidity was the <emph rend="italic">kwi'-mia'-tchi-kwa,</emph> or <purpose>"sweet-root," a kind of wild licorice</purpose>







which, nevertheless, differed so far from the product with which we are acquainted that an<pb n="226" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=251"/>







unwholesome amount of bitter was mingled with its sweet. Yet extremely popular was it with these denizens of the night of history, as it has continued to be late into the noonday of the present Zu&#241;is. Doubtless, too, the ancient Zu&#241;i, like the modern, dried the root to serve as an ingredient for other foods. </variation><variation>With the advance of the season the rush stems grew tough, the licorice more bitter than ever, and they were replaced with great quantities of <purpose>watercress</purpose>







<emph rend="italic">(pi'-k'ai-a),</emph> like in taste and appearance, though smaller, the celery we all prize. It grew abundantly in every spring and living streamlet, was boiled and eaten with other food, the residue each day being made into flat, compact cakes, and dried with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> into greenish-black, very stemmy, and indurate bricks, which were packed away for second cookings.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>Another far more nutritious food, but one requiring masterly care in its preparation, was a <purpose>diminutive wild potato</purpose>







<emph rend="italic">(k'ia-pia mo'-we),</emph> which grew in all bottomlands favored to any extent with moisture. These potatoes were poisonous in the raw 



 



<pb n="227" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=252"/>







state or whole, but were rendered harmless by the removal of the skin. As they were never larger than nutmegs, this had to be accomplished by a preliminary boiling with <ingredient>ashes.</ingredient> Afterward the potatoes were again stewed and eaten with the <ingredient>water they had been boiled in,</ingredient> usually with the addition of <ingredient>wild onions</ingredient> as a relish. <variation>A very important addition, too, were these <purpose>onions,</purpose>







which grow in springtime under many of the ranges of cliffs throughout the Southwest, and although true onions, resemble in size and appearance the Eastern garlic. They were invariably eaten raw, in which condition they were almost strong enough to temporarily benumb the organs of taste, flood the eyes, and annihilate all sense of everything in the region of smell save themselves. Peeled and dried for preservation, they resembled diminutive hickory-nuts, which may have suggested, with the foregoing, their Zu&#241;i name, <emph rend="italic">mo'-kwi tet-tchi;</emph> from <emph rend="italic">mo,</emph> nut or fruit, <emph rend="italic">kwi'-mon-ne,</emph> a root, and <emph rend="italic">tet'-tchi,</emph> to stink--"stinking root-nuts."</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>Apace with the season more and more 



 



<pb n="228" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=253"/>







plants furnished food material. Everywhere that rain had fallen on the lower plains grew in fitful and brief luxuriance a <purpose>small variety of milkweed</purpose>







which bore in abundance little seed-vesicles resembling those of the common mustard, although a trifle more corpulent. These were called <emph rend="italic">thla'-pi-a-we,</emph> meaning "hanging pods." Divested of their skins, they were eaten raw, or boiled with other foods, or, again, toasted in hot ashes and soaked in the all-important <ingredient>brine-sauce</ingredient> with <ingredient>mashed onions.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose>A kind of wild, hard-shelled squash,</purpose>







from which doubtless were derived varieties of the true garden plant cultivated by the Zu&#241;is today, grew abundantly in moist arroyos, the fruit of which, while still green, was cooked in various ways. Principally, however, it was boiled to paste, mixed liberally with <ingredient>rancid suet,</ingredient> and fried on hot stone slabs. As such it resembled eggplant fried in butter, the far-gone smell and flavor of the suet being, curiously enough, only to a limited extent recognizable in it.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>A great luxury was a <purpose>kind of puff-ball, or 



 



<pb n="229" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=254"/>







fungus,</purpose>







produced in warm seasons in spontaneous liberality by the rains. These were peeled, toasted, and eaten with a <ingredient>sauce of brine</ingredient> and <ingredient>ground onions,</ingredient> flavored with the <ingredient>aromatic seeds of certain caraway plants native to the country.</ingredient></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>During early summer the <purpose>unripe seedy pods of the yucca(Spanish bayonet, or palmita),</purpose>







a quart or two of which may sometimes be gathered from a single stalk or spike, were much sought after by the ancient Zu&#241;is. They were boiled excessively either in <ingredient>water</ingredient> or in <ingredient>water and ashes.</ingredient> When afterward cleansed they had much the appearance of gherkins, which indeed they prove similar to in taste when pickled in <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient> They were eaten either plain or with a liberal allowance of the <ingredient>flavored brine-sauce</ingredient> <emph rend="italic">(k'i&#196;'thl-k'o-se).</emph> <variation>Like them, gummy, with a flavor of cauliflowers, were the <purpose>hearts of a species of the century plant (agave),</purpose>







which were prepared in the same way.</variation> <variation>Later on the <purpose>large green fruit of the soapweed, or datila</purpose>







(pl. X,<emph rend="italic">f</emph>), a plant similar in appearance to both of the above mentioned, either roasted thoroughly in 



 



<pb n="230" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=255"/>







the ashes or else boiled, were esteemed quite as much as the yucca pods.</variation> Both forms of food are still prepared, in their seasons, the century plants, however, more rarely, because not native to the present habitat of the Zu&#241;is. So important were the two former sources of food considered, that they were credited with having possessed, in the mystic days, conscious existence and extremely jealous dispositions. Doubtless their jealousy and virulence were attributed from the observed fact that either was equal to the other as food, and both were poisonous if eaten raw. As illustrative of this belief, you will not infrequently hear some old member of the Zu&#241;i household tell the youngsters stories like the following, which, although absurd, are curious and ridiculous enough to cause universal laughter and clapping of tiny hands. The old worthy mentioned, very likely with his mouth full of the boiled fruits, will champ a little faster and exclaim:</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>First to ripen, first, too, in importance among the fruits, was the <purpose>datila,</purpose>







called <emph rend="italic">tsu'-pi-a-we</emph> (see pl. X,<emph rend="italic">f</emph>) instead of <emph rend="italic">su'-pi-a-we,</emph> on account of its blushing color when ripe. Few who have not visited the Southwest in autumn imagine that, dry and sterile though it be throughout most of the year, a fruit rivaling in its size, shape, color, and exceeding sweetness the banana, grows there in abundance on the warmer plains. Yellow and red, this long, pulpy fruit hangs in clusters so heavy that they bend or sometimes break the stalks that bear them. Yet, however delicious, these, like the fruit I have compared them with, may not be 



 



<pb n="234" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=259"/>







eaten raw in large quantity with impunity, for their effects on the digestion are, though opposite, equally summary. Tempted by their rare sweetness, ancient Zu&#241;i must have early discovered how to remedy this defect, by pleasing his taste--as predatory school-boys do with green apples--in chewing but not swallowing the datilas, for we find that exactly this process is the initiatory step toward rendering the pulp harmless, equally delicious, and even more nutritious than it is in a state of nature.</p>



<p>After great stores of the fruit had been gathered in little, square burden-baskets by the men and heaped in shady, cool places, it was peeled by the women and thoroughly masticated. By this means not only were the seeds separated from the pulp, but the latter was thus made ready to be set away in water-tight <implement>basket-bowls</implement> for fermentation. By fermentation an agreeable pungent taste was added and the saliva acting on the glutinous or mucilaginous ingredients heightened the sweetness. The process was stopped by excessive boiling, which reduced the pulp to homogenous 



 



<pb n="235" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=260"/>







paste, which on cooling was kneaded into little, flat cakes. The latter, when partially dried were pounded together and rolled into large cylinders. In the course of time these cylinders grow quite solid and gummy, and semi-translucent like the gelatin ink rollers used by printers. In taste the food resembles black licorice. A little slice being hacked off was immersed in <ingredient>two or three quarts of water.</ingredient> When thoroughly soaked, it was stirred, churned, squeezed, and strained, until a dark-red, pasty fluid was formed, than which hardly any delicacy known to the ancient Zu&#241;is ranked more highly or commanded such extravagant bargains in barter with the surrounding tribes.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>The possible rival of <emph rend="italic">tsu'-pi-a-we</emph> was made from the <purpose>hearts of the mescal plant or the mature agave.</purpose>







When large quantities of these cabbage-like hearts had been gathered, great pits were dug in gravelly knolls. Within and around the pits, fires were built, which were kept burning whole days or nights. When the ground had been thoroughly heated, the <ingredient>mescal hearts</ingredient> 



 



<pb n="236" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=261"/>







were thrown in on a layer of coarser leaves of the same plant, with which they were also covered. They were then buried deep in the hot gravel. Huge fires were kept burning over the mounds thus formed until the mescals were considered done.</p>



<p>Meanwhile crowds gathered, dances of a semi-sacred, though not very refined nature, were celebrated, and the pits were opened amid universal rejoicing. The time was divided between riotous feasting and serious mastication of the baked, already very sweet leaves, to separate them from the fiber. The pulp or paste thus formed was spread out thinly over large mats (pl. X <emph rend="italic">i</emph>), and when dried could be conveniently rolled up for transportation. Another and more wholesome method was pursued, if the quantity furnished by the pit proved too much for the maxillary powers of the party. This was to pound the leaves, and, if necessary, moisten them slightly to give them a pulpy consistency, and thus spread and dry them on the plaited mats. Although much less valued by the Indians, this kind of food was toothsome and more 



 



<pb n="237" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=262"/>







nutritious, perhaps, than any other ancient preparation.<ref target="n23" height="superscript">23</ref></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>In dry season or wet, there was one class of fruit that rarely failed, hence we find modern ceremonial and ancient folklore teeming with allusions to it--the <purpose>cactus.</purpose>







Of the many varieties of this plant growing in the Southwest, three were especially fruitful, bearing <ingredient>juicy, plump berries</ingredient> of an acid-sweet taste peculiarly agreeable during the hot dry season in which they ripened. Of these the <emph rend="italic">k&#226;-shi,</emph> or formidable club cactus, bore the largest and perhaps sweetest fruit <emph rend="italic">(tui'-a-we),</emph> of a brilliant although dark scarlet color, and in shape and size not unlike gumbo. The <emph rend="italic">shu'-ne-po</emph> and <emph rend="italic">me'-wi</emph> (pl. X, <emph rend="italic">g</emph>), two varieties of the low-lying chain cactus, bore red and yellow fruit which, though smaller, was more luxuriant and less spiny, hence preferred.</p>



<p>On account of the barbed spines which arm the cactus and its product, and which had the unpleasant quality of sinking deeper and deeper into the flesh once fixed in it, special apparatus had to be employed for gathering the berries or pods. A picker 



 



<pb n="238" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=263"/>







was made of flexible wood, slitted as are the bark-peelers used by willow weavers, and forming long tweezers with which the fruit was grasped (pl. X, <emph rend="italic"> j).</emph> The baskets used were closely woven, quadrangular, although somewhat flat, to fit the back, and gradually tapering from the large opening toward the bottom. They were supported by a band or strap which passed around the forehead or over the shoulders (pl. X, <emph rend="italic">a).</emph> Leaves or grasses were thrown in to prevent the spines from piercing through the meshes.</p>



<p>When a basketful had been gathered it was carried home and emptied upon a bed of clean sand. With two flat sticks the fruit was then stirred about in the sand until divested of its spines, after which it was eaten raw, dried, or roasted slightly in the ashes as an additional security against the spines. Large quantities were gathered for preservation by drying, but as the fruit thus prepared was liable to injury by worms, it was usually ground on a <implement>mealing-slab</implement> (pl. X, <emph rend="italic"> d),</emph> and either stored away in skin bags, to be used in connection with other material for bread-making later on, 



 



<pb n="239" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=264"/>







or formed into huge cakes by the addition of <ingredient>water</ingredient> which rendered it adhesive so as to be easily molded in baskets.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>Among the sandy defiles of the upper plains, mesas, and mountains, grow abundant low bushes bearing very <purpose>juicy little yellow berries called <emph rend="italic">k'ia'-po-li mo'-we,</emph> or the "juice-filled fruitage."</purpose>







These berries were in high favor with the ancient Zu&#241;is as food. They were collected in great quantities and boiled or stewed, forming a sweet but acrid sauce which, although not quite so acid, resembled otherwise the cranberry.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>Another favorite berry was the <purpose>small and equally acrid fruit of the wild currant, called in Zu&#241;i <emph rend="italic">ke-la shi'-u-ni,</emph> or the "first to leaf out,"</purpose>







which grew along the edges of malpais mesas in verdant luxuriance rare to be seen in the Southwest. <variation>Like the two latter, the <purpose>chokecherry or "bitter hanging-fruit"</purpose>







formed the ingredient of frequent sauces.</variation> <variation>The <purpose>wild plum,</purpose>







or <emph rend="italic">si'-lu-e-la mo'-we,</emph> was used not only in the raw and stewed state, but was also dried and preserved for after use.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>A much more abundant fruit, <purpose>very sweet 



 



<pb n="243" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=268"/>







and aromatic in flavor, was the <emph rend="italic">ta'-kwi mo'-we,</emph> or cedar-berries.</purpose>







They were collected in large quantities, boiled, roasted, or dried and ground to form the meal with which were made several varieties of cake, and which will be mentioned with other preparations farther on.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>So long continued and often interrupted was the labor of collecting the various <purpose>nuts and seeds</purpose>







described in the last chapter, that<pb n="248" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=273"/>







they were dried, almost as fast as gathered, by toasting. The means whereby this toasting, or more properly parching, was effected, were ingenious, but the method most laborious. Into one of the shallow trays, which the reader will remember were plastered with clay freely tempered by the addition of grit to keep it from cracking (pl. x, <emph rend="italic">h),</emph> a quantity of glowing wood coals



<illustration><caption>FIG. 3.-The Zu&#241;i hunter</caption><description>An illustration of a Zu&#241;i hunter in front of his dwelling.</description></illustration>



 



<pb n="249" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=274"/>







was placed, together with <ingredient>two or three quarts of the seeds or nuts.</ingredient> The operator, quickly squatting, grasped the tray at opposite edges, and with a rapid, spiral-wise motion of the basket, kept the grain and coals dancing separately round and round, yet almost touching one another, meanwhile puffing the embers with every breath to keep them alive and free from ashes. So dextrously was all this done that the grains were evenly browned, yet none of them scorched; and the frail basket, protected by the thin coating of clay grown hard by long use, was never burned by the fiercest heat of the moving coals. If thus the seeds were rendered more palatable, less liable, when long kept, to germinate, readily tractable on the <implement>mealing stone,</implement> how much more owed the later Zu&#241;is to this early industry. For with the separation from its osier matrix of the thin clay lining, baked hard enough in some instances to form a vessel by itself--lo! is born the <emph rend="italic">potter's art</emph>.<ref target="n25" height="superscript">25</ref> And probably from this crude beginning, by easy, yet lingering steps, all the marvelous beauty and perfection 



 



<pb n="250" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=275"/>







of Pueblo fictile productions were matured. Most probably did I say? Most certainly I may now say; for the spirally built cooking-pot of the older Southwestern ruins (pl. XI, <emph rend="italic">b)</emph> was but the reproduction in clay--rough surface, zigzag ornamentation, and all--of the spirally woven basket-bottle <emph rend="italic">(a),</emph> the name of which earlier object lingered on to distinguish the "basket in clay" as but the offshoot of the basket in osiers. In no other way can the angular the other extremely conventional features of the ancient Pueblo ceramic decorations be explained than by referring them to the imitation of basketry patterns, themselves the mere outgrowth of discolored splint lines. Moreover, by a similar train of reasoning it is seen that the Pueblos owed, too, the art and patterns of weaving--embroidery and all--to basketry, proof almost positive of which exists today in the etymology of the names, of stitches and designs.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose>The pi&#241;on-nuts and acorns were rarely used alone for bread-making but, like the sunflower-seeds and <emph rend="italic">suthl'-to-k'ai</emph> grain,</purpose>







which were extremely rich in oil, were added to the meal of the more starchy varieties as seasoning or "shortening." The <ingredient>nuts and sunflower-seeds</ingredient> were shucked by being reheated in the roasting-tray, 



 



<pb n="253" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=280"/>







and, while still hot, rolled lightly under the <implement>muller,</implement> or <emph rend="italic">molina,</emph> on a coarse slab of lava. The brittle shells were broken by this slight pressure, while the oily meats, rendered soft by the warmth, came out clean and perfect. In this shape they were usually eaten. If designed for thickening soups or stews, which purpose they served admirably, or for use as shortening, they were carefully parched yet again until friable, then slightly ground on a fine-grained stone. So rich were the sunflower and <emph rend="italic">suthl'-to-k'ia</emph> seeds that no amount of drying made it possible to reduce them to meal except in the condition of paste. As such, however, they were formed with the fingers into little patti-cakes which, laid on leaves, or hardened by roasting deep buried in the ashes, were eaten with other food in the place of meat, supplying the lack of the latter, at least to the taste, most admirably. <variation><purpose>The dryer, more starchy seeds, such as the <emph rend="italic">mi'-t&#196;-li-k'o k'u'-shu-tsi,</emph> or purslane, wild rice, and various grass-grains,</purpose>







were of course readily ground and were susceptible of being made into <pb n="254" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=281"/>







a great variety of mushes, breads, and cakes.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>For <purpose>mush,</purpose>







the <ingredient>meal was left coarse</ingredient> and added to <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> until a thick, sticky mass was formed, to stir which was no longer possible. Whatever of this half-cooked mush happened to be left over, was rolled into balls, flattened out and dried, or baked on the embers in which measure of economy arose, no doubt, the earliest suggestion of bread. Bread of other kinds soon followed as a few selected recipes might well show; but let us first consider some kindred culinary inventions.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>It will be borne in mind that these ancients had to effect the boiling of foods with hot stones. Doubtless surviving many efforts to thoroughly cook mush in this way without either filling it with grit or wasting it, were two methods deserving of attention. Some <ingredient>coarse meal</ingredient> was moistened with <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> sufficiently to render it adhesive. This was thoroughly kneaded and rolled into little, elongate balls or cylinders. These cylinders were then encased in leaves and thrown into the boiling 



 



<pb n="255" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=282"/>







basket--together with the heating stones--until sufficiently cooked, when they were dipped up with a wicker scoop. After the stones had been fished out, the fluid remaining, now thick, like gruel or gravy, was allowed to settle, when all of it was poured off except the sandy dregs, and served with the lumps of mush or dumplings. Occasionally little slices or fragments of <ingredient>jerked meat</ingredient> were incased in the meal cylinders to give variety; or, not infrequently <ingredient>meal of juniper berries</ingredient> was kneaded in to impart its sweet taste and aromatic flavor. Both of the former varieties of <purpose>boiled bread</purpose>







were sometimes seasoned with <ingredient>sprigs of cedar</ingredient> by throwing the latter into the <ingredient>water</ingredient> as the boiling progressed.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose>Griddle cakes</purpose>







were made by cooking as much as possible, <ingredient>fine and coarse meal</ingredient> equally blended, with <ingredient>scalding water.</ingredient> The resulting paste or batter was poured over hot, well-polished slabs of sandstone.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose>"Stone-cakes"</purpose>







were made in the same way, except that as a preliminary to the baking, huge sandwiches composed of alternating layers of hot sandstone slabs<pb n="256" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=283"/>







and batter (pl. XI, <emph rend="italic">c</emph>) were built up, carefully inclosed in a casing of larger slabs cemented with mud, and buried in a hot pit over which a fire was built. These cakes were made sweet, very like "Indian pudding," although more solid, by the addition to the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> of <ingredient>wild honey,</ingredient> or by the mastication and fermentation of a portion of it previously to the baking.</p>



<p><variation>Sometimes for the <purpose>baking of separate loaves,</purpose>







these little pits were lined with flat stones set up edgewise around the sides. A rock of lava, if possible, was provided for the lid, and thus was completed the earliest style of oven known to the primitive Zu&#241;is.</variation> <variation>By far their most perfect oven, however, was the smaller of their granaries. These natural cavities which art had but completed as receptacles, were seldom used for baking, save when great feasts or long journeys made requisite large quantities of bread. This bread was mixed like mush with the addition of <ingredient>sour dough</ingredient> or <ingredient>stone-cake</ingredient> to make it rise. It was kneaded into little lumps not exceeding ordinary cookies in size, but much thicker. Meanwhile a 



 



<pb n="257" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=284"/>







fire was kept burning in the oven (or granary) until the surrounding rock was thoroughly heated, when the brands and coals were withdrawn, the cavity swept out with wisps of cedar-brush, and the little lumps of dough, now swollen, laid in, row after row, with long, spatula-shaped staves. The opening was closed with a sandstone slab, every crevice perfectly cemented with mud, and the whole thing left to itself while the sun traveled one long "step" through the sky. At the end of this time the "closing stone" was broken down and the loaves taken out--dark-blue or brownish-gray in color, but thoroughly done and as palatable as any bread since devised by even the most modern Zu&#241;is.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>We may now turn to the foods he made of it. Most easily rendered suitable among these were the <purpose>green-corn preparations.</purpose>







As with ourselves, the <ingredient>ears</ingredient> were roasted on the coals (or, as he had it, "ripened"), or boiled in his little narrow-necked pots of clay. <variation>The delicacy of the year was the far-famed <purpose>succotash,</purpose>







made by scraping the <ingredient>milky kernels from the ears,</ingredient> mingling them with <ingredient>little round beans,</ingredient> which had now come to be domesticated, and with <ingredient>bits of fresh meat,</ingredient> the whole being seasoned with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> thickened with <ingredient>sunflower-seeds,</ingredient> <emph rend="italic">suthl'-to-k'ia,</emph> or pi&#241;on-<ingredient>nut meal,</ingredient> and boiled until reduced to an almost homogeneous stew.</variation> <variation>A little dish, then and long after 



 



<pb n="265" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=292"/>







common to the Zu&#241;is, still a favorite with their distant, primitive neighbors, the <purpose>Havasupai,</purpose>







than which no <ingredient>green-corn</ingredient> cookery of civilization can boast anything more delicious, was made by scraping the kernels off in great quantity, grinding them excessively in their own milk with <ingredient>sunflower seeds</ingredient> and <ingredient>green squash.</ingredient> Sprinkled with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> this paste was boiled until evaporation left it thick and gelatinous like curdled milk, although more adhesive when warm, more solid when cold.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>Of course the <purpose>baked corn</purpose>







--not baked in underground ovens, but in the abandoned granaries of a former period or in the <implement>dome ovens</implement> [see pl. XIV, XV] nearer at hand--was well known.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p><purpose>After the corn was ripened, two modes of making it eatable were extremely simple. Still on the ear it was toasted, or, in the kernel, parched.</purpose>







In several ways this parching was accomplished. Crudest of all these was burial and constant stirring in hot ashes; but the favorite process was to half fill a <emph rend="italic">thle'-mon-ne,</emph> or black, shallow roasting pot or pan (pl. XI, <emph rend="italic">d),</emph> with clean, dry 



 



<pb n="266" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=293"/>







sand. The pot was then set over the fire until the sand became thoroughly heated, when the <ingredient>corn</ingredient> was poured in and constantly stirred with a bundle of hard-wood sprigs <emph rend="italic">(e)</emph> so loosely tied at the middle that they could be spread apart in order that the sand and corn might readily pass between them. When well browned and swollen, a judicious shaking of the toasting vessel brought all the kernels to the top, whence they were easily separated from the sand. <variation>Of the corn thus parched, a highly concentrated and nutritious substance was made, the grains first being cracked, re-toasted, and then <purpose>ground to fine flour.</purpose>







</variation> <variation>A little of this <ingredient>flour</ingredient> stirred into <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> made a <purpose>gruel</purpose>







which required no cooking and was capable alone of sustaining life throughout extended journeys, where lightness of burden and ease of preparation were prime requisites.</variation> <variation>Mixed with <ingredient>water</ingredient> and sweetened by a means heretofore described, or happily by the addition of <ingredient>ground licorice-root,</ingredient> fermented and slightly boiled, it made a <purpose>thin syrup or sweet gruel</purpose>







<emph rend="italic">(tsa'-shi-we),</emph> ever the favorite at the Zu&#241;i evening feast.</variation></p>



 



<pb n="267" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=294"/>







<p><variation>When the <purpose>corn was designed for consumption without further preparation than by the parching, salt, if abundant enough, was used in place of the sand,</purpose>







imparting to the kernels roasted in it a <ingredient>delicate seasoning</ingredient> unattainable by the cruder methods first described.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>Almost as simple as the parched corn was the <emph rend="italic">mi'-li-a-we,</emph> which was no other than baked <ingredient>corn</ingredient> boiled on the ear. A variety of food very like this was called <emph rend="italic">tchu'-la-a-we,</emph> <purpose>ordinary corn on the ear</purpose>







being roasted or browned over the coals, then shelled and boiled in <ingredient>water,</ingredient> either with or without <ingredient>meat.</ingredient> <variation>A more elaborate food was called <purpose>"skinned corn,"</purpose>







which was similar in many respects to the hulled corn of the Northern states. The <ingredient>corn</ingredient> being first excessively 



 



<pb n="293" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=322"/>







boiled in <ingredient>wood-ashes and water,</ingredient> was then thoroughly washed and again boiled, either for consumption in the simple condition in which it left the cooking-pot or by combination in various ways to form the basis of bread, dumplings, griddle-cakes, or the like.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="accompaniments">



<p>Passing over the various dishes which answer to our hasty-pudding, mushes, and the like, which were all well known, we may be interested to find out how the settled, semi-civilized, pueblo Zu&#241;i improved on the baked things of his farming or cliffdwelling predecessor. His most notable advance was perhaps the <purpose>introduction of ashes, or of very finely ground lime,</purpose>







called <emph rend="italic">a'lu-we,</emph> mingled with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> into <ingredient>fermented mush-yeast</ingredient> to overcome its acidity. <variation>The most prized <purpose>leaven of his time,</purpose>







however, was chewed <emph rend="italic">sa'-ko-we</emph> mixed with <ingredient>moderately fine meal</ingredient> and <ingredient>warm water</ingredient> and placed in little narrow-necked pots over or near the hearth until fermentation took place, when <ingredient>lime flour</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> were added. Thus a yeast, in nowise inferior to some of our own, was compounded. In addition to its leavening qualities, this yeast had the 



 



<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=324"/>







 



<pb n="illustration" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=325"/>







<illustration><caption>FOOD RECEPTACLES</caption><description>An illustration of various baskets and clay vessels to hold food.</description></illustration>



 



<pb n="295" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=326"/>







remarkable property, when added to the <ingredient>meal of blue corn or black,</ingredient> to change the color during cookery to a beautiful green hue, or, mingled with <ingredient>yellow-corn flour,</ingredient> to render it light blue.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>Doubtless survivals of a former effort, alluded to once before, to thoroughly effect the cooking of mushes, gruels, etc., by the 



 



<pb n="298" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=329"/>







immersion of heated stones, was a series of <purpose>boiled breads or dumplings</purpose>







of which the simplest were the <emph rend="italic">mu'-k'i&#196;-li-we</emph>and <emph rend="italic">mu'-k'i&#196;-pa-we.</emph> The first of these was made by mixing <ingredient>fine meal</ingredient> or <ingredient>flour</ingredient> with an equal quantity of <ingredient>coarse meal</ingredient> of <emph rend="italic">sa'-k'o-we</emph>, salting, and by the addition of <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and the intervention of excessive kneading to form a stiff dough. This was divided into little pieces which were rolled into hard balls between the hands. A pot of <ingredient>water</ingredient> was set over one of the <implement>columnar receptacles</implement> and, as soon as this was made to boil violently, the little balls were poured in. Instead of disintegrating, they became harder and harder with the progress of the cooking, yet enough of their substance mingled with the water to cause it to become pasty, no sooner than which the pot was lifted from the fire, and the balls, fluid, and all were poured into a <implement>large eating trencher</implement> or bowl of pottery. While still hot these "water balls," as they were called, were eaten with <ingredient>brine sauce.</ingredient> <variation><emph rend="italic">Mu'-k'i&#196;-pa-we</emph> differed from these only in having a <purpose>less proportion of coarse meal added 



 



<pb n="299" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=330"/>







and of different color</purpose>







from the fine, in being more thoroughly salted, seasoned with <ingredient>lime yeast,</ingredient> and mixed before cooking, with <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> instead of cold. The dough was pressed between the hands to form flat cakes, and by the boiling, this food, affected by the <ingredient>lime,</ingredient> was rendered light blue.</variation> <variation>A better kind of <purpose>dumpling was made in the form of little pellets of blue cornmeal,</purpose>







finely ground, mixed with a considerable quantity of <ingredient>lime-batter</ingredient> or <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> kneaded into stiff dough, and wrapped tightly in <ingredient>corn-shucks.</ingredient> During the boiling these dumplings became not only extremely blue but considerably swollen through the agency of the yeast.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>More remarkable than any of these, however, was a kind of <purpose>stewed dumpling</purpose>







called <emph rend="italic">k'ia-mu-k'i&#196;-li-we.</emph> Considerable care was required in the manufacture of these. <ingredient>Fine flour</ingredient> was boiled in <ingredient>water</ingredient> until paste had been formed. Into this paste enough <ingredient>meal</ingredient> was mixed to make a stiff dough, and of this dough little balls or pellets were rolled out and spread evenly over a <implement>yucca sieve</implement> or screen of sticks connected 



 



<pb n="300" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=331"/>







at the ends. A large pot half-filled with <ingredient>water</ingredient> was set over the fire, inside of which a smaller vessel, partially filled with water and weighted with pebbles to keep it steady, was placed. Upon this smaller pot was laid the sieve or screen holding the balls of dough, the larger pot then being covered with a slab of stone and kept boiling until the dumplings were thoroughly cooked by steaming.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>Perhaps belonging to this same class of food, although counted among the delicacies of the Zu&#241;is, was the <emph rend="italic">&#196;'-tea-mu-we,</emph> a kind of <purpose>sweet pudding.</purpose>







It was made of <ingredient>yellow cornmeal,</ingredient> a portion of the batter of which was sweetened either by previous mastication and fermentation or by the admixture of <ingredient>dried flowers.</ingredient> This batter was most dextrously enwrapped in <ingredient>green corn-leaves</ingredient> preserved for the purpose by drying and rendered flexible as occasion required by immersion in <ingredient>hot water.</ingredient> Of necessity these little masses of paste or dough took the form of crescents. They were usually boiled, rarely baked, but in either case were perhaps the sweetest 



 



<pb n="301" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=332"/>







cooked food known to the Zu&#241;is, which heightened sweetness doubtless owed not a little to the succulent corn-leaves.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>Perhaps more complex than any of the hitherto described products of the ancient Zu&#241;i kitchen were the <emph rend="italic">tchu'-tsi-kwah-na-mu'-we.</emph> These were made by hulling <ingredient>corn,</ingredient> then grinding it with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> precisely as colors are ground by artists with oil. This batter, fine and sticky, well seasoned with <ingredient>lime-yeast,</ingredient> was wrapped in <ingredient>broad shucks</ingredient> carefully folded over and tied at the ends, then boiled. The batter was solidified by the boiling and when done resembled to a great extent well-cooked gristle or tough gelatin. Great quantities of these <purpose>rubber-like dumplings</purpose>







were made at a time, as the process of their manufacture was tedious and laborious. When cold they were freshened by roasting on the embers or by baking in the little <implement>hearth-cists</implement> of the kitchen.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>A <purpose>crude kind of batter-cake,</purpose>







yet much of an improvement on the variety before described, the forerunner, doubtless, of the most important breadstuff known to the<pb n="302" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=333"/>







Zu&#241;is today, was made from <ingredient>fine corn flour.</ingredient> This and <ingredient>lime-yeast</ingredient> were mixed together in liberal quantities, <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> enough being added to make a stiff batter, which was boiled until adhesive and pasted or spread over the well-greased, polished <implement>baking-stone</implement> in the corner of the hearth. <variation>Differing from these in being raised with <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> before baking, therefore thicker, and circular in shape, were the <emph rend="italic">k'os-he'-p&#196;-tchi-we,</emph> or <purpose>salt tortillas.</purpose>







The dough of which these were formed was invariably made of <ingredient>very finely ground white corn,</ingredient> so stiff that balls of it might be flattened out on a smooth stone. These round, thin masses of dough, first indented on one side with the tips of the fingers, were laid roughened surface downward on an extremely hot <implement>baking-stone,</implement> meanwhile the other surface being similarly indented. They were then constantly turned until thoroughly done and browned.</variation> <variation>This same dough, minus the yeast, and thinner, like batter, was used to make <purpose>"johnny-cakes" or "corn-dodgers,"</purpose>







which were baked on little flat stones at first well heated, then placed very near a hot fire.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>The rudest forms of true <emph rend="italic">bread</emph> were made by placing in a bowl <ingredient>fine flour,</ingredient> into which enough <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> was poured to make of it dough, and sufficient <ingredient>lime-yeast</ingredient> to leaven it. This was then kneaded and molded into thick cakes, which were set away a short time to rise, after which they were cooked on hot coals by frequent turning, in which form they were called <emph rend="italic">mui'-&#196;-li-we;</emph> <purpose>(fire loaves); or baked, buried deep under hot ashes. In this shape they were known as <emph rend="italic">lu-pan-mu'-lo-ko-na,</emph> or ash-bread,</purpose>







which differed as much from the former as though made from entirely foreign materials. It is needless to say that this bread was also frequently baked, especially for feasts, when it assumed, under the artistic treatment of the Zu&#241;i women, most extraordinary shapes (see the initial illustration), in the large dome-shaped ovens [pl. XIV, XV] or in the little fire-boxes on the tops of the houses.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>We now come to the greatest delicacy in the way of bread known either to the older or the recent Zu&#241;is. In its simplest form it was known as <emph rend="italic">k'os-he-pa-lo-kia,</emph> or <purpose>"salty 



 



<pb n="304" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=337"/>







buried-bread."</purpose>







It was made by the mixture of <emph rend="italic">sa-ko k'o'-ha-na,</emph> or the <ingredient>samp of white corn</ingredient> in <ingredient>water</ingredient> to which enough <ingredient>fine flour</ingredient> of the same <ingredient>corn</ingredient> was added to render the batter very sticky. <ingredient>Broad husks,</ingredient> made pliable with <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> were then laid on a flat stone; the paste spread over them to the thickness of about an inch, covered with more husks folded at the edges to keep the batter in place, covered over with another stone, and so on until a sandwich like that described for "stone-cakes" was built up (pl. XI, <emph rend="italic">c).</emph> Instead of being inclosed in a casing of thicker stones, this was buried in the <implement>hearth-cist</implement>--which had been previously heated almost to redness--then sealed up with mud, and baked by a night-long fire. <variation>Leaving salt out of this recipe and adding to it <ingredient>dried flowers,</ingredient> <ingredient>licorice-root,</ingredient> <ingredient>wild honey,</ingredient> or, more frequently than any of these, <ingredient>masticated and fermented meal,</ingredient> this <purpose>buried bread was made sweet</purpose>







like our own Indian pudding, which it exactly resembled in taste. The latter variety was baked, however, even more slowly, and quite as often cooked in a small <pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=338"/>







<illustration><caption>CLEANING AN OVEN PREPARATORY TO BAKING<lb/>The unbaked loaves are seen near the woman's feet</caption><description>A photograph of a woman baking bread in a small dome-shaped oven.</description></illustration>



 



<pb n="305" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=340"/>







<implement>mush-pot</implement> of earthenware, well lined with <ingredient>husks</ingredient> to keep the batter from adhering to its sides, as between flat stones.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>Perhaps one of the most curious delicacies, for such it was considered, ever known to the Zu&#241;is, was made not by baking, but by freezing. This was called <emph rend="italic">thlem-m&#196;thl-to-we</emph> <purpose>("slab-bread").</purpose>







The plain variety was simply thin mush reduced to paste by boiling, then placed between two stones which were laid in cold places and left until thoroughly frozen. <variation>The unbaked batter of the <emph rend="italic">tchik-k'we'-pa-lo-kia,</emph> or "sweet buried-bread," excessively boiled, then treated in this manner, made what we might call an <purpose>exceedingly coarse ice-cream</purpose>







and certainly prized as highly by these ancients, to say the least, as is the latter delicacy among ourselves.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose>Six varieties of the <emph rend="italic">he'-we</emph> are in common use: the yellow, the blue or green, the red, the white, the brindle or all-color, and the black. They are the <emph rend="italic">bread</emph> of the Zu&#241;is.</purpose>







No meal, however sumptuous, is ever eaten without one or another of them. Most of the colors result from the hues of the corn-grains used. If, for instance, yellow <emph rend="italic">he'-we</emph> be desired, <ingredient>yellow corn</ingredient> exclusively is used for its manufacture. The blue is deepened by the addition of <ingredient>lime-yeast</ingredient> to the <ingredient>meal of blue corn.</ingredient> Green is produced by the equal mixture of <ingredient>blue meal and yellow,</ingredient> and the addition of <ingredient>lime-yeast and ashes.</ingredient> It and the blue are the most constantly used of all varieties. White is made whiter with a little <ingredient>kaolin;</ingredient> black, or rather a sable purple, with <ingredient>certain 



 



<pb n="337" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=374"/>







charred and powdered leaves.</ingredient> The all-color <emph rend="italic">he'-we</emph> is more difficult of production. Six dishes of <ingredient>paste</ingredient> are supplied, each as if prepared for one of the above-named colors. Three of these are cooked (those containing <ingredient>lime or ashes),</ingredient> while the others are left cold. For each sheet of the <emph rend="italic">he'-we</emph> a tiny dip into first one then another of the dishes is made, each dip being dashed upon the stone. A mottled or brindled sheet is the result. The appearance of this, being so far superior to its more substantial qualities that it forms almost its only recommendation, makes it rather unpopular except on stated occasions.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose>Of each variety of <emph rend="italic">he'-we</emph> except the last described, several kinds or grades are made.</purpose>







The thick, <emph rend="italic">he-y&#196;'-ho-ni,</emph> usually eaten warm, is formed of several layers; that is, three or four applications are made co&#235;xtensive with the surface of the stone before the sheet is withdrawn. It is then turned, quickly replaced, and neatly folded while still comparatively moist.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose>The salty, <emph rend="italic">k'os'-he'-we,</emph> is perhaps the most wholesome of all the plain breadstuffs</purpose>







<pb n="338" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=375"/>







of the Zu&#241;is. <ingredient>Salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>lime-yeast</ingredient> are added to the <ingredient>pastes,</ingredient> and a liberal quantity of <ingredient>suet,</ingredient> also salted, rubbed over the stone before baking. When not designed for immediate consumption, this salty <emph rend="italic">he'-we</emph> is rolled into neat little sticks or cylinders corresponding in length to the width of the stone. No bread is lighter or more tempting than these <emph rend="italic">he'-po-lo-lo-we</emph> piled one above the other on the bright wicker-trays in which they are served. <variation><purpose>Another very grateful kind of wafer-bread is the <emph rend="italic">kwi'-k'ia-he'-we,</emph> or milk <emph rend="italic">he'we.</emph></purpose>







In the mixture of the <ingredient>pastes</ingredient> of which this is formed, <ingredient>milk</ingredient> instead of water is used, a food richer to the palate than "cream biscuits" being the result.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>Such of the wafer-bread as is designed for daily use is baked at once in great quantity. The piles of sheets laid one above another are often so high that they look like huge bales of fine wrapping-paper. Partially doubled or folded into masses, which we may call quires, or even reams, they are packed away in permanent half-buried jars provided with close-fitting lids. 



 



<pb n="339" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=376"/>







Thus the moisture is preserved which keeps the <emph rend="italic">he'-we</emph> from crumbling in the fingers as it is eaten, and gives it the peculiar feel and flavor in the mouth which distinguishes it as the most perfect of all known corn-foods. Notwithstanding the care used in storing it, this thin food will, if kept beyond a certain time, become dry and far more flaky than the most delicate pastries. The flakes are carefully preserved together with the crumbs of feasts and the residue from the <implement>bread-trays</implement> of each meal. When a sufficient quantity has accumulated, it is further dried by exposure to heat, then quite finely pulverized with the hands. <purpose>One of the several dishes made from this chipped <emph rend="italic">he'-we</emph> is wafer toast <emph rend="italic">(he'-la-kwi-we).</emph></purpose>







The chips, together with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>untried suet</ingredient> or scraps, are thrown into a <emph rend="italic">thle-mon,</emph> or <implement>earthen toasting-pan,</implement> and stirred until well browned. This, ground on the metate to the condition of coarse meal, forms one of the staple articles of food for long journeys. <variation>Chief among these latter preparations, however, is the same <ingredient>meal of toasted <emph rend="italic">he'-we</emph> chips, ground finer,</ingredient> cooked in part 



 



<pb n="340" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=377"/>







as is the plain cornmeal batter, in other part stirred into <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and a second time baked on the stone. In this condition it is called <purpose>double-done <emph rend="italic">he'-we,</emph> and no longer tastes like the food from which it is thus made over, but rather like the most delicate pie-crust.</purpose>







</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p><purpose>A sweet <emph rend="italic">he'-we (he'-tchi-kwa),</emph> of a bright-red color, and in taste resembling "London sugar wafers," is made from the fine meal of red corn.</purpose>







The cooked portion of the ingredient <ingredient>paste</ingredient> being well boiled in a decoction of <ingredient>red corn-leaves and shoots</ingredient> (plucked earlier in the season and carefully dried for this express purpose), imparts the color and taste which distinguish this from all other kinds of <emph rend="italic">he'-we</emph> heretofore described. <variation>Yet another <emph rend="italic">he'-tchi-kwa</emph> is made by the chewing and fermenting process so often alluded to on former pages. This, while neither very sweet nor bright-colored, possesses a peculiar flavor which is highly regarded by the natives, making it extremely popular on the mornings of feast days. The material of which it is made, quite otherwise baked, is called <purpose>"buried-bread 



 



<pb n="341" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=378"/>







broad <emph rend="italic">he'-we" (he'-k'ia-pa he'-pa'lo-k'ia).</emph></purpose>







Several smooth, thin <implement>baking-stones</implement> are heated and placed within easy reach. Meanwhile the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> is thickly applied to the regular <emph rend="italic">he'-we</emph> stone, each sheet being taken off as soon as it is done enough to hold together, and placed between a couple of the hot baking-slabs. Thus a pile of alternating stones and thick <emph rend="italic">he'-we</emph> sheets is built up to the height of a foot or two, and allowed to stand until the steam, which at first pours out in volumes, begins to disappear. The well-baked and pressed cakes (if we may call them such) which result from this, are quite brittle, although by no means tough when eaten in fresh condition. In the course of time, however, they become very hard, and in common with the dried bits of the ordinary buried-bread, are reduced to fine flour for the use of traveling or hunting parties.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>Sometimes the <ingredient>meal of sweet corn</ingredient> is treated in this or other ways, making a most delicious flour; of which a very little goes a long way toward satisfying hunger. Of all substances known to the Zu&#241;is, 



 



<pb n="342" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=379"/>







however, none approach in nutritive quality the <emph rend="italic">tchu'-k'i-na,</emph> or <purpose>"moistening flour."</purpose>







<ingredient>White or yellow corn</ingredient> is boiled with <ingredient>cob-ashes</ingredient> until the hull may be removed. It is then dried a day or two and well toasted in the <implement>parching pot,</implement> ground to coarse samp, toasted again, ground to very fine flour, and once more toasted, then carefully sifted. Thus manipulated, what with waste and excessive reduction, a bushel of corn makes but a few quarts of flour. A single teaspoonful of this powder when stirred into a <ingredient>pint of water,</ingredient> will make a tolerably thick batter of it; in which condition it is drank, a few sips sufficing to satisfy the most hungry appetite. <variation>When combined with <ingredient>meat-meal, or jerked venison</ingredient> toasted and well ground up with <ingredient>red pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> it embraces all the elements necessary for man's sustenance.</variation> Very rarely, all this too is made the basis of a kind of <emph rend="italic">he'-we;</emph> but as, in the former condition, it may be preserved year in and out, is ever ready for consumption without the intervention of fire, and may be transported in small compass yet in 



 



<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=380"/>







 



<pb n="illustration" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=381"/>







<illustration><caption>SMALL GARDENS AT ZU&#241;I</caption><description>A photograph of several garden plots.</description></illustration>



 



<pb n="343" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=382"/>







sufficient quantity for a long campaign--it rarely gets further than its first stages.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>In big stone bins, or boxes made by setting thin sandstone slabs into and across one end of a small store-room and then 



 



<pb n="372" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=417"/>







cementing them with mud, the <ingredient>wheat</ingredient> is placed. But a small hole through the top of the box is left unsealed. Previously to a feast-day, basketful after basketful of the <purpose>wheat</purpose>







is brought forth and washed in the river. It is then soaked in <ingredient>lukewarm water,</ingredient> and hulled, as soon as it is partially dry, on a coarse metate. When quite dry, it is winnowed over a blanket at the doorway, and the grains are then ground over a full set of the metates, by as many girls



<illustration><caption>FIG. 6-Placing wheat flour in basket bowls.</caption><description>An illustration of a Zu&#241;i women placing flour in baskets.</description></illustration>



 



<pb n="373" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=418"/>







as can be mustered. When the flour leaves the last stone, it is quite fine. After the girls have "eaten and scattered out," you may see the matron of the house packing and piling the flour in snowy mountains far above the rims of the <implement>meal-baskets</implement> (fig. 6). When one of these is "full," that is, heaped up five or six times its own height, the woman unconcernedly picks it off the floor, sets it on her head, and trips away toward the place where it is to be mixed--usually near the fireplace, so that she may work the dough after dark. <variation>Hither she brings the <implement>bread-bowl</implement>--a hemispherical tub, it were better called--and with <ingredient>water, hot and cold,</ingredient> <ingredient>sour yeast</ingredient> (minus the lime), and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> makes up the <emph rend="italic">mo'-tse,</emph> or, as we would name it, <purpose>"sponge."</purpose>







This is allowed to stand near the fireplace until morning.</variation> <variation>While the oven is heating outside, the most buxom young woman of the family, spreading a blanket on the floor and laying near it a large square of white cloth and a round, well-polished <implement>bread-stone,</implement> kneels down and prepares for kneading. Into the <emph rend="italic">mo'-tse</emph> she first pours a quantity of <ingredient>hot 



 



<pb n="374" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=419"/>







tallow,</ingredient> then quickly adding enough <ingredient>fresh flour</ingredient> to stiffen the mass, kneads it excessively by pushing one hand down through



<illustration><caption>Fig. 7 - Kneading wheat bread</caption><description>An illustration of a Zu&#241;i women kneading dough near a fireplace.</description></illustration>



the center of the dough, to the bottom of the bowl, while with the other she pulls or stretches up a quantity from the outer 



 



<pb n="375" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=420"/>







edge, jamming it in turn down the center as she draws the first hand out; and so on alternately (fig. 7), until it all becomes perfectly homogeneous and cohesive. Taking out a little lump of this dough, she wets it, sprinkles it with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> kneads it on the <implement>bread-stone</implement> over and over again, rolls it up into a ball, pats it out flat, turns it over upon itself, greases it well all over, lays it on the white cloth, and pricks it full of holes with a grass straw. Thus is formed the <purpose>ordinary Zu&#241;i loaf.</purpose>







On grand occasions (such as belong properly to the concluding chapter), these forms are fancifully varied. You may see men and women, deer, antelopes, and rabbits, birds, butterflies, sunflowers, and perforated rosettes in effigy, quite artistically modeled, although rather inclined to fatten out of detail by rising. The dough loaves are laid on flat stones or boards, and taken to the oven which has been cleared meanwhile of its fire, swept out and scented with cedar leaves, and passed in by means of a long-handled shovel of pine, usually quite handsomely carved (pl. XI, <emph rend="italic">f).</emph> As soon as the 



 



<pb n="376" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=421"/>







oven is full, the vent-hole at the top is plugged, the doorway closed with a heavy stone and plastered, and the bread left baking for the space of from twenty minutes to half an hour, or under certain circumstances a longer time. Then the stone is taken down and the loaves shoveled out. They are crisp, brown, and very light, having almost doubled in size during the baking. The bread is hearty and nutritious, although inclined to be slightly sour if overleavened.</variation></p>



<p><variation>Some of the dough used for a bread-making is always reserved and made up into <purpose>flat cakes</purpose>







like those of corn flour described in an earlier chapter as <emph rend="italic">he-'pa-tchi-we,</emph> or tortillas.</variation> <variation>By the addition of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>shortening,</ingredient> a sort of <purpose>unsweetened cake,</purpose>







very grateful and rich, is made in the same way.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>A most excellent <purpose>fried cake called <emph rend="italic">mu'-tsi-k'o-we,</emph> or "contorted cakes,"</purpose>







and the only impromptu wheat-food known to the Zu&#241;is, is made of simple <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> worked into stiff dough, flattened and stretched into thin, round patties, and immersed 



 



<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=422"/>







 



<pb n="illustration" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=423"/>







<illustration><caption>CULTIVATING THE GARDEN<lb/>A pail of water and a gourd dipper for irrigating are seen</caption><description>A photograph of a cultivated field.</description></illustration>



 



<pb n="377" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=424"/>







a minute or two in <ingredient>boiling suet.</ingredient> Brown as pie-crust and crisp as <emph rend="italic">he'-we,</emph> these twisted and shriveled little cakes formed my favorite luxury during that extended period throughout which I was required to "change my flesh, that I might indeed, become of the <emph rend="italic">blood of Zu&#241;i."</emph></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>"They make a great deal of flour at once; <purpose>to make bread</purpose>







they mix this with <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> and make a dough which resembles the cakes called <emph rend="italic">oblis.</emph> They collect a great quantity of <ingredient>herbs,</ingredient> and when they are 



 



<pb n="390" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=437"/>







quite dry they use them all the year in cooking their food."<ref target="n32" height="superscript">32</ref></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p>"The old grandmother, surprised with his knowledge, turned away, took the halves of the huge <purpose>deer carcass,</purpose>







and hung them from loom-loops on the rafters. She spread the skin out on the floor--wondering at its bigness--sprinkled it with <ingredient>ashes,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and rolled it up. Then she told the young man how he should soak it in the river next day, denude it of hair by means of a big <implement>bone scraper</implement> (that had belonged to his uncle) and dress it. Before she began to cut up the <ingredient>deer,</ingredient> she drew the sinew cords from its back, scraped them flat, and hung them on a ladder-round to dry, telling the youth how he should sew 



 



<pb n="432" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=483"/>







the skin with them into fine garments after it was dressed and whitened. Gradually, while still with the chatter of age she talked on, he grew sleepy, and stretching himself out by the hearth, fell asleep. Until late into the night, however, the old woman continued to hack the joints and cut the meat into thin strips and hang it on cords to dry, singing meanwhile the songs she had known when the boy's uncle had been a great hunter.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame" class2="accompaniments">



<p>Piled high on more than one flat <implement>basket-tray</implement> (pl. xxvii, <emph rend="italic">a, d)</emph> are the sheets and rolls of paper-bread or <emph rend="italic">he'-we</emph>--the sheets dully symbolizing the green earth and blue sky 



 



<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=613"/>







 



<pb n="illustration" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=614"/>







<illustration><caption>VARIETIES OF COOKED FOODS</caption><description>An illustration of twelve different types of Zu&#241;i food.</description></illustration>



 



<pb n="557" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=615"/>







in their colors; the rolls, not less, the six chief hues of the rainbow. On special occasions these bulky wafers are reinforced by one or two deep <implement>basket-bowls</implement> of puffy, double-lobed wheaten loaves like overgrown bakers' rolls (fig. <emph rend="italic">a</emph>), but browner and thicker-skinned outside, light-buff and porous, coarse-grained, yet quite as spongy, within. Then there are the <emph rend="italic">tchu'-tsi-kwah-na-mu-we,</emph> or "skinned-corn-paste-loaves,: neatly done up, like druggists' packets, in wrappers of corn-husk (fig. <emph rend="italic">i</emph>); and if not further like drugs, medicinal, still, like them again in that they are certainly good medicine for the disease of hunger; best, however, when that disease is acutest. Partaking somewhat of the nature of these latter (for they are well done up and cooked by boiling) are the crescent-shaped, soft, sweet; and sticky <emph rend="italic">&#226;'-te-a-mu-we </emph> (fig. <emph rend="italic">b),</emph> bright in their twisted envelopes of green corn-leaves, yet as yellow inside of this exterior as the squash-blossoms with which they have been seasoned. Neither less yellow, less sticky, nor less a delicacy, although decidedly 



 



<pb n="558" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=616"/>







less sweet and more saline, like overdone "Indian pudding" in which salt has gained mastery over the molasses, is the <emph rend="italic">k'os'-he-pa-lo-k'ia </emph>in its sooty, unsteady, little cooking-pot with its rim of upturned, rather singed corn-shucks (fig. <emph rend="italic">h</emph>). Capping this feast in their resistless, yea relentless, attractiveness to the Zu&#241;i palate, are the husk-beswathed slabs of red <emph rend="italic">he'-pa-lo-k'ia</emph> (fig. <emph rend="italic">c).</emph> Nor is there lack of more solid foods; for, could such a stuff as green syrup with gigantic pills of "blue-mass" floating about in it, be readily imagined, I would ask my readers to kindly draw such a pleasing picture, the more vividly to realize the appearance of the big bowl of <emph rend="italic">mu'-k'i&#196;-li-we,</emph> or dumpling soup, than he will by merely examining fig. <emph rend="italic">f.</emph> This bowl of slimy breadstuff swelters, but does not out-steam; the equally generous trencher of stewed meat-joints and toasted hominy (fig. <emph rend="italic">e</emph>) which stands beside it in the middle of this oval array. Of all dishes most indispensable to Zu&#241;i dinners, this over-seethed, vastly rich and greasy, vermilion-colored, pepper-scummed, diabolical <emph rend="italic">olla</emph> 



 



<pb n="559" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=617"/>







<emph rend="italic">podrida,</emph> ranks next to the universal <emph rend="italic">he'-we.</emph> No wonder that within convenient reach of it, tilted up over a primitive plate of sandstone, is a <implement>skewer</implement> of broiled meat-shreds; or, more often, a spindle of suet and tidbit-stuffed sheep-intestines (fig. <emph rend="italic">j),</emph> browned to brittleness at the periphery but somewhat underdone toward the center. This dietic bobbin, however hot and reeking, must be, if one would have it relish at its best, returned to the coals repeatedly, during its unwinding course at a long dinner. <variation>On another sandstone plate lies the <purpose>blood-pudding,</purpose>







composed of <ingredient>chopped liver,</ingredient> <ingredient>lights,</ingredient> <ingredient>suet,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>coarse browned meal,</ingredient> <ingredient>brains,</ingredient> and <ingredient>clotted blood,</ingredient> rammed into a <ingredient>large intestine</ingredient> and baked or boiled until, what with swelling and congealing when allowed to grow cold, it looks like a hugely distended Bologna sausage, and tastes like unspiced head-cheese. Less digestible, moreover, it certainly is not.</variation> <variation>In the nature of <emph rend="italic">entr&#233;es</emph> are other preparations precisely like this last in outward appearance (fig. <emph rend="italic">k).</emph> A typical one of these is the same kind of <purpose>large intestines 



 



<pb n="560" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=618"/>







stuffed with its own half-digested contents,</purpose>







thoroughly enhanced by the liberal addition of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>red pepper,</ingredient> and <ingredient>parched meal,</ingredient> then roasted for three hours or more to solidity and shining brownness in front of a raging fire of embers.</variation> Most unprepossessing in its semblance is this unassimilated meal of some sheep or roebuck; but to the vegetable-famished Zu&#241;i (no less than it proved to my own taste after a preliminary training of some months in the native dietary) it is a most grateful change, a promoter of appetite, and an excellent digester of some of the poisons above catalogued. <variation><purpose>A really superior sauce or condiment--</purpose>







never absent from luncheons and rarely so from other meals--at least in the height of the chile season, is the <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>coriander-leaf,</ingredient> and <ingredient>water paste,</ingredient> served in the lava-stone trough in which it has been freshly macerated and crushed (fig. <emph rend="italic">g</emph>).</variation> Save that it completes the list of our illustrations (fig. <emph rend="italic">l</emph>) there would be no need to mention the ever-present jar or earthen box of salt and chile-colorado or red-pepper meal--which (having been toasted) looks and 



 



<pb n="561" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=619"/>







smells like snuff; but tastes like the wrong end of a lighted cigarette (until you get used to it)!</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">



<p>The dishes already described are but the repastorial bulwarks of Zu&#241;i; for in addition to them one may frequently see <purpose>corn, sweet or common, cooked on the cob</purpose>







in the various ways long ago mentioned; <variation>either <purpose>stewed beans,</purpose>







or <ingredient>beans in large bunches (pods and all)</ingredient> boiled until soft, and eaten as asparagus is eaten;</variation> fried, roasted, or baked squash; boiled pumpkin; <variation><purpose>snaky coils of desiccated melon strips--</purpose>







simmered with or without <ingredient>dried peaches,</ingredient> or the <ingredient>peaches stewed without the melon strips,</ingredient> both sweet without sugaring;</variation> greens made from water-cress or young milkweed pods; small game, served with a rich gravy of squash-seed meal, and often the grinning, pop-eyed heads of larger game or domesticated animals, buried over night in a fire-surmounted cist of stone, and black as the sable of a dead coal from the singeing they have thereby been subjected to. <variation>The ears, hoofs, and tails of deer, antelope, and cattle, first scorched in a blazing fire, then boiled 



 



<pb n="562" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=620"/>







a day or two, also show up at the larger Zu&#241;i dinners in the shape of <purpose>thick gelatinous soups.</purpose>







</variation> <variation>Finally, most curious of all the eatables of these motly meals, are <purpose>parched locust-chrysalides, or <emph rend="italic">chum'-al-li.</emph></purpose>







These incipient, though active insects are industriously dug in great numbers from the sandy soil of the ca&#241;on woodlands, by the women, who go forth to their lowly chase, like berry-pickers, in merry shoals. They are then confined in little lobe-shaped cages of wicker, brought home toward evening, and at once both cleaned and "fattened," by immersion over night in <ingredient>warmish water,</ingredient> of which, if they be a lively lot, they absorb so much as to increase in individual bulk before morning to more than twice their natural size. Then they are taken out and treated to a <ingredient>hot bath in melted tallow,</ingredient> which causes them to roll up and die, after which they are salted and parched as corn is, in an <implement>earthen toasting-pot,</implement> over a hot--very hot--fire.</variation></p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p>The Indians now began to prepare our first meal. One of the <purpose>rabbits</purpose>







they threw into the middle of the blazing fire, where almost instantly the hair and parts of the skin were singed off. When the carcass looked more like a cinder than the body of an animal, it was hauled forth, and with a few dextrous turns of Kesh'-pa-he's hand, divested of its charred skin as a nut would be of its shuck--then dressed, spread out on a <implement>skewer,</implement> spitted, and set up slantingly, to take care of itself for a while before a thick bed of embers.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="breadsweets">



<p>From the basket-bottle some <ingredient>water</ingredient> was poured into our cooking-pot, and when it had begun to boil violently, some <ingredient>coarse meal</ingredient> was briskly stirred in. Before this had quite become mush, while still sticky and quite thin, that is, some of it was 



 



<pb n="595" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=653"/>







poured out on a stone, some <ingredient>dry meal</ingredient> thoroughly kneaded into it, and the whole ingeniously wrapped or plastered around the end of a long stick. This stick, like the rabbit spit, was then set up slantingly over the coals and occasionally turned until considerably swollen, and browned to a nicety. Behold a fine <purpose>loaf of exceedingly well-done--and as I afterward found--also exceedingly good-tasting corn-bread!</purpose>







</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="beverages">



<p>The bowl of <ingredient>snow-water</ingredient> was removed from its place under the stone, and into it was stirred some <emph rend="italic">tchu'-k'i-na-o-we</emph>--just enough to <purpose>make a cream-like fluid to serve as our beverage,</purpose>







and on the upturned sides of our saddle skins, in the light and warmth of our genial fire, our meal was at last spread out. The rabbit carcass, delicately cooked as ever was game at Delmonico's, the mush in the kettle it had been boiled in, the bread on the stick it had been baked around, and the one good-sized bowl of <emph rend="italic">tchu'-k'i-na-o-we</emph> broth in our midst, we all sat down, made our sacrifices to the gods, and ate as only hungry travelers can eat, enjoying our food as only hunters and 



 



<pb n="596" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=654"/>







husbandmen are privileged to enjoy the fruits of their labors.</p>



</recipe>



<recipe class1="meatfishgame">



<p>"They're in!" called out Kesh'-pa-he excitedly; and forthwith the flexible sappling probe was introduced, twirled a few times, and withdrawn, two squirming, staring-eyed rats well twisted to its end, and another prodding brought out one more. The rats were choked <emph rend="italic">en route</emph> to our camp, and, perhaps a little too soon for their own comfort, thrown into a bed of embers, where, after roasting a few moments, they bloated up into oblong balls, became divested of their tails, legs, ears, <alt synonym1="whiskers?">winkers,</alt> and all other irregularities, and when pulled from the fire, looked like roasted potatoes overdone. They were "shucked" in a twinkling--came out clean and white except for a greenish tendency of what were once their under-sides--and were forthwith mashed into pulp between two stones--meat, bones, visceral 



 



<pb n="600" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=zuni&#38;PageNum=658"/>







contents, and all, and stirred into about a pint of <ingredient>salt and water.</ingredient> Thus concocted was the <purpose>"rat-brine:"</purpose>







green in color, semi-fluid, and meaty in taste (for they made me eat some of it, I do not regret to say), and very aromatic in flavor, a quality which the rats derive from the trees in which they live and on the berries and leaves of which they feed. Disgusting indeed would this delicacy of the hunter be, were the wood-rat of the Southwest anything like his various Eastern representatives and congeners; but he is not. He lives on but one or two kinds of food all his life, and the peculiar flavor of the sauce made from him is due to the way in which--visceral contents and all--he is worked up into "rat-brine."</p>



</recipe>



